(this.webpackJsonpyds=this.webpackJsonpyds||[]).push([[0],{23:function(e,t,a){e.exports=a(37)},28:function(e,t,a){},31:function(e,t,a){},35:function(e,t,a){},36:function(e,t,a){},37:function(e,t,a){"use strict";a.r(t);var i=a(0),o=a.n(i),n=a(15),s=a.n(n),r=a(8),h=(a(28),a(12)),l=a(6),c=(a(31),function(e){var t=e.exams;return o.a.createElement("div",{className:"homepage"},o.a.createElement("ul",null,o.a.createElement("li",null,o.a.createElement(r.b,{to:"/"},"Home")),t.map((function(e){return o.a.createElement("li",{key:"".concat(e)},o.a.createElement(r.b,{to:"".concat(e)},e.split("-").join(" ")," Exam"))}))))}),d=a(18),u=a(19),m=a(21),p=a(20),f=a(22),g=(a(35),function(e){function t(e){var a;Object(d.a)(this,t),(a=Object(m.a)(this,Object(p.a)(t).call(this,e))).generateRandomNumber=function(e){return parseInt(Math.random()*e)},a.generateRandomColor=function(){for(var e=a.generateRandomNumber(16777215).toString(16),t=e.length,i=0;i<t;i++)t<6&&(e=0+e,t++);return"#"+e},a.handleClick=function(){var e=a.state.data[a.state.randomSectionIndex].questions,t=a.state.randomSectionIndex,i=a.state.randomQuestionIndex,o=document.getElementsByTagName("body")[0],n=a.generateRandomColor();t+1>=a.state.data.length&&i+1>=e.length?(i=0,t=0):i+1>=e.length?(i=0,t+=1):i+=1,a.setState({textColor:"white"}),o.style.backgroundColor="white",setTimeout((function(){a.setState({randomSectionIndex:t,randomQuestionIndex:i,showSolution:!1,textColor:"black"}),o.style.backgroundColor=n}),500)},a.showSolution=function(){a.setState({showSolution:!0})};return a.state={data:e.questions,randomSectionIndex:0,randomQuestionIndex:0,showSolution:!1,textColor:"black"},a}return Object(f.a)(t,e),Object(u.a)(t,[{key:"componentDidMount",value:function(){var e=document.getElementsByTagName("body")[0],t=this.generateRandomColor();e.style.backgroundColor=t}},{key:"render",value:function(){var e=this,t=this.state.data[this.state.randomSectionIndex],a=t.directions,i=t.text,n=t.questions[this.state.randomQuestionIndex],s=n.number,r=n.answer,h=n.question,l=n.choices,c=h.includes("\n");return o.a.createElement("div",{className:"container"},o.a.createElement("h3",{className:"text-transition",style:{color:this.state.textColor}},s,") Directions: ",a),c?o.a.createElement("p",{className:"text-transition",style:{color:this.state.textColor},dangerouslySetInnerHTML:{__html:h.replace(/\n/g,"<br/>")}}):void 0!==i?o.a.createElement("div",{className:"text-transition",style:{color:this.state.textColor}},o.a.createElement("p",null,i),o.a.createElement("h3",null,h)):o.a.createElement("h3",{className:"text-transition",style:{color:this.state.textColor}},h),l.map((function(t,a){return o.a.createElement("li",{key:a,className:"text-transition",style:{color:e.state.textColor}},t)})),o.a.createElement("span",{className:this.state.showSolution?"active solution":"not-active solution"},"Answer: ",l[r]),o.a.createElement("div",{className:"center-content"},o.a.createElement("button",{className:"btn",onClick:this.showSolution},"Show Solution"),o.a.createElement("button",{className:"btn",onClick:this.handleClick},"New Question")))}}]),t}(i.Component)),b=(a(36),[{routeName:"2018-Fall",items:[{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the space.",questions:[{number:1,answer:3,question:"For smokers who are under increased pressure to give up smoking, one of the easiest ---- is that quitting smoking makes people more likely to put on weight.",choices:["incentives","attempts","purposes","excuses","features"]},{number:2,answer:3,question:"The primary ---- of an organisation\u2019s accounting department are to process financial information and to prepare financial statements at the end of the accounting period.",choices:["advancements","compensations","obstacles","objectives","classifications"]},{number:3,answer:0,question:"Scholars and historians have offered possible locations for the mythical island Atlantis, even in the face of ---- scientific evidence that it does not exist.",choices:["compelling","doubtful","erroneous","refutable","ambiguous"]},{number:4,answer:1,question:"The Big Bang theory is the explanation most commonly ---- by astronomers for the origin of the universe.",choices:["discovered","accepted","regulated","conducted","influenced"]},{number:5,answer:3,question:"The relationship between sport and aggression has been studied ---- for decades, yet researchers still have a limited understanding of the link between the two.",choices:["severely","suspiciously","uniquely","extensively","instantly"]},{number:6,answer:1,question:"Sense of control refers to the degree to which people believe that they can deliberately ---- desired outcomes and avoid undesirable ones in their environment.",choices:["fill out","bring about","switch off","turn down","hand over"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word(s) or expression(s) to fill the space(s).",questions:[{number:7,answer:2,question:"For a long time, scientists ---- aware that the Earth\u2019s atmosphere is not static, but is in constant motion, producing areas of ever-changing pressure around the globe, but from 1700 onward, scientists ---- to discover how and why large-scale atmospheric movements occur.",choices:["had been / have begun","would have been / had begun","have been / began","would be / were beginning","were / would have begun"]},{number:8,answer:4,question:"Science ---- our every question, but it ---- humanity\u2019s best tool yet for tackling our greatest challenges.",choices:["may not answer / had remained","must not answer / has remained","should not answer / will remain","cannot answer / remained","might not answer / remains"]},{number:9,answer:4,question:"Five of the Solomon Islands ---- whole by rising sea levels, ---- a glimpse into the future of other low-lying nations, such as the Netherlands and Italy.",choices:["are being swallowed / having offered","had been swallowed / being offered","will be swallowed / having been offered","were swallowed / offered","have been swallowed / offering"]},{number:10,answer:1,question:"Research ---- media has primarily examined the effects of media on children ---- a developmental perspective with a psychological focus on the correlation or causal variables between the media and children\u2019s behaviour.",choices:["against / under","through / across","at / over","on / from ","in / beyond"]},{number:11,answer:3,question:"Identifying the specific effects of beneficial microbes that thrive ---- the surface of our bodies and deep ---- our tissues, researchers are gaining a new view of how our bodies function.",choices:["at / over","in / along","by / down","on / within","from / through"]},{number:12,answer:2,question:"Most cheesemakers believe that the brilliant nuances of flavour found in raw milk, with its naturally present \u2018good\u2019 bacteria, simply cannot be duplicated in a pasteurised milk cheese ---- some well-respected cheeses, including British Stilton, are made only from pasteurised milk.",choices:["now that","after","although","because","only if"]},{number:13,answer:4,question:"Surprisingly, the symbol for zero emerged later than the concepts for other numbers, and ---- the Babylonians used a symbol for zero, it was merely a placeholder and not used for computational purposes.",choices:["just as","as if","in case","because","even though"]},{number:14,answer:1,question:"Studies have found that the effects of a cup of coffee or a glass of cola are noticeable after just 10 minutes ---- the peak caffeine concentration in the blood occurs after 45 minutes.",choices:["since","but","provided that","as long as","unless"]},{number:15,answer:2,question:"Animals are hunted by humans ---- for their meat ---- for parts of their bodies that are used to create medicines, clothes, and jewellery.",choices:["neither / nor","such / that","not only / but also","the more / the more","as / as"]},{number:16,answer:2,question:"---- its notoriety as a naval weapon, the first modern torpedo was developed in landlocked Austria, or rather in what was then the Austrian Empire stretching down to the Adriatic.",choices:["Along with","In terms of","Despite","Due to","Instead of"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:'Sometimes when people assert that a language has no grammar, what they really mean is that there is no grammar book for that particular language. But the rules of a language ---- in the heads of speakers of that language. We know the rules are there ---- the way the speakers behave. They use similar structures ---- similar events. If you hear the sentence for "Give me some water." in a rarely spoken language such as Spelitzian, you can be pretty sure you can use the same pattern for "Give me some food.", ---- there are other possible patterns as well. If there were not any patterns, people would not be able to communicate because they would have no way of knowing what other people meant ----.',questions:[{number:17,answer:4,question:"But the rules of a language ---- in the heads of speakers of that language.",choices:["alter","recover","endure","apply","exist"]},{number:18,answer:0,question:"We know the rules are there ---- the way the speakers behave.",choices:["because of","despite","contrary to","instead of","similar to"]},{number:19,answer:3,question:"They use similar structures ---- similar events.",choices:["against","on","from","for","into"]},{number:20,answer:4,question:'If you hear the sentence for "Give me some water." in a rarely spoken language such as Spelitzian, you can be pretty sure you can use the same pattern for "Give me some food.", ---- there are other possible patterns as well.',choices:["provided","once","in case","because","even if"]},{number:21,answer:1,question:"If there were not any patterns, people would not be able to communicate because they would have no way of knowing what other people meant ----.",choices:["saying","to say","having said","being said","to have been said"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:"An electric car future is speeding closer \u2013 economic analysts project that a third of all automobiles could be battery-powered by 2040. Most of these vehicles ---- large lithium batteries, which prompts worries about whether the world\u2019s lithium supply can keep up. ----, another element, cobalt, is a bigger concern. The best lithium battery cathodes (negative electrodes) all contain cobalt, and its production is limited. Even with a very conservative estimate of 10 million electric vehicles (EVs) in 2025, the demand ---- cobalt that year could reach 330,000 metric tons, whereas the available supply at that time would be at most 290,000 metric tons. Recycling lithium batteries is complicated and rarely done. Even with higher rates and cheaper processes, recycling ---- the use of lithium batteries until 10 or more years after mass-market penetration of EVs. But newer cathode chemistries offer hope. ---- recently developed nickel-rich and cobalt-free formulations, cobalt demand may decline.",questions:[{number:22,answer:1,question:"Most of these vehicles ---- large lithium batteries, which prompts worries about whether the world\u2019s lithium supply can keep up.",choices:["call off","rely on","take in","go through","cut down"]},{number:23,answer:3,question:"----, another element, cobalt, is a bigger concern.",choices:["Consequently","In conclusion","At least","However","Otherwise"]},{number:24,answer:0,question:"The best lithium battery cathodes (negative electrodes) all contain cobalt, and its production is limited. Even with a very conservative estimate of 10 million electric vehicles (EVs) in 2025, the demand ---- cobalt that year could reach 330,000 metric tons, whereas the available supply at that time would be at most 290,000 metric tons.",choices:["for","into","about","from","to"]},{number:25,answer:1,question:"Even with higher rates and cheaper processes, recycling ---- the use of lithium batteries until 10 or more years after mass-market penetration of EVs.",choices:["has not reduced","will not reduce","does not reduce","did not reduce","is not reducing"]},{number:26,answer:4,question:"---- recently developed nickel-rich and cobalt-free formulations, cobalt demand may decline.",choices:["Rather than","Similar to","In comparison with","As opposed to","Thanks to"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the given sentence.",questions:[{number:27,answer:1,question:"----, but the creation of genetic techniques to safely halt or reverse age-related conditions in humans has so far proven improbable.",choices:["Some researchers have doubts whether a new genetic technique could be developed as a first step towards the medical world\u2019s fabled \u2018elixir of youth\u2019","It has long been known that manipulating certain genes in an organism can slow ageing and extend its lifespan","More proof will be needed before new genetic treatments using stem cells can be promoted as the key to turning back the clock on old age","Ageing of the body is a dynamic process, as often reported by a number of researchers","The efficacy of new methods utilised to prevent ageing is still questionable"]},{number:28,answer:3,question:"Because bodybuilders exert large amounts of energy, ----.",choices:["they are judged on the physical appearance of their muscles and encouraged to focus on body image","they try to achieve the body type that will help them be effective competitors in their sport","bodybuilding is the development of the physique through exercise, often for competitive exhibition","their metabolism generally requires more calories per day than the average person","bodybuilding is an activity that includes weight training in order to build muscle mass"]},{number:29,answer:2,question:"While people can generally cough voluntarily, ----.",choices:["infectious viruses can be easily transmitted between individuals through coughing","most people cough once or twice an hour during the day to clear irritants off the airway","environmental pollutants, such as cigarette smoke and dust, can also cause a cough","the cough that accompanies a cold usually lasts one to two weeks","vitamins and minerals may be helpful in treating conditions that lead to coughs"]},{number:30,answer:0,question:"When mental disorders, physical conditions, and functional decline co-occur, ----.",choices:["older adults face a greatly increased risk of hospitalisation and placement in long-term care facilities","some older adults have been found to be relatively active well into their 80s and 90s","it is important to note that older adults vary substantially in terms of their physical and mental health","physical decline is associated with causing a number of mental disorders among older adults","mental health problems such as depression are not a natural consequence of growing older"]},{number:31,answer:3,question:"Unless there are substantial changes in the ways that humans affect ecosystems, ----.",choices:["we have already caused permanent losses in global biodiversity","our knowledge of Earth\u2019s species is still incomplete","there could be as many as 30-50 million species on Earth","there will be much larger losses of biodiversity in the near future","the scale by which we consider biodiversity ranges from local to global"]},{number:32,answer:2,question:"----, our very lives depend on it to sustain agriculture and to keep our bodies healthy.",choices:["Since scientists have long struggled to comprehend the complexities of the weather","Just as the Earth\u2019s atmosphere would remain stagnant without weather","While cold weather might cause us discomfort or even more severe health conditions","Given that humanity has, indeed, changed the weather","If predicting the weather is still, in many ways, a haphazard occupation"]},{number:33,answer:3,question:"----, the nations of Europe raced to colonise the continent.",choices:["Given that almost all European interaction with Africa took place along the coasts until the 18th century","Because African responses to the challenge of European imperialism were complex","Even if colonial administrations enticed or coerced Africans into producing goods for export","When technological advances made Africa\u2019s interior readily accessible in the late 19th century","Despite several factors that drove the European scramble for Africa in the 18th century"]},{number:34,answer:2,question:"----, the Romans became the first major society to wear seasonal clothing.",choices:["Although Romans were very careful about the way they dressed","As most of what we know about Roman clothing comes from written sources","Because their empire grew so great and took them into very different climates","Even if Romans made warm winter boots and the first known raincoat","Whereas wealthy Romans had slaves to help choose their clothing"]},{number:35,answer:2,question:"----, the ethnic characteristics and traditions of the Balkan Peninsula\u2019s food culture have been well preserved.",choices:["Provided that it displays both Asian and western European influences","Even if meat might not have played a central role in the past","Even though the eastern influence has been very strong in the last several centuries","As long as its food culture is shaped by the historic, social and climatic elements","While the use of numerous spices constitutes the basics of its cuisine"]},{number:36,answer:3,question:"The Sung dynasty Chinese (AD 960-1279) had the technology to make rockets, ----.",choices:["so the first European picture of a rocket was made in 1400","thus it was occasionally used as a weapon by Europeans","because the earliest European recipe for black powder appeared in 1265","but there is no definitive evidence that they did so","as the origin of the rocket is shrouded in mystery"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the most accurate Turkish translation of the sentences in English, and the most accurate English translation of the sentences in Turkish.",questions:[{number:37,answer:3,question:"Intelligence, which has been open to a range of definitions due to its abstract nature and thus has become a controversial topic, is usually regarded as a measure of cognitive skills and the ability to solve problems.",choices:["C\u0327og\u0306unlukla bilis\u0327sel becerilerin ve problem c\u0327o\u0308zme yeteneg\u0306inin bir o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308tu\u0308 olarak go\u0308ru\u0308len zeka\u0302, soyut dog\u0306as\u0131ndan o\u0308tu\u0308ru\u0308 bir dizi tan\u0131ma ac\u0327\u0131k oldug\u0306u ic\u0327in tart\u0131s\u0327mal\u0131 bir konu ha\u0302line gelmis\u0327tir.","Zeka\u0302, soyut dog\u0306as\u0131 gereg\u0306i bir dizi tan\u0131ma ac\u0327\u0131k","olup tart\u0131s\u0327mal\u0131 bir konu ha\u0302line gelse de genellikle bilis\u0327sel becerilerin ve problem c\u0327o\u0308zme yeteneg\u0306inin bir o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308tu\u0308 olarak go\u0308ru\u0308lmektedir.","Genellikle bilis\u0327sel becerilerin ve problem c\u0327o\u0308zme yeteneg\u0306inin bir o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308tu\u0308 olarak go\u0308ru\u0308len zeka\u0302n\u0131n soyut dog\u0306as\u0131 nedeniyle bir dizi tan\u0131ma ac\u0327\u0131k olmas\u0131, onu tart\u0131s\u0327\u0131lan bir konu ha\u0302line getirmis\u0327tir.","Soyut dog\u0306as\u0131ndan o\u0308tu\u0308ru\u0308 bir dizi tan\u0131ma ac\u0327\u0131k olan ve bu yu\u0308zden tart\u0131s\u0327mal\u0131 bir konu ha\u0302line gelen zeka\u0302, genellikle bilis\u0327sel becerilerin ve problem c\u0327o\u0308zme yeteneg\u0306inin bir o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308tu\u0308 olarak go\u0308ru\u0308lmektedir.","Zeka\u0302 c\u0327og\u0306u zaman bilis\u0327sel becerilerin ve problem c\u0327o\u0308zme yeteneg\u0306inin bir o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308tu\u0308 olarak go\u0308ru\u0308lmu\u0308s\u0327, soyut dog\u0306as\u0131 gereg\u0306i bir dizi tan\u0131ma ac\u0327\u0131k olmus\u0327 ve bundan dolay\u0131 tart\u0131s\u0327mal\u0131 bir konu ha\u0302line gelmis\u0327tir."]},{number:38,answer:2,question:"World War I was supposed to be the war to end all wars, but defeated countries were faced with harsh peace terms, which led to the outbreak of World War II.",choices:["I. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n tu\u0308m savas\u0327lara son verecek savas\u0327 olacag\u0306\u0131 du\u0308s\u0327u\u0308nu\u0308lu\u0308yordu, fakat yenilen u\u0308lkelerin ag\u0306\u0131r bar\u0131s\u0327 kos\u0327ullar\u0131yla kars\u0327\u0131 kars\u0327\u0131ya kalmas\u0131 sonucunda","II. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131 gerc\u0327ekles\u0327ti.","Tu\u0308m savas\u0327lara son verecek savas\u0327 olacag\u0306\u0131 zannedilen I. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019nda yenilen u\u0308lkeler ag\u0306\u0131r bar\u0131s\u0327 kos\u0327ullar\u0131yla kars\u0327\u0131 kars\u0327\u0131ya kald\u0131 ve bu durum II. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n ortaya c\u0327\u0131kmas\u0131na neden oldu.","I. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n tu\u0308m savas\u0327lar\u0131 sona erdirecek savas\u0327 olacag\u0306\u0131 zannediliyordu, ancak yenilen u\u0308lkeler ag\u0306\u0131r bar\u0131s\u0327 kos\u0327ullar\u0131yla kars\u0327\u0131 kars\u0327\u0131ya kald\u0131, ki bu da II. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n ortaya c\u0327\u0131kmas\u0131na neden oldu.","II. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n gerc\u0327ekles\u0327mesine neden olan s\u0327ey, I. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n tu\u0308m savas\u0327lara son verecek savas\u0327 olacag\u0306\u0131n\u0131n du\u0308s\u0327u\u0308nu\u0308lmesine rag\u0306men yenilen u\u0308lkelerin ag\u0306\u0131r bar\u0131s\u0327 kos\u0327ullar\u0131yla kars\u0327\u0131 kars\u0327\u0131ya kalmas\u0131yd\u0131.","I. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n tu\u0308m savas\u0327lar\u0131 sona erdirecek savas\u0327 olacag\u0306\u0131na inan\u0131lsa da yenilen u\u0308lkelerin ag\u0306\u0131r bar\u0131s\u0327 kos\u0327ullar\u0131yla kars\u0327\u0131 kars\u0327\u0131ya kalmas\u0131, II. Du\u0308nya Savas\u0327\u0131\u2019n\u0131n ortaya c\u0327\u0131kmas\u0131na neden oldu."]},{number:39,answer:2,question:"Today\u2019s urban developments, coupled with an increasing population, threaten many archaeological sites in Egypt.",choices:["Gu\u0308nu\u0308mu\u0308zdeki kentsel gelis\u0327meler, nu\u0308fus art\u0131s\u0327\u0131n\u0131n da etkisiyle birlikte, M\u0131s\u0131r\u2019daki birc\u0327ok arkeolojik alan ic\u0327in tehdit olus\u0327turmaktad\u0131r.","M\u0131s\u0131r\u2019daki birc\u0327ok arkeolojik alan, gu\u0308nu\u0308mu\u0308zdeki kentsel gelis\u0327meler ve artmakta olan nu\u0308fus yu\u0308zu\u0308nden tehdit alt\u0131ndad\u0131r.","Gu\u0308nu\u0308mu\u0308zdeki kentsel gelis\u0327meler, artmakta olan nu\u0308fusla birlikte, M\u0131s\u0131r\u2019daki birc\u0327ok arkeolojik alan\u0131 tehdit etmektedir.","Gu\u0308nu\u0308mu\u0308zdeki kentsel gelis\u0327meler, nu\u0308fus art\u0131s\u0327\u0131n\u0131 beraberinde getirerek M\u0131s\u0131r\u2019daki birc\u0327ok arkeolojik alan ic\u0327in tehdit olus\u0327turmaktad\u0131r.","Gu\u0308nu\u0308mu\u0308zdeki kentsel gelis\u0327melerin artmakta olan nu\u0308fusla desteklenmesi, M\u0131s\u0131rda`ki birc\u0327ok arkeolojik alan\u0131 tehdit etmektedir."]},{number:40,answer:4,question:"Makro fotog\u0306rafc\u0327\u0131l\u0131g\u0306\u0131n en o\u0308nemli tekniklerini kes\u0327fetmek ic\u0327in, fotog\u0306rafc\u0327\u0131lar bir bahc\u0327ede \u0131s\u0327\u0131k ve konumla c\u0327al\u0131s\u0327mal\u0131 ve ufak hareketlerle arka plan\u0131n nas\u0131l deg\u0306is\u0327tig\u0306ini fark etmelidir.",choices:["The key techniques of macro photography include working with light and position in a garden, through which photographers can notice how the background changes with slight moves.","Discovering the key techniques of macro photography requires photographers to work with light and position in a garden and to notice how the background changes with their slight moves.","To notice the key techniques of macro photography, photographers may work with light and position in","a garden and discover how the background changes in accordance with slight moves.","To discover the key techniques in macro photography, photographers need to work with different ranges of light and position in a garden and notice the changes in the background caused by slight moves.","To discover the key techniques of macro photography, photographers should work with light and position in a garden and notice how the background changes with slight moves."]},{number:41,answer:3,question:"Hastal\u0131g\u0306\u0131n biyolojik dog\u0306as\u0131 ku\u0308ltu\u0308rden ku\u0308ltu\u0308re deg\u0306is\u0327mese de hastal\u0131klar\u0131n nas\u0131l alg\u0131land\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131n ciddi bir bic\u0327imde deg\u0306is\u0327iklik go\u0308sterdig\u0306ine dair net kan\u0131tlar vard\u0131r.",choices:["The biological nature of disease does not change from one culture to another, though we have clear evidence showing that how diseases are understood is dramatically different.","While the biological nature of disease differs slightly from one culture to another, there is dramatic variation in how diseases are understood, as shown by clear evidence.","Even if there is clear evidence suggesting that how diseases are understood varies dramatically from one culture to another, the biological nature of disease remains constant.","Although the biological nature of disease does not change from one culture to another, there is clear evidence that how diseases are understood varies dramatically.","There is clear evidence suggesting that the biological nature of disease does not change, but how diseases are understood varies to a great extent from one culture to another."]},{number:42,answer:2,question:"Akademik bas\u0327ar\u0131s\u0131zl\u0131g\u0306\u0131n o\u0308nlenmesi ciddi bir konudur c\u0327u\u0308nku\u0308 akademik bas\u0327ar\u0131s\u0131zl\u0131g\u0306a ug\u0306rayan c\u0327ocuklar yas\u0327amlar\u0131 boyunca o\u0308nemli sosyal ve ekonomik problemler yas\u0327arlar.",choices:["It is important that academic failure is prevented since children who fail academically are likely to suffer from significant social and economic problems throughout their lives.","Should academic failure not be avoided, which is a serious subject, children who fail academically face important social and economic problems throughout their lives.","Prevention of academic failure is a serious subject because children who fail academically experience significant social and economic problems throughout their lives.","As a subject, prevention of academic failure is serious because children who fail at school go through significant social and economic problems throughout their lives.","What makes prevention of academic failure a serious subject is that children who fail academically have significant social and economic problems throughout their lives."]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Video games are likely to affect the way we behave in a number of ways. For instance, there is concern about whether violence in games makes young people more violent. This is controversial even within the scientific community. Numerous studies about the effects of games on the brain have come up with conflicting results. A team of scientists gathered all scientific articles to date and compared results. In total they found 116 experiments, the first from the 1980s. Many compared regular video game players with people who had never played. Changes in the brain were measured using techniques which detect whether brain regions increase or reduce in size and how these changes affect the brain\u2019s activity. The study found that the clearest negative impact is the risk of addiction, which could affect other brain functions. Games that heavily rely on online multiplayer modes are the most associated with addiction, due to social interactions being more rewarding than just playing against the computer. However, since video games usually display increasing levels of difficulty, they are continually challenging our skills, making the brain perform at 100% of its capacity, resulting in effective cognitive training. Video games also contribute to the proper functioning of the brain, and can even improve it.",questions:[{number:43,answer:3,question:"There is a controversy about video games even among scientists because ----.",choices:["not many scientists have developed the suitable research design to investigate the issue","video games affect our brains in a number of ways","scientists are still waiting for convincing findings from clinical testing","different studies have produced contradictory findings","there are not many changes in the brains of video game players"]},{number:44,answer:3,question:"Why do online multiplayer games tend to be more addictive than others?",choices:["They display more violence than other games.","They lead to more conflicting behaviours.","They help some regions of the brain get bigger.","They involve communication between players.","They contribute more to the functioning of the brain."]},{number:45,answer:0,question:"Which of the following questions cannot be answered according to the passage?",choices:["Is there a way to avoid the risk of addiction to video games?","Is there any research on the effects of video games on the brain?","Can video games help people socialise with others?","Can video games better brain functioning?","Are there any disadvantages associated with video games?"]},{number:46,answer:3,question:"What is the author\u2019s attitude towards video games?",choices:["Sarcastic","Indifferent","Objective","Sceptical","Pessimistic"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Nearly 20 US states have started to implement former president Barack Obama\u2019s Clean Power Plan, which places limits on carbon dioxide emissions from power plants in an effort to reduce the impacts of climate change. The plan has been in legal limbo for the past year, yet scientists have now calculated another outcome of the policy: harm to crop yields if the plan is stopped. Along with carbon pollution, coal-fired power plants spew pollutants that form smog, which was already known to contribute to increased rates of asthma and premature deaths. The new research estimates the extent to which smog, under air-pollution policies in place before the Clean Power Plan, would limit production in 2020 of four major crops: corn, cotton, potatoes, and soybeans. Led by environmental engineer Shannon Capps, the research team also estimated the extent to which those crop production losses would shrink under three nationwide counter scenarios. One improved the efficiency of individual power plants. Another modelled a policy similar to the Obama plan, setting state carbon dioxide emission goals for the electricity sector. And the third established a tax on carbon emissions, under which emissions decreased the most. But the greatest drop in smog-forming pollutants \u2013 and the greatest gains in crop yields \u2013 came from policies such as the Clean Power Plan.",questions:[{number:47,answer:3,question:"Which of the following is true about crop production according to the passage?",choices:["The losses are insignificant since only four crops are affected.","Smog has no significant effect on crop production in the US.","If coal-fired power plant efficiency is improved, crop yields will increase dramatically.","Coal-fired power plants produce smog, thereby negatively impacting crop yields.","The losses will continue at the same pace even after implementing the Clean Power Plan."]},{number:48,answer:0,question:"According to the passage, in order to estimate crop production losses, the new research ----.",choices:["analysed alternate models using Obama\u2019s Clean Power Plan as a point of reference","relied upon asthma and premature death statistics","targeted all crops including corn, cotton, potatoes, and soybeans","adopted models that were different from the Clean Power Plan","excluded models based on policies in place before the Clean Power Plan"]},{number:49,answer:3,question:"What is the main idea of the passage?",choices:["There is no difference between the Obama plan and other similar plans in terms of reducing emissions.","Crop production will continue to shrink under all three plans proposed by the researchers.","Reducing carbon dioxide emissions from power plants will not necessarily increase crop production.","Policies like the Clean Power Plan are needed to reduce smog rates and increase crop yields.","Improving the efficiency of power plants is necessary to control crop production losses."]},{number:50,answer:0,question:"Which of the following would be the best title for the passage?",choices:["The Importance of the Clean Power Plan ","Three Plans for Crop Production","Pollution from Power Plants","Smog: How Harmful Can It Be?","Why is the Obama Plan in Legal Limbo?"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Fasting could boost your brainpower. A stomach hormone that stimulates appetite seems to promote the growth of new brain cells and protect them from the effects of ageing \u2500 and may explain why some people say that fasting makes them feel sharper. Ghrelin is known as the hunger hormone, as it is made by the stomach when it gets empty. If we go a few hours without food, its levels rise in our blood. But there is also evidence that ghrelin can enhance cognition. Animals fed reduced-calorie diets have better mental abilities. Injecting ghrelin into mice improves their performance in learning and memory tests, and seems to boost the number of connections in their brains. Now Jeffrey Davies at Swansea University, UK, and his team have found further evidence that ghrelin can stimulate brain cells to divide and multiply, a process called neurogenesis. When they added the hormone to mouse brain cells grown in a dish, it switched on a gene known to trigger neurogenesis. \u2018\u2019If the same happens in animals, this could be how ghrelin affects memory,\u2019\u2019 says Davies, whose work was presented at the British Neuroscience Association conference in 2017. The work may have implications for treating neurodegenerative conditions. Davies\u2019s team have found that ghrelin, or chemicals that act the same way, could help treat some conditions like Parkinson\u2019s disease.",questions:[{number:51,answer:3,question:"According to the passage, the hormone ghrelin ----.",choices:["is called the hunger hormone because it prevents one from feeling hungry for long hours","is produced by the body in higher amounts when there are more brain cell connections in the brain","slows down the neurogenesis process when produced in considerably low amounts","plays a role in a number of functions from the production of new brain cells to enhanced mental abilities","affects our appetite in a negative way and causes us to consume more food than we actually need"]},{number:52,answer:1,question:"According to the passage, Jeffrey Davies ----.",choices:["ended up working on the neurogenesis process by chance when he was working on Parkinson\u2019s disease","discovered that ghrelin contributes to neurogenesis, which might be the reason why it improves memory","presented his study at the British Neuroscience Association conference in order to increase awareness of Parkinson\u2019s disease","thinks that more research on ghrelin is needed in order to understand its effects on Parkinson\u2019s disease","believes that ghrelin affects memory in mice differently from humans"]},{number:53,answer:4,question:"The underlined phrase in the passage \u2018switched on\u2019 is closest in meaning to ----.",choices:["protected ","covered ","maintained","transferred","activated"]},{number:54,answer:1,question:"What is the primary purpose of the author?",choices:["To describe how the neurogenesis process takes place in human brain","To highlight that the brain can gain substantial benefits from increased levels of ghrelin","To discuss whether ghrelin could be used as a treatment for Parkinson\u2019s disease","To emphasise the importance of Davies\u2019s study on mice and their mental abilities","To draw particular attention to the 2017 conference held by the British Neuroscience Association"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"First impressions can affect your life course \u2013 how you manage job interviews, whether you gain friends at social gatherings, etc. A study by Harvard psychologist Mahzarin Banaji showed that first impressions can strike us even after we think we have abandoned them. Still, however quickly and unintentionally these impressions form themselves in us, we are not mindless robots. \u201cPeople have some flexibility,\u201d says psychologist Melissa Ferguson from Cornell University, who is interested in how people form, and change, their impressions of others. She has a guy named Bob to thank for her findings. For her studies, Ferguson introduces test subjects to a fictional character named Bob. Sometimes Bob is portrayed as good, with a list of a hundred nice behaviours. When subjects find out he is convicted of an immoral act involving a child, the good impression of Bob completely flips. Other times, Bob does a hundred things making study subjects see him as a moderately nasty guy. Then it is revealed that Bob donated a kidney to a stranger. Here too, Ferguson`s subjects adjusted their opinion; they thought better of him, but still did not think well of him. \u201cThey did not flip,\u201d she says. \u201cA single piece of extremely negative information undoes a positive first impression, but it does not work the same way in the opposite direction. It takes more to overcome a negative first impression.\u201d",questions:[{number:55,answer:1,question:"It is understood from the passage that first impressions ----.",choices:["do not shape our lives profoundly when formed quickly and unintentionally","might not be as easy to get rid of as we may think","may be misleading in job interviews or at social gatherings","lose their effectiveness after a certain amount of time has passed","have such a strong impact on our lives that it is impossible to change them"]},{number:56,answer:4,question:"What could be concluded from the passage about first impressions?",choices:["First impressions about people hardly ever change, positively or negatively, even with lots of effort.","We do not have any control over our first impressions and cannot change them later.","The effects of positive first impressions last much longer than those of negative first impressions.","People may sometimes act like mindless robots when it comes to first impressions.","We can change our first impressions of others later although they are formed unintentionally."]},{number:57,answer:1,question:"What can be concluded from the study conducted by Ferguson?",choices:["Positive information changes the negative first impressions of people to a great extent even though it is about something trivial.","Positive first impressions about someone are more likely to turn into negative opinions when a bit of negative information is provided.","Negative first impressions are more likely to change quickly and easily than positive first impressions.","When nasty people do something really good, people adopt a positive attitude towards them, ignoring their unpleasant background.","People tend to have positive first impressions about others most of the time, but later they may change their mind."]},{number:58,answer:3,question:"Which could be the best title for this passage? ",choices:["The Lack of Control over First Impressions","How to Ward Off Negative First Impressions ","Different Perspectives on First Impressions ","Constructing and Adjusting First Impressions ","Forming Reliable First Impressions"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Dating from 1513, a map drawn by Turkish mariner Piri Reis is one of the earliest cartographic depictions of the Americas. Historians have long been fascinated by many aspects of his map, such as its level of accuracy. The route to the New World, the Americas, was at first a secret closely guarded by the Spanish and Portuguese navigators who were exploring the Atlantic \u2013 for example, Christopher Columbus, who was working for the Spanish monarchy. Reis surprisingly placed the New World on the correct longitudinal meridian in relation to the African continent. His was the earliest known map to do so. However, similar to other maps of the time, the scale of this map is inconsistent, with the Americas drawn much larger than Africa or Asia. Piri Reis wrote on the map itself that he had consulted other maps in Arabic, including some classical sources. He also referred to four contemporary Portuguese maps, as well as one by Columbus. The mystery remains, however, as to how Piri Reis gained access to Columbus\u2019s discoveries.",questions:[{number:59,answer:2,question:"It can be understood from the passage that Piri Reis\u2019s map ----.",choices:["was the first one to include depictions of the Americas ","was preceded by others that include Africa","was not the only map showing the Americas","is the first example of a marine map","is more accurate than once believed"]},{number:60,answer:1,question:"It can be understood from the passage that Spanish and Portuguese explorers ----.",choices:["were initially very open to providing Piri Reis with information","wanted to ensure that no others could find their way to the Americas","were the only ones exploring the Atlantic","were in direct competition with Christopher Columbus","worked very closely with monarchies to establish the New World"]},{number:61,answer:3,question:"The most surprising aspect of Piri Reis\u2019s map is that ----.",choices:["it was the most complete map of the time","the scale was consistent with the previous ones","the locations of Africa and Asia were correctly noted ","his placement of the New World was accurate","it was the first to include longitudinal meridians"]},{number:62,answer:4,question:"Which of the following is true about Piri Reis and his map?",choices:["The Americas appeared much larger than Africa and Asia on Piri Reis`s map because he basically relied upon Arabic maps.","It was impossible that he could have had the same knowledge as Christopher Columbus.","There is some doubt about how Piri Reis made use of the discoveries of previous explorers and their maps.","Due to the similarity in scale inconsistencies, it is often considered that Piri Reis essentially copied his classical sources.","How Piri Reis managed to learn about the discoveries of Columbus is still unknown today."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the dialogue.",questions:[{number:63,answer:0,question:"Robert:\n- You`ve persuaded me to volunteer for that organ donation team, but I can\u2019t figure out what exactly we\u2019re supposed to do.\nLee:\n- The team is trying to encourage families to consider how they would feel about donation if they needed an organ transplant when not enough people give their consent.\nRobert: - ----\nLee:\n- Exactly. Surveys show that 30% of people have never discussed organ donation with their friends and relatives.",choices:["So, as far as I understand, the team is basically trying to raise people\u2019s awareness about the issue.","I see. People are aware of the importance of organ transplantation but most are unwilling to be donors.","OK, so non-profit organisations try to ensure that the ethical considerations are understood.","Yeah, everybody knows that organ transplantation is a must for those who desperately need organs.","I think more and more people are now well-informed about the challenges of the procedure."]},{number:64,answer:2,question:"Journalist:\n- So, your company has set up a system that offers online clinical-counselling, and you\u2019re the chief operating officer. Do you think e-therapy is more effective for certain people?\nPsychologist:\n- Of course, for any therapy to be effective, it has to meet the individual needs of patients. E-therapy may appeal to people looking for convenience, flexibility and privacy, in particular. College students and workers with not much time usually opt for our online services.\nJournalist: - ----\nPsychologist:\n- People have a tendency to think that because you\u2019re using an online service, it must be impersonal and can\u2019t have the same effect. But it\u2019s not true. The difference in results between e-therapy and a face-to-face one is quite minimal.",choices:["How do you talk tech-challenged people into e-therapy?","Why do you think e-therapy will overtake face-to-face therapy?","What is the biggest myth about e-therapy?","How does an e-therapy session work?","How does e-therapy help people with a serious mental illness?"]},{number:65,answer:3,question:"Richard:\n- I saw a video the other day on the Internet about a polyglot.\nLucy:\n- A polyglot? What\u2019s that?\nRichard:\n- A polyglot is a person who speaks several different languages. The person in the video I saw speaks eight languages including Portuguese and Chinese.\nLucy: - ----\nRichard:\n- There are some methods used. For example, allocating a few hours a day for a language until mastering it, including intense listening and speaking activities.",choices:["Why aren\u2019t there more people who can speak many languages like this?","What\u2019s the minimum number of languages needed to describe someone as a polyglot?","Do you think he\u2019s completely fluent in all eight of those languages?","How do you think such people manage to learn so many languages?","How many more languages do you think he can add to his repertoire?"]},{number:66,answer:3,question:"Sarah:\n- Recently, I\u2019ve read a magazine article, and it says over the first four years of marriage, spouses report a gradual increase in their willingness to forgive each other.\nFrancis:\n- So, it means they learn to forgive each other as they spend more time together.\nSarah: - ----\nFrancis:\n- What do you mean?\nSarah:\n- The article says forgiving benefits both partners only if the forgiven partner is agreeable and cooperative. If not, he or she tends to offend again.",choices:["I think anyone who is in a close relationship will, at some point, have to decide whether or not to forgive.","Well, I believe the most important thing in relations is mutual trust. If you have it, you don\u2019t experience such forgiveness problems.","It\u2019s also possible that even if someone wants to forgive, they might not think that the wrongdoer or offender really deserves it.","One needs to be cautious, though, as forgiveness could backfire, depending on the offending partner\u2019s personality.","Maybe the reason is that being exposed to situations where forgiveness is required helps one improve that skill."]},{number:67,answer:4,question:"Stacy:\n- I\u2019m so bored with my never-ending to-do list. But I can\u2019t say I\u2019ve been able to cross a single item off the list so far.\nCarole:\n- Maybe you should stop procrastinating and just start working on your list.\nStacy:\n- What do you mean?\nCarole: - ----\nStacy:\n- I think you\u2019re right, finding another person with the same aspirations will help me take action.",choices:["I don\u2019t get why you\u2019ve been feeling so desperate about your life plans. You\u2019re one of the most ambitious and motivated people I know.","Well, I\u2019ve been seeing a psychologist to deal with the same type of issue. Maybe that\u2019s something you can look into as well.","Life seems to be getting busier for us modern working women. Maybe keeping a diary of goals you\u2019ve achieved will help you stay focused.","Maybe one way to deal with your problem is just making a habit out of it. I mean you should make a habit of taking action to fulfil your plans.","You don\u2019t have to keep waiting for the perfect moment. Plus sharing your goals and plans with someone else could be a good idea."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best rephrased form of the given sentence.",questions:[{number:68,answer:2,question:"Mentally healthy adults have a right to refuse medical intervention even if this is likely to result in fatal consequences.",choices:["No matter how deadly the results of medical intervention are, mentally healthy adults are choosing to reject it.","If they are mentally healthy, adults could reject medical intervention without considering whether or not such an intervention could lead to some tragic outcomes.","Regardless of possible deadly results of rejecting medical intervention, adults who are mentally healthy have an entitlement to do it.","It is a right for mentally healthy adults to oppose medical intervention even though they may be aware of possible deadly results.","It is possible for mentally healthy adults to consider refusing medical intervention when they are aware of serious implications of this."]},{number:69,answer:1,question:"While some people believe that video games are a waste of time, certain games can be a good vehicle for training specific skills, such as enhancing short-term memory, agility or reaction time.",choices:["Although some people are convinced that video games are useful in teaching specific skills like improving short-term memory, agility or reaction time, some of them are futile activities, according to some others.","Certain video games can be good means for practising some specific skills like improving short-term memory, agility or reaction time, but there are some people who believe that video games are of no use.","Some people assume that video games are time-consuming, although they know that certain video games are efficient tools in teaching specific skills like improving short-term memory, agility or reaction time.","Video games are thought to be time-consuming; however, they may be beneficial for some people practising certain skills like improving short-term memory, agility or reaction time.","There are some people who presume that video games are beneficial in specific skills like improving short-term memory, agility or reaction time; however, those games could be a waste of time indeed."]},{number:70,answer:4,question:"Since December 2014, the Breathe Project in the US has been making use of high definition cameras that let residents monitor the air pollution in their cities online.",choices:["US residents have been contributing to the Breathe Project since December 2014 by monitoring the air pollution in their cities with online use of high definition cameras.","In the US, air pollution has been monitored online by the Breathe Project with high definition cameras since December 2014 in order to inform residents about the rates in their cities.","Residents can reduce air pollution in their cities by using online high definition cameras of the Breathe Project, which was launched by the US in December 2014.","High definition cameras used by the Breathe Project in the US since December 2014 help residents combat air pollution in their cities through online monitoring.","High definition cameras that have been utilised by the Breathe Project in the US since December 2014 enable residents to monitor the air pollution in their cities online."]},{number:71,answer:0,question:"The growing awareness of the impact of job stress is best illustrated by the sheer increase in the volume of job stress research in recent years.",choices:["The past few years have witnessed a dramatic rise in the amount of job stress research, which best demonstrates the increasing recognition of the impact of job stress.","The influence of job stress has increased recently, which is best shown by the awareness that has been substantially enhanced by the growth in the amount of job stress research.","People are becoming increasingly aware of the volume of job stress research, which has been best illustrated by the recent increase in the influence of job stress.","Lately, there has been more research in the field of job stress, which means that it may lead to a higher level of consciousness about the influence of job stress.","Although there has been a considerable increase in the number of studies on job stress recently, there is still a need for greater understanding of the influence of job stress."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the missing part of the passage.",questions:[{number:72,answer:0,question:"According to a study in Usenge, Kenya, near the town of Kisimu, most families in the village do not value formal Western schooling. There is no reason they should, as their children will for the most part spend their lives farming or engaged in other occupations that make little or no use of Western schooling. These families emphasise teaching their children the indigenous, informal knowledge that will lead to successful adaptation in the environments in which they will really live. ---- They hope that their children may be able to leave the village and to go to a university. These families tend to emphasise the value of Western education and to devalue indigenous informal knowledge. Thus, the families typically value and emphasise one or the other kind of knowledge, but not both.",choices:["At the same time, there are some, perhaps not many, families in the village that have different expectations for their children.","They believe that investing a lot of time in the development of academic skills needed for school success is a poor investment.","Furthermore, they see the learning of informal knowledge as relevant to their everyday adaptation as a better use of their time.","Some wealthy and educated parents living in the village share the same opinion with such families and do not favour formal Western schooling.","In formal Western schooling, however, children typically study a variety of subjects, including maths, foreign languages, etc., from an early age."]},{number:73,answer:1,question:"As children move into adolesence, they seek much more autonomy. At this stage, parents must achieve a delicate balance between granting autonomy and making sure their children do not get into situations where problematic or even dangerous behaviour could occur. ---- This makes it likely that their children will be involved with other teens who are enthusiastic about school and not into risk-taking.",choices:["However, some parents may find it difficult to develop clear rules to ensure the teenager engages in appropriate activities when not under adult supervision.","It could be helpul if parents establish effective communication with their children with regard to what they are doing each day and foster their academic interests.","Children who are not regularly monitored by their parents are more likely to adopt destructive habits, suffer from depression, and obtain poor grades.","The most important issues to consider are the time teens need to be home, where they can go when they are out, and whom they can be with.","On the contrary, offering numerous opportunities for young people to play a greater role in civic life and governance is another way to prevent problems."]},{number:74,answer:1,question:"Medieval Islam became the principal heir to ancient Greek science, and Islamic civilisation remained the world leader in virtually every field of science between 800-1300 AD. The sheer level of scientific activity underlines this point, as the number of Islamic scientists during the four centuries after the Prophet matched the number of Greek scientists during the four centuries following Thales. Islamic scientists established the first truly international scientific community, stretching from Iberia to Central Asia. ---- A moment\u2019s thought, however, shows how unreasonable it is to evaluate the history of Islamic science only or even largely as a link to European science, or even to subsume Islamic science into the \u2018Western tradition\u2019. Medieval Islam and its science must be judged on their own terms, and those terms are as much Eastern as Western.",choices:["Early Islamic rulers encouraged the mastery of foreign cultural traditions, including notably Greek philosophy and science.","Yet, medieval Islamic science is sometimes dismissed as a conduit passively transmitting ancient Greek science to the European Middle Ages.","Islam was and is based on literacy and the holy book of the Quran, and contrary to the popular view, Islam showed itself tolerant toward others.","The result was another hybrid society, the cultural \u2018Hellenisation\u2019 of Islam and its typically bureaucratised institutions.","The institutional aspects of Islamic science are only beginning to be studied with scholarly rigour, and nothing like a full historical survey exists for the Islamic case."]},{number:75,answer:2,question:"Even though there are a number of teaching approaches, the literature indicates that teachers have two primary orientations to teaching: an orientation toward conveying knowledge and an orientation toward facilitating learning. ---- On the other hand, if the teacher wants to maximise students\u2019 understanding, he or she will probably focus on the integration and elaboration of information in ways that could facilitate meaningful learning and critical thinking.",choices:["Interestingly, teachers\u2019 approaches to teaching are also mediated by situational and contextual factors in addition to a number of other factors.","Hence, the various characteristics of students in these classrooms will influence the approach to teaching as well as its outcomes.","For example, a teacher whose goal of teaching is to transmit and increase knowledge will likely focus on the content and provide structured learning experiences.","Moreover, it is generally known that the values and beliefs of teachers influence their perceptions and judgements and also affect their behaviour in the classroom.","Furthermore, this teacher might believe that students should be rewarded for good work and penalised for lack of effort and poor work."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the irrelevant sentence in the passage.",questions:[{number:76,answer:4,question:"(I) In ancient time-measurement systems, including those of both Egypt and China, daylight and night-time were each given 12 hours. (II) This was convenient for use with sundials, which are known from Egypt as early as 1500 BC, although telling the time `by the Sun` probably predates the first humans. (III) However, because the length of daylight and night-time varies with the season, so did the length of the sundials. (IV) When water clocks came into use, shortly after them, a conflict between the two forms of measurement became apparent. (V) In the 8th century AD, the Chinese began to add primitive but a bit more sophisticated equipment to water clocks.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:77,answer:0,question:"(I) Early world history focuses on agricultural civilisations, but it must also pay attention to regions that developed different kinds of economies and different organisational structures. (II) The development of agriculture was a radical change in humans` way of life. (III) By providing a dependable source of food, it allowed people to live in larger groups. (IV) Later on, toolmaking technology advanced with the discovery of metalworking, which in turn further increased agricultural production. (V) Increased production freed some members of the society to perform other kinds of work and this in turn encouraged a further series of organisational changes we call civilisation.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:78,answer:2,question:"(I) Most non-marine food chains depend on insects. (II) Almost all birds eat insects, and even those that eat seeds as adults still feed insects to their young. (III) If there were no longer any insects, we would not need the 430,000 tonnes of insecticides that are sprayed onto crops every year. (IV) Insects also break down plant matter and help recycle nutrients into the soil. (V) Without any insects at all, most bird and amphibian species would be extinct in two months.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:79,answer:2,question:"(I) In its earlier days, people treated the experience of watching television rather like that of the cinema, but in many ways, television is nothing like cinema. (II) While film is designed to be a public event and its characteristic mode is a complete performance, television is a procession of segments arranged as a series and watched privately or domestically. (III) Communal watching of programmes provides opportunities for displays of family warmth and affection, so television watching may promote strong emotional connections among families and friends. (IV) Contrary to the intense quality of film that receives sustained attention from the audience, television watching is more casual and episodic. (V) Another obvious distinction is that films typically start with a disordered narrative and move through a series of ups and downs to a resolution, but television presents itself as a set of repeated segments which do not always form a unity of any kind.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:80,answer:3,question:"(I) Martin Luther King Jr. was born in 1929 and grew up in the Deep South, a region of America with a history scarred by slavery and racial segregation. (II) An intelligent and deeply religious man, he attended college at the early age of 15 and went on to study theology, receiving his doctorate in 1955. (III) King was inspired by early civil right leaders, such as Howard Thurman, who knew his father and was a trusted mentor. (IV) In 1963, King led the \u2018March on Washington\u2019, a huge event where thousands gathered on the National Mall to hear him speak. (V) He also looked up to Mahatma Gandhi, and was to adopt his teachings of non-violent resistance in his own struggle for equality in the US.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]}]}]},{routeName:"2018-Spring",items:[{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the space.",questions:[{number:1,answer:2,question:"Gender studies is a multifaceted field of inquiry into social structures and social relations that has important ---- for the study of violence, peace and conflict.",choices:["challenges","divisions","implications","drawbacks","requirements"]},{number:2,answer:2,question:"Nano-tech products can potentially save lives as well as give us hundreds of new conveniences from enhanced drug delivery and disease ---- to fabric that will not stain.",choices:["progression","manipulation","detection","transmission","inheritance"]},{number:3,answer:1,question:"The thin, invisible layer of gas surrounding the Earth, which is called the atmosphere, shields us from the vacuum of space and protects us from ---- solar radiation.",choices:["delicate","excessive","vigorous","elaborate","swift"]},{number:4,answer:3,question:"Architectural analysis is not only a ---- academic pursuit, done for its own sake, but it can be informative and entertaining as well.",choices:["mutually","convincingly","drastically","purely","deniably"]},{number:5,answer:1,question:"Childcare is a broad term that ---- services which protect the health, safety, and well-being of children who require custodial care by adults other than their own parents for a temporary period of time.",choices:["hinders","encompasses","creates","eliminates","suspends"]},{number:6,answer:4,question:"Taking a break, and distracting your mind for a while, not only gives you the spare time to be creative, but it can also give your brain the space it needs to ---- creative solutions to problems you have been struggling with.",choices:["make up for","get away from","fight back against","look up to","come up with"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word(s) or expression(s) to fill the space(s).",questions:[{number:7,answer:2,question:"A number of studies have concluded that a given level of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere ---- less warming than previously ----.",choices:["is producing / to think","has produced / thinking","produces / thought","has been producing / having thought","had produced / being thought"]},{number:8,answer:3,question:"Anyone who ---- unusual reactions to antihistamines (medicines that relieve or prevent the symptoms of some kinds of allergy) in the recent past ---- his or her physician know before taking the drugs again.",choices:["used to have / might let","had had / must have let","was having / could let","has had / should let","had / might have let"]},{number:9,answer:2,question:"By 2.5 million years ago, when they began ---- stone tools, early humans had understood that they ---- the natural world to their own advantage.",choices:["to have made / had to alter","to make / used to alter","making / could alter","having made / should have altered","to have been making / must have altered"]},{number:10,answer:2,question:"Dramatists and scriptwriters could place their characters ---- the centre of a terrifying human conflict, and may allow us to watch these characters suffer the pains of avoiding a collision ---- the conflict.",choices:["on / for","over / in","at / with","to / about","by / from"]},{number:11,answer:2,question:"---- the problems of obesity and disordered eating growing around the world, public health professionals have focused research efforts on identifying potential causes and treatments ---- these related problems.",choices:["About / in","On / towards","With / for","Through / from","Among / at"]},{number:12,answer:1,question:"---- there is no consensus among folklorists on how to define folklore nor how to explain the issues of the meaning and the function of it, folklore generally refers to cultural expressions, such as narratives, music, dance, beliefs and festivals.",choices:["Once","While","Until","As","In case"]},{number:13,answer:2,question:"Industrial nations consume nearly 75 to 80 percent of the fossil fuels burned each year; ----, they are responsible for the majority of greenhouse gas emissions.",choices:["instead","on the contrary","as a result","for example","however"]},{number:14,answer:3,question:"Buildings such as the Hagia Sophia in Istanbul, Turkey date back to the sixth century and yet are still standing ---- they are located in earthquake-prone areas.",choices:["as long as","unless","as if","although","since"]},{number:15,answer:4,question:"In statistics, ---- the standard deviation allows us to see how much individuals vary within a sample, ---- the standard error allows us to estimate how much samples will vary within a population.",choices:["whether / or","no sooner / than","rather / than","hardly / when","just as / so"]},{number:16,answer:4,question:"The idea of the Internet was initially to provide redundancy of communications ---- a catastrophic event like a nuclear blast, which might destroy a single connection or computer but not the entire network.",choices:["such as","on behalf of","in terms of","in addition to","in case of"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage",text:"Fossil fuel use is one of the main causes of climate change and the greenhouse effect. ----, we must significantly reduce carbon dioxide emissions from activities like heating and transportation. One option would be to ---- to renewable energy sources wherever possible, such as solar, hydropower, wind or geothermal systems. Another important step is to reduce our individual energy footprint. For example, driving a car places a particularly high burden on the environment ---- the carbon dioxide emissions into the air. Yet, we should keep in mind that there are several ways to lessen the impact and still continue ---- cars. For instance, by choosing ---- many new energy-saving models, we can help reduce harmful emissions.",questions:[{number:17,answer:4,question:"----, we must significantly reduce carbon dioxide emissions from activities like heating and transportation.",choices:["Conversely","Similarly","Otherwise","However","Therefore"]},{number:18,answer:2,question:"One option would be to ---- to renewable energy sources wherever possible, such as solar, hydropower, wind or geothermal systems.",choices:["confine","object","switch","accommodate","respond"]},{number:19,answer:3,question:"For example, driving a car places a particularly high burden on the environment ---- the carbon dioxide emissions into the air.",choices:["regardless of","rather than","as opposed to","due to","in spite of"]},{number:20,answer:2,question:"Yet, we should keep in mind that there are several ways to lessen the impact and still continue ---- cars.",choices:["to have used","being used","using","to be used","having used"]},{number:21,answer:0,question:"For instance, by choosing ---- many new energy-saving models, we can help reduce harmful emissions.",choices:["from","onto","at","towards","over"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:"When fighting fat, and trying to eat healthily, changing your eating environment is easier than changing your mind. A research team in the US has set about uncovering the hidden persuaders in our homes that trick us ---- overeating \u2013 things like serving spoons, cupboards and colours. But most of these tempters can also be reversed to make us slimmer and healthier. ---- there are many solutions to mindless eating, most of them will go undiscovered because if we have a problem with our diet, we tend to focus on food itself, not on our surroundings. All that requires willpower, which is hard work and has to last a lifetime to be ---- successful. Research has found subtle ways to change our homes, workplaces, schools, or modify our approach to restaurant dining and grocery shopping, so we mindlessly eat less ---- eating more. If we want to automatically eat better, we do not need to change our minds, we ---- our surroundings.",questions:[{number:22,answer:1,question:"A research team in the US has set about uncovering the hidden persuaders in our homes that trick us ---- overeating \u2013 things like serving spoons, cupboards and colours.",choices:["against","into","without","behind","off"]},{number:23,answer:4,question:"---- there are many solutions to mindless eating, most of them will go undiscovered because if we have a problem with our diet, we tend to focus on food itself, not on our surroundings.",choices:["Given that","Just as","Before","Unless","Although"]},{number:24,answer:2,question:"All that requires willpower, which is hard work and has to last a lifetime to be ---- successful.",choices:["coincidentally","vaguely","truly","partially","seemingly"]},{number:25,answer:1,question:"Research has found subtle ways to change our homes, workplaces, schools, or modify our approach to restaurant dining and grocery shopping, so we mindlessly eat less ---- eating more.",choices:["due to","instead of","with regard to","in terms of","together with"]},{number:26,answer:0,question:"If we want to automatically eat better, we do not need to change our minds, we ---- our surroundings.",choices:["have to optimise","must have optimised","may have optimised","could have optimised","would optimise"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the given sentence.",questions:[{number:27,answer:3,question:"Because of its power and potential for both harm and good, ----.",choices:["modern meteorology has made notable improvements in the critical discipline of predicting severe weather","meteorologists are the only professionals who can keep their jobs and still be wrong half the time","scientists have studied cloud seeding with the goal of making it rain in places experiencing prolonged droughts","the weather has been a subject of intense interest and scrutiny by human beings since ancient times","it seems unlikely that we will ever get to the point of being able to predict the weather with 100 percent accuracy"]},{number:28,answer:3,question:"Forensic investigators must collect evidence while the crime scene is still fresh ----.",choices:["because forensic science is the use of scientific methods to investigate crimes","since forensic scientists study evidence at the homes and workplaces of suspects","although it is the job of forensic scientists to provide evidence at a criminal trial","even if the area is unsafe and they have to work under armed guard","as many sciences, from chemistry to engineering, are used in an investigation"]},{number:29,answer:0,question:"Although alchemy began as a way to turn other metals into gold, ----.",choices:["it matured into a system of thinking about nature that contributed to the development of modern chemistry","alchemistic ideas and practices flourished in the ancient world within several cultural traditions","a number of spectacular failures eventually led to the disappearance of alchemy in China","alchemists continued in their relentless quest for gold well into the sixteenth century","its objectives were to find ways of accelerating the rates at which metals could be changed into gold"]},{number:30,answer:1,question:"Although the available evidence shows no use of colour or decoration on early footwear, ----.",choices:["the existence of twenty-five-thousand-year-old clothing suggests that footwear may be older than is even presently known","the elaborate weaving on some shoes seems to indicate that prehistoric people would care about the appearance of the shoes","prehistoric shoes had to resist heavy usage, whether made from leather or from plant fibers","the oldest known shoes are ten-thousand-year-old sandals found in a desert area of eastern Oregon of the US","prehistoric humans would make their shoes shortly after killing animals, such as sheep and deer"]},{number:31,answer:1,question:"While most research on the role of genetics and the heritability of aggression has ruled out the idea of an aggressive gene, ----.",choices:["most definitions of aggression indicate that it represents behaviours that are intended to hurt or harm another","it is currently thought that one might inherit the biological susceptibility for being aggressive","one of the most widely discussed theories of aggressive behavior is Albert Bandura`s social learning theory","there are a number of different ways to conceptualise subtypes of aggressive behaviours","much of the research on aggression has focused primarily upon children who are physically aggressive"]},{number:32,answer:2,question:"----, it will not be possible to turn a draft into a finished piece of work.",choices:["Although an author may have a hard time evaluating what he or she has written","Even if an author thinks that characterisation is poor in his or her work","Unless an author knows the strengths and weaknesses of a manuscript","Because an author should realise that revision turns an amateur into a professional","When rewriting and polishing lead an author to produce a good novel"]},{number:33,answer:1,question:"Some birds build nests simply to protect their young ----.",choices:["since many small animals that live above the ground make their homes in trees","until they have learned how to look after themselves and survive in the wild on their own","given that they make mud huts that are placed in all kinds of places, from undergrowth to fence posts","although sometimes a squirrel takes over an empty bird`s nest and makes its home there","while colonies of wasps build their nests from the top downward"]},{number:34,answer:3,question:"Of the 20 amino acids that make up all proteins, 9 are considered essential ----.",choices:["if thousands of proteins are assembled from some 20 different amino acids","as the best sources of complete protein are lean meats, fish, low-fat dairy products, and eggs","even if some foods are better sources of protein than others","because they cannot be made in our bodies and must be obtained from the foods we eat","although the proteins in the foods we eat are digested first into small peptides"]},{number:35,answer:0,question:"Trans fat may be as harmful to your health as saturated fat ----.",choices:["because it increases blood cholesterol levels, among other adverse effects","although major sources are hardened vegetable fat such as margarine","as long as foods high in saturated fat include red meats and dairy products","since a diet that has generous amounts of vegetables is naturally lower in fat","even if a diet high in fat can also be unnecessarily high in calories"]},{number:36,answer:1,question:"----, he was foremost an inventor and more interested in attracting public interest in his work than advancing scientific knowledge.",choices:["When the philosopher Alfred North Whitehead famously credited Thomas Edison with the discovery of a method of invention","While Thomas Edison saw himself as a member of the larger scientific community and presented papers before the National Academy of Sciences","As Thomas Edison began his inventive career by becoming a contract inventor in the telegraph industry after working as a telegraph operator in the mid-1860s","Because Thomas Edison depended more on the assistance of a large staff of experimenters and machinists who made important contributions to his inventive efforts","Although reputation was significant for Thomas Edison, particularly because of his popular image as the primary inventor of several new technologies"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the most accurate Turkish translation of the sentences in English, and the most accurate English translation of the sentences in Turkish.",questions:[{number:37,answer:1,question:"Since the 1970s, media literacy has developed through the work of educators who have implemented programs to explore mass media, popular culture, and communication technologies with children and young people.",choices:["Medya okuryazarl\u0131\u011f\u0131, kitle ileti\u015fimini, pop\xfcler k\xfclt\xfcr\xfc ve ileti\u015fim teknolojilerini \xe7ocuklar ve gen\xe7 insanlarla ke\u015ffetmek i\xe7in \xe7al\u0131\u015fan e\u011fitimcilerin yapt\u0131\u011f\u0131 programlar sayesinde 1970`lerden beri geli\u015fmektedir.","1970`lerden beri medya okuryazarl\u0131\u011f\u0131, \xe7ocuklarla ve gen\xe7 insanlarla kitle ileti\u015fimini, pop\xfcler k\xfclt\xfcr\xfc ve ileti\u015fim teknolojilerini ke\u015ffetmek i\xe7in programlar uygulayan e\u011fitimcilerin \xe7al\u0131\u015fmalar\u0131 arac\u0131l\u0131\u011f\u0131yla geli\u015fmektedir.","\xc7ocuklar ve gen\xe7 insanlarla kitle ileti\u015fimini, pop\xfcler k\xfclt\xfcr\xfc ve ileti\u015fim teknolojilerini ke\u015ffetmek i\xe7in programlar d\xfczenleyen e\u011fitimcilerin \xe7al\u0131\u015fmalar\u0131 sayesinde medya okuryazarl\u0131\u011f\u0131 1970`lerden g\xfcn\xfcm\xfczdeki h\xe2line gelmi\u015ftir.","Medya okuryazarl\u0131\u011f\u0131n\u0131n geli\u015fmesi \xe7ocuklarla ve gen\xe7 insanlarla kitle ileti\u015fimini, pop\xfcler k\xfclt\xfcr\xfc ve ileti\u015fim teknolojilerini ke\u015ffetmek i\xe7in 1970`lerden beri programlar uygulayan e\u011fitimcilerin \xe7al\u0131\u015fmalar\u0131 sayesinde olmu\u015ftur.","Kitle ileti\u015fimini, pop\xfcler k\xfclt\xfcr\xfc ve ileti\u015fim teknolojilerini ke\u015ffetmek \xfczere 1970`lerden beri \xe7ocuklara ve gen\xe7 insanlara uygulanan programlar e\u011fitimcilerin \xe7al\u0131\u015fmalar\u0131yla birlikte medya okuryazarl\u0131\u011f\u0131n\u0131 geli\u015ftirmi\u015ftir."]},{number:38,answer:3,question:"As members of households established complex relationships with outsiders during the agrarian era, they came under the influence of new rules, structures, and expectations.",choices:["Hane fertleri, tar\u0131m d\xf6nemi boyunca yabanc\u0131larla \xe7e\u015fitli ili\u015fkiler kurarak yeni kurallar\u0131n, yap\u0131lar\u0131n ve beklentilerin etkisi alt\u0131na girmi\u015flerdir.","Hane fertlerinin yabanc\u0131larla karma\u015f\u0131k ili\u015fkiler kurmas\u0131 tar\u0131m d\xf6nemine denk gelmi\u015ftir ve bu d\xf6nemde yeni kurallardan, yap\u0131lardan ve beklentilerden etkilenmi\u015flerdir.","Tar\u0131m d\xf6neminde hane fertlerinin yabanc\u0131larla \xe7e\u015fitli ili\u015fkiler kurmas\u0131n\u0131n sebebi; yeni kurallar\u0131n, yap\u0131lar\u0131n ve beklentilerin etkisi alt\u0131na girmi\u015f olmalar\u0131d\u0131r.","Tar\u0131m d\xf6neminde hane fertleri yabanc\u0131larla karma\u015f\u0131k ili\u015fkiler kurduk\xe7a yeni kurallar\u0131n, yap\u0131lar\u0131n ve beklentilerin etkisi alt\u0131na girmi\u015flerdir.","Yeni kurallar\u0131n, yap\u0131lar\u0131n ve beklentilerin etkisi alt\u0131na giren hane fertleri, tar\u0131m d\xf6neminde yabanc\u0131larla daha karma\u015f\u0131k ili\u015fkiler kurmu\u015flard\u0131r."]},{number:39,answer:3,question:"More than a hundred different studies have shown that there really is a significant relation between happiness and physical health.",choices:["Yap\u0131lan y\xfczden fazla farkl\u0131 \xe7al\u0131\u015fma g\xf6stermi\u015ftir ki mutluluk ile beden sa\u011fl\u0131\u011f\u0131 aras\u0131nda ger\xe7ekten \xf6nemli bir ili\u015fki bulunabilir.","Mutluluk ile beden sa\u011fl\u0131\u011f\u0131 aras\u0131ndaki \xf6nemli bir ili\u015fkinin ger\xe7ekli\u011fi, y\xfczden fazla farkl\u0131 \xe7al\u0131\u015fma sayesinde ortaya konmu\u015ftur.","Mutluluk ile beden sa\u011fl\u0131\u011f\u0131 aras\u0131nda ger\xe7ekten \xf6nemli bir ili\u015fki olup olmad\u0131\u011f\u0131n\u0131 g\xf6stermek i\xe7in y\xfczden fazla farkl\u0131 \xe7al\u0131\u015fma yap\u0131lm\u0131\u015ft\u0131r.","Y\xfczden fazla farkl\u0131 \xe7al\u0131\u015fma, mutluluk ile beden sa\u011fl\u0131\u011f\u0131 aras\u0131nda ger\xe7ekten \xf6nemli bir ili\u015fki oldu\u011funu g\xf6stermi\u015ftir.","Y\xfczden fazla farkl\u0131 \xe7al\u0131\u015fmaya g\xf6re, mutluluk ile beden sa\u011fl\u0131\u011f\u0131 aras\u0131nda ger\xe7ekten \xf6nemli bir ili\u015fki olabilir."]},{number:40,answer:3,question:"Kar\u015f\u0131la\u015ft\u0131\u011f\u0131m\u0131z b\xfct\xfcn problemleri e\u015fit derecede iyi \xe7\xf6zemeyebiliriz, \xe7\xfcnk\xfc her bir problem farkl\u0131 ve yarat\u0131c\u0131 bir \xe7\xf6z\xfcm gerektirebilir.",choices:["We cannot solve all the problems we encounter equally well because we may need to develop a unique and creative solution to each problem.","The reason why we may not deal with all the problems we confront equally well is that each problem may require a different and innovative solution.","Because each problem may call for a distinct and creative solution, all the problems we face cannot be settled equally well.","We may not be able to solve all the problems we confront equally well since each problem might require a different and creative solution.","We could not overcome all the problems we encounter equally well now that a different and innovative solution may need to be produced for each problem."]},{number:41,answer:0,question:"20. y\xfczy\u0131l\u0131n ba\u015flar\u0131nda Albert Einstein ad\u0131nda gen\xe7 bir Alman, klasik fizi\u011fi sarsarak ve mutlak bir zaman ve uzay fikrini sonland\u0131rarak g\xf6relilik kuram\u0131n\u0131 \xf6ne s\xfcrd\xfc.",choices:["At the turn of the 20th century, a young German named Albert Einstein proposed his theory of relativity, shaking classical physics and ending the idea of an absolute time and space.","A young German named Albert Einstein shook classical physics at the beginning of the 20th century and put forward his theory of relativity, ending the idea of an absolute time and space.","At the turn of the 20th century, a young German named Albert Einstein shook classical physics and ended the idea of an absolute time and space by proposing his theory of relativity.","Proposing his theory of relativity at the turn of the 20th century, a young German named Albert Einstein shook classical physics and ended the idea of an absolute time and space.","The theory of relativity, proposed by a young German named Albert Einstein at the beginning of the 20th century, shook classical physics and ended the idea of an absolute time and space."]},{number:42,answer:0,question:"\xc7\u0131rakl\u0131k sistemleri Avrupa ve Asya \xfclkelerinde yayg\u0131n bir bi\xe7imde kullan\u0131lagelmi\u015f olsa da Birle\u015fik Devletler`dekinden biraz farkl\u0131 bir bi\xe7imde i\u015flemektedir.",choices:["Although apprenticeship systems have been used widely in European and Asian countries, they operate in a somewhat different manner than those in the United States.","European and Asian countries have been widely using apprenticeship systems that operate in a slightly different manner than the United States.","Apprenticeship systems are widely used not only in European and Asian countries but also in the United States, but in a somewhat different manner in the former.","Both European and Asian countries and the United States have been widely using apprenticeship systems, but the latter has been practising it in a slightly different manner.","There is a slight difference between the apprenticeship systems in European and Asian countries and those in the United States, though both have been widely used for a long time."]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Pick up a glass, fill it from the tap and take a sip. You just had a tiny dose of the pill your neighbour took days before. Excreted and flushed through our sewage works and waterways, drug molecules are all around us. A recent analysis of streams in the US detected an entire pharmacy: diabetic medications, muscle relaxants, opioids, antibiotics, antidepressants and more. Drugs have even been found in crops irrigated by treated waste water. The amounts that end up in your glass are minuscule, and will not lay you low tomorrow. However, someone prescribed multiple drugs is more likely to experience side effects due to these small doses, and risks rise exponentially with each drug taken by a person over 65. \u201cThese drugs have been individually approved but we have not studied what it means when they are together in the same soup,\u201d says Mae Wu at the National Resources Defense Council (NRDC).",questions:[{number:43,answer:0,question:"Which of the following can be true about the tap water in the US?",choices:["The drugs in the tap water are not expected to have immediate side effects on healthy people.","There can be a lower risk for elder members of society who take more than one drug a day.","Most drugs in the tap water are harmless, but illegal ones can make people sick.","It is more likely for a person to be affected if there are multiple drug residues in the tap water.","The tap water used in houses does not cause negative effects for adults at all."]},{number:44,answer:3,question:"It is pointed out in the passage that the tap water ----.",choices:["can dramatically increase the severity of diseases due to the variety of compounds found in it","contains drugs that have been found to be illegal as they are harmful for human health","makes it possible for us to determine the types of pills our neighbours take every day","contains medicinal leftovers, which can pass on to us when we drink water from our taps","does not pose any threats for human health because most of the drugs dissolve quite well in it"]},{number:45,answer:4,question:"What can be inferred from Mae Wu`s words?",choices:["The combination of medical waste in the tap water creates a very hazardous toxic soup.","She believes that drinking tap water can cause serious side effects in most people.","The NRDC is planning to study the effects of drugs when they are together in the same mixture.","Despite being approved individually, all drugs can be dangerous when mixed with tap water.","She is unsure of the health effects of the combination of small doses of different drugs in the tap water."]},{number:46,answer:3,question:"What is the main purpose of the author?",choices:["To blame the US authorities for failing to take precautions against drug leftovers","To catch the attention of academicians to find a solution to the problem of contaminated tap water","To dissuade readers from continuing to use tap water in the US","To warn readers against possible health risks that may be caused by tap water","To call for more action from the NRDC in sterilising tap water"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Admired by native peoples for thousands of years, the Texas horned lizard has an array of abilities. It mostly eats ants \u2013 lots of them, and most parts of an ant`s body are indigestible, which necessitates a huge stomach. Eating more than two hundred ants per day means exposure out in the open for long periods, and having a `heavy` stomach means that a horned lizard finds it difficult to run away from predators. Instead, it relies on an armory of defences. It has camouflage colouring, with an outline broken up by spines and outgrowths, and it will freeze if a predator approaches. Its horns and spines can pierce the throat of a snake or bird, and it can hiss and blow itself up to look even more fearsome. When it comes to coyotes, foxes, and dogs, a horned lizard`s most spectacular defence is to squirt foul-tasting blood from the sinuses behind its eyes. That usually has the desired effect. But it squirts only when it is provoked, since it risks losing up to one quarter of its blood. Such abilities are, however, no defense against human invasion of its land. Its strange shape and colouring has made it attractive to reptile collectors, and its habit of freezing means that it is prone to being run over.",questions:[{number:47,answer:1,question:"For a horned lizard, eating too many ants meansthat it ----.",choices:["has to spend more time to digest what it has eatenthan to hunt for food","is more vulnerable to predators while trying to runaway","will become highly indigestible for its predators","seems to get physically stronger in its struggleto survive in the wild","causes a huge decrease in the ant population livingaround its habitat"]},{number:48,answer:0,question:"How does a horned lizard defend itself when facedwith a predator?",choices:["It blends into its surroundings using its naturalcolouring and shape.","It freezes the predator with the help of its spines.","It makes itself smaller than normal to confuse thepredator.","It releases a kind of liquid to make the predatorsuffocate.","It changes its colour and shape to become morethreatening to its predators."]},{number:49,answer:0,question:"It could be bad for a horned lizard to use itsown blood for defence because ----.",choices:["it might lose a high amount of blood, which would putits life at risk","predators like the taste of the blood, making themmore willing to eat it","the bright colour of the blood could make it easyfor predators to see it","it is an ineffective way of defence when the predator isa snake or bird","the smell of the blood could attract more predators"]},{number:50,answer:2,question:"Upon contact with humans, a horned lizard ----. ",choices:["is often hunted by collectors due to being confusedwith other reptiles","attacks humans in an effort to defend its territory","is likely to be run over because it does not move whenin danger","immediately changes its original shape and colour","tries to escape by crawling rather than moving fast"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:' More mythology surrounds the shark than any other creatures in the ocean. This is partly a symptom of their colossal size \u2013 adult male great whites can measure in excess of five metres; the temptation for humans to add a metre here or there after reported sightings is irresistable. Sharks are also, by nature, mysterious. Scientists still know next to nothing about great whites\u2019 breeding habits; a birth in the wild has never been observed. One of the biggest great white shark myths is that the creature, disabled by its notoriously poor vision, often mistakes surfers and scuba-divers for its main prey \u2013 seals and sea lions. "Completely false," says Richard Aidan Martin, director of the ReefQuest Centre for Shark Research in Vancouver, Canada. After observing 1,000 predatory attacks on sea lions by great whites for five years, he states that the sharks rocket to the surface and crush their prey with incredible force; however, they usually approach humans with leisurely or undramatic behaviour. Martin points out that great whites are curious and investigative animals, which is what most people do not realise. When great whites bite something unfamiliar to them, whether a person or a sea creature, they are looking for tactile evidence about what it is. They usually throw humans out of their mouth after an exploratory bite rather than swallow them for food because humans are too bony. To add more, great whites must be extremely selective about their diet. Their digestive tracts function very slowly, and eating the wrong thing would slow the shark down for days and stop them from consuming anything else.',questions:[{number:51,answer:0,question:"It is understood from the passage that great whites ----.",choices:["have hardly ever been examined in terms of their breeding habits","are mysterious because why they mainly prey on seals and sea lions has not been clarified","are giant creatures whose size can never be measured exactly","have been studied more extensively than any other creatures in the ocean","have unusual breeding habits to which scientists have been paying particular attention"]},{number:52,answer:3,question:"It is emphasised in the passage that Richard Aidan Martin ----.",choices:["monitored great whites mistaking surfers and scuba-divers for seals and sea lions","focused especially on the disadvantages of great whites\u2019 notoriously poor vision","examined attacks on sea lions by great whites to prove their aggressive nature","noted that great whites do not come closer to humans in an actively predatory way","tried to collect precise information on great whites by observing 1,000 attacks on humans"]},{number:53,answer:4,question:"Which of the following is pointed out in the passage?",choices:["Great whites confuse humans with seals and sea lions due to their low ability to see.","Great whites bite humans to explore if their bones are to their taste.","Great whites are often incapable of choosing the right food for their diet.","Great whites avoid biting humans and sea creatures that are unfamiliar to them.","Great whites` diet does not include humans because they have too much bone for them."]},{number:54,answer:1,question:"Which could be the best title for this passage? ",choices:["The Extraordinary Diet of Great Whites","The Unknown World of Great Whites","Deadly Attacks of Great Whites on Humans","The Impressive Size of Great Whites","Enormous Diversity of Great Whites\u2019 Prey"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"The story of Hansel and Gretel, in which two children outsmart a witch who is about to destroy them, was passed down to us from the brothers Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm. They began recording various folk tales told to them by villagers and farmers near the town of Kassel, Germany, in about 1807. Hansel and Gretel was told to the brothers by a young girl, Doretchen Wild, who years later became Wilhelm Grimm`s wife. The fairy tale gained wide popularity after German composer Engelbert Humperdinck made it the basis of a children`s opera, first introduced in Munich in 1893. However, the opera, as well as subsequent versions of the story, omits the most traumatising aspect of the traditional tale: the parents\u2019 deliberate abandonment of their children to the wild beasts of the forest. Another important feature of Hansel and Gretel is that it was not only known through German oral tradition. A version circulating in France as early as the late 17th century had a house made not of gingerbread but of gold and jewels, in which a young girl is held by a giant whom she eventually pushes into his own fire. However, it was the Grimm brothers who immortalised the tale for future generations \u2013 an excellent story that every child throughout the world should come across.",questions:[{number:55,answer:3,question:"Which of the following can be said about the story of Hansel and Gretel?",choices:["It was initially written by the Grimm brothers and became very popular in a short time.","It illustrates the dangers faced by two children who lived in Kassel, Germany, in about 1807.","It reveals the typical features of German culture because it is told by villagers and farmers.","It was verbally transferred to the Grimm brothers like some other stories.","It was told by Doretchen Wild to the villagers and farmers in Kassel, Germany."]},{number:56,answer:3,question:"What can be understood about Humperdinck?",choices:["He was criticised for presenting Hansel and Gretel differently from the previous versions of it.","He intentionally highlighted some details of Hansel and Gretel to increase its popularity.","He reached a large audience especially attracted to the opera but not to the story of Hansel and Gretel.","He made Hansel and Gretel quite famous by producing a children`s opera inspired by the story.","He removed the traumatising part of Hansel and Gretel to create a more cheerful story."]},{number:57,answer:3,question:"The saddest part of Hansel and Gretel is that ----.",choices:["a giant in France is pushed into a fire by a little girl","the children`s parents are not aware of the dangers of wild beasts in the forest","the parents do not care for their children and cause them to get caught by a witch","despite the presence of wild beasts, the children are left alone in the forest without any concern","a young girl is captured in a giant`s house"]},{number:58,answer:1,question:"What is the Grimm brothers` impact on the story of Hansel and Gretel?",choices:["They gave inspiration to many other arts, and showed a fairy tale can be a product of popular culture.","They recorded one of the diverse versions of the story and made it universally known as a children`s literature must-read.","They added a new dimension to children`s literature by telling a story which has wild beasts and witches trying to catch children.","They proved that the important thing is to record a story so it can be used in other cultural activities.","They showed that traumatising events can be used as instructions for children."]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:'In Bertrand Piccard`s family, there is a tradition of being first. His grandfather, Auguste, was the first person to ride a balloon into the stratosphere. His father, Jacques, was the first to reach the Earth`s deepest point, the Pacific`s Mariana Trench. And in 1999, Piccard completed the first non-stop, around-the-world balloon flight. This feat, plus an environmentally conscious approach to innovation, spurred the renowned Swiss adventurer to dream of circumnavigating the globe in a plane that uses no fuel. The result is the Solar Impulse 2, an aircraft equipped with more than 17,000 solar cells. Thanks to lithium batteries that efficiently store energy reserves, it is the first solar-powered plane that can fly through the night. "If we want to solve our pollution and energy problems," says Piccard, a psychiatrist by training, "we need to increase our energy efficiency and focus on clean technologies. Solar Impulse 2 is really a way to show that those technologies are mature."',questions:[{number:59,answer:1,question:"What can be inferred about Piccard\u2019s father and grandfather?",choices:["They preferred to follow their dreams rather than have careers.","They were not afraid of taking risks and pursuing their dreams.","They were both renowned scientists in their fields. ","They were very supportive of Piccard\u2019s ambitions.","They were just as concerned about the environment as Piccard."]},{number:60,answer:2,question:"What motivated Piccard to fly around the world in a solar-powered plane?",choices:["His desire to follow in his family\u2019s footsteps and continue their tradition of being first","His awareness of the need to develop environmentally friendly, cost-effective engineering","His previous success and his desire to be environmentally friendly","His attempt to make the world\u2019s first balloon flight","His knowledge of green technologies and his family\u2019s concern about pollution and energy problems"]},{number:61,answer:2,question:"What is clearly stated as being unique about Piccard\u2019s aircraft?",choices:["It has more solar cells than any aircraft built before it. ","It runs completely on the cleanest lithium batteries. ","It has very efficient energy storage means, which will allow it to fly at night.","It uses solar cells for power, allowing it to fly without fuel or the need to ever stop.","It reserves all the energy it gains from the solar cells in lithium batteries."]},{number:62,answer:3,question:"In Piccard\u2019s own words, what is the main purpose of Solar Impulse 2?",choices:["To show that a plane with no fuel is able to fly around the world","To indicate that more needs to be done to further develop solar-powered planes","To contribute to the improvement of lithium batteries\u2019 efficiency","To demonstrate that the technology available today is ready to help solve pollution and energy problems","To prepare the world for the next generation of clean technologies"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the dialogue.",questions:[{number:63,answer:0,question:"Reporter:\n- Kids love to eat hamburgers, but they`re not very healthy. Tell us about the public school initiative to make lunches healthier for students.\nDietician:\n- With some help from food engineers, we`ve created a mushroom-beef blend that`s being used in schools across the country to help students eat healthier. Reporter:\n- ---- \nDietician:\n- True. In addition to fewer calories and saturated fats than regular hamburgers, this blend is also a greener alternative to meat since mushrooms are more sustainable than beef. \nReporter:\n- That makes sense as they require fewer resources than livestock to produce.",choices:["I think there are more than just health benefits to using this vegetable and meat blend.","It seems that the health benefits are the most positive thing about this vegetable and meat blend.","As far as I understand, blending mushrooms with beef requires some careful procedures.","I don`t think this is a more sustainable alternative to traditional meat hamburgers.","Great! I think students will like eating this vegetable and meat blend at lunch."]},{number:64,answer:3,question:"Researcher:\n- From your documentary, we learned that Princess Diana secretly collaborated with journalist Andrew Morton to write a book about her life, in which he discloses details of her troubled relations with the royal family.\nDocumentarist:\n- Well, when the book was published in 1992, Diana\u2019s cooperation was a secret. But, when Morton republished the book after her death in 1997, he exposed the fact that Diana herself was the direct source for many revelations in the book.\nReporter:\n- ----\nDocumentarist:\n- He wanted to bring an important fact to light; the Princess herself wanted the public to know she was not living a fairy tale, but a life of misery.",choices:["Why did Morton\u2019s book change the way the world looked at the royal family?","Do you think the public was as deeply affected as Morton by Diana\u2019s death?","How could Morton convince people that his book was based on Diana\u2019s own words?","What may have prompted Morton to reveal Diana\u2019s involvement in the publication?","How did Morton deal with the criticism from the royal family and the British media?"]},{number:65,answer:4,question:"Journalist:\n- You\u2019re the co-leader of an international project to drill for rock samples in the South China Sea. Why is that sea bed of such interest?\nGeophysicist:\n- We want to answer questions about when it was formed to better understand continental movements.\nJournalist:\n- ----\nGeophysicist:\nWe also plan to study the microbiology of the ocean crust to see if there are new organisms at these great depths.",choices:["What key questions do you hope to answer? ","What kind of rocks do you expect to find? ","How will you determine how old the rocks are? ","What methods are you going to use to collect all these samples?","What other things may this study help us understand?"]},{number:66,answer:3,question:"Professor:\n- And here you see a picture of a little devil frog. The male produces noisy sounds in pursuit of a partner.\nStudent:\n- ----\nProfessor:\n- Well, he`s a poisonous frog and has bright colours which warn predators that he`s unsafe to eat.\nStudent:\n- How significant characteristics it has!",choices:["Do the sounds he makes differ or does he use the same kind of sounds?","How do the partners react to these sounds when they hear them?","Is it really difficult for the little devil frog to find a partner?","But doesn`t it make him noticeable and vulnerable to being attacked?","Is it only males, or do females also produce such sounds before mating?"]},{number:67,answer:1,question:"Matthew:\n- A friend of mine plays in an orchestra and has invited me to their concert. I\u2019m really nervous because I don\u2019t know anything about orchestras.\nJudy:\n- Actually, most people don\u2019t know much about orchestras. Just pay attention to the instrument categories, and then you\u2019ll be less worried.\nMatthew:\n- ----\nJudy:\n- Well, each group sits together. First, you have the strings. Woodwinds are in the following section. Behind them are the brass instruments, and at the back is the percussion section.",choices:["How do you know the features of all these categories? Have you ever taken a course about orchestras?","How exactly is a typical orchestra organised? If I learn that at least, maybe I can relax and enjoy the performance.","As far as I know, you\u2019ve attended several concerts before. Can you predict what will attract me most at the concert?","What do you know about the percussion section? I think that\u2019s the section my friend plays in. So, please tell me about it.","I don\u2019t even know the name of instruments played in an orchestra. Are there many different instruments?"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best rephrased form of the given sentence.",questions:[{number:68,answer:3,question:"While in Holland, John Locke had time to complete a number of important works that established his reputation as England\u2019s foremost political theorist.",choices:["Whereas John Locke wrote many of his important works in Holland, he earned a reputation as the most important political theorist in England.","John Locke, who was famous for being England\u2019s principal political theorist, spent some time in Holland to produce some of his most important works.","His stay in Holland, during which he completed most of his important works, helped John Locke to be accepted as one of the most significant political theorists of England.","Thanks to several important works he finished during his stay in Holland, John Locke made quite a name for himself as the leading political theorist of England.","It was the countless important works he finalised in Holland that earned him a name as one of the most prominent political theorists in England."]},{number:69,answer:2,question:"Delicately carved from mammoth tusk, the Lady of Brassempouy was discovered in southwest France in 1894 and is among the oldest representations of a human face.",choices:["The oldest representation of a human`s face is an 1894 mammoth tusk, delicate carving of the Lady of Brassempouy, which was found in southwest France.","The Lady of Brassempouy, representing the oldest human face, was made from gently carved mammoth tusk and unearthed in southwest France in 1894.","Found in 1894 in southwest France, the Lady of Brassempouy is one of the oldest representations of a human face, gently carved from the tusk of a mammoth.","Amongst many delicate mammoth tusk carvings of the human face, the Lady of Brassempouy is the oldest and its discovery was made in southwest France in 1894.","One of the oldest delicate human face carvings, the Lady of Brassempouy was identified in 1894 to be made of mammoth tusk in southwest France."]},{number:70,answer:3,question:"While professional advertisers scoff at the idea, the general public seems to assume that subliminal advertising is widely and effectively practiced.",choices:["Despite the fact that professional advertisers ridicule the public for believing in the widespread and efficient use of subliminal advertising, the public still insists on doing so.","As professional advertisers praise this concept, an increasing portion of the population also believes that subliminal advertising is commonly and efficiently used.","Professional advertisers appear to be praising the idea that subliminal advertising is generally practiced, an assumption commonly held by the general public.","It appears that ordinary people believe subliminal advertising is extensively and successfully carried out although professional advertisers laugh at this notion.","The general population thinks that there are some people who make use of subliminal advertising efficiently; however, professional advertisers seem to think the opposite."]},{number:71,answer:4,question:"The years following the 1789 revolution in France brought massive upheaval in French society, which, in turn, produced profound changes in dress and fashion.",choices:["Although the revolution took place in France in 1789, it was only after many years that French society went through considerable changes in dress and fashion following this great disturbance in their society.","The revolution in France in 1789 led to a serious disturbance among people in French society, and this was the reason why the French had to allow for fundamental and important changes in dress and fashion.","If it were not for the revolution in France in 1789, dress and fashion in French society might not have changed considerably despite the enormous disturbance it caused in their society.","What contributed to the revolution in France in 1789 were the major changes in dress and fashion, which resulted from the huge confusion experienced by French society at that time.","It was not until after the revolution in France in 1789 that French society experienced dramatic changes in dress and fashion, due to the enormous turmoil generated by this period."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the missing part of the passage.",questions:[{number:72,answer:4,question:"It has been a basic tenet that an individual who uses substances heavily will become addicted. There are reports, however, of people becoming addicted to a substance with exposure only once or a few times. Some experts believe people are born with the predisposition to become addicted. ---- Thus, the potential for addiction may be hereditary. On the other hand, a psychological problem may lead the individual into addiction. The need for instant gratification, a feeling of being socially ostracized, and an inability to cope with the downfalls of life have all been cited as possible springboards to addiction.",choices:["One characteristic that marks addiction, whether to chemicals or nonchemical practices, is the genetic modification it leads to.","A careful medically-controlled withdrawal program can reverse the chemical changes in genes caused by the addiction.","Habitual use of an addictive substance can produce changes in body chemistry and any treatment must be geared to a gradual reduction in dosage.","Studies have found that many former addicts have enough determination to avoid drugs for the rest of their lives.","Children of addicts have a greater probability of becoming addicts themselves than children whose parents are not."]},{number:73,answer:1,question:"In almost all cultures and societies, children have collected a broad spectrum of items. Although the activity seems to be universal, very little has been written on this subject. And even though collecting has played an important part in many individuals\u2019 lives, it is seldom described in memoirs or autobiographies. This may be because many collections are suddenly abandoned when the collector grows up. ---- Other collections, however, continue into adult life, becoming lifelong passionate occupations; this is especially likely with collections that have some kind of economic value or present the adult with challenges or opportunities for further study.",choices:["Most children will carry on adding to their collections throughout adulthood because they are so attached to them.","Many are often split up and disappear during childhood unless parents understand the fascinating world of the small collector and pay special attention to saving them.","The spirit of the collector, once established, never leaves the individual but is turned in new directions and can result in life-changing career choices.","Grand collections may end up in places like museums, which seems to be the dream of collectors who do not want their passionate investments to disappear with them.","Collecting trains the eye, creates a sense of order, and develops aesthetic appreciation, while at the same time creating a sense of economic appreciation for certain items."]},{number:74,answer:3,question:"Fossils are remnants or traces of an animal or plant of a past geologic age that have been preserved in various ways in the Earth\u2019s crust. From earliest times people must have seen fossils, but the first reports we have on the subject are from the ancient Greeks. Xenophanes of the early Ionian school is said to have noticed fossilised sea creatures high on mountains; he correctly interpreted this as meaning that these mountains had once been under water. ---- For example, he associated the fossilised bones of large creatures with mythical animals or with giant humans.",choices:["In the 17th century, Nicolaus Steno argued persuasively that fossils are remains of living organisms.","In Roman times, Suetonius casually mentions that the emperor Augustus kept a collection of large fossil bones in his villa.","The famous scholar Avicenna put forward an idea that confused people about fossils for centuries.","Later, Herodotus reached the same conclusion regarding fossilized clam shells, but he misinterpreted other fossils.","Theophrastus, Aristotle\u2019s successor, is said to have written a book on fossils, which was lost later, where he refers to fossilised fish."]},{number:75,answer:3,question:"According to a World Bank report in 1993, the East Asian miracle, achieving high economic growth for all people, is due to a combination of fundamentally sound development policies, tailored interventions, and an unusually rapid increase of physical and human capital. The more advanced economies in the Asian region are part of this success and have been referred to as high-performing East Asian economies. ---- In addition, these economies have displayed high per capita incomes, along with a much-improved income distribution, compared with most other developing economies.",choices:["In contrast, the dramatic growth of the Asian tiger economies has been based on the export of manufactured goods.","Poorer countries have greater difficulty than relatively richer countries climbing up the ladder of development.","The study suggests that economies with a strong inward focus could not succeed.","Such economies have a record of high and sustained economic growth.","Promoting trade is positively related to levels of per capita income."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the irrelevant sentence in the passage.",questions:[{number:76,answer:2,question:"(I) Across the globe, people greeted the end of World War II with a profound sense of relief. (II) By virtually any measurement, the war had been the most devastating conflict in human history. (III) The more traditional and more widely accepted date for the start of World War II is 1 September 1939, with the quick but not quite blitzkrieg (lightning) German invasion of Poland. (IV) The war\u2019s economic cost alone has been calculated at perhaps five times that of World War I. (V) In human terms, it claimed half again as many military lives: 15 million versus 10 million for World War I.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:77,answer:3,question:"(I) The idea of the human mind as the domain of absolute protection from external intrusion has persisted for centuries. (II) Today, however, this presumption might no longer hold. (III) Sophisticated neuro-imaging machines detect the electrical activity of neurons, enabling us to decode and even alter the nervous system signals that accompany mental processes. (IV) Medical devices connected to the brain are vulnerable to sabotage, and neuroscientists suggest that the same vulnerability applies to brain implants. (V) Whereas these advances have a great potential for research and medicine, they pose a fundamental ethical, legal and social challenge: determining under what conditions it is legitimate to gain access to another person\u2019s neural activity.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:78,answer:0,question:"(I) The best conditions for dandelion seeds are relatively calm, sunny days that generate thermal updraughts. (II) A 2003 study at the University of Regensburg in Germany found that 99.5 percent of dandelion seeds land within 10 metres of their plant. (III) That is because the seed `parachute` falls at about 30 cm per second and dandelions only grow about 30 cm high. (IV) So, that gives each seed just one second of flight time to be blown sideways by the wind to its new home. (V) Higher wind speeds do not really increase the distance the seeds fly, because strong winds tend to blow downwards as well as sideways, so the seeds just land even sooner.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:79,answer:3,question:"(I) The conventional wisdom is that it is a molecule`s specific shape that allows our noses to distinguish between one smell and another. (II) But there is new evidence that it is actually the frequency of a molecule`s vibration, a quantum effect, that is all-important. (III) Most olfactory (smell) scientists believe that receptors within our noses act like a lock that can only be activated by a molecule of a specific shape \u2013 the `key`. (IV) Molecules are collections of atoms that can be thought of as being connected by springs that can vibrate. (V) The trouble is, some molecules with different shapes have similar smells.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:80,answer:1,question:"(I) Established on 7 April 1948, the World Health Organisation (WHO) is one of the original agencies of the United Nations. (II) WHO defines health not merely as the absence of disease or illness, but as a state of complete physical, mental, and social well-being. (III) Headquartered in Geneva, Switzerland, WHO was set up to improve international cooperation for better health conditions across the world. (IV) It took over from the Health Organisation of the League of Nations and the International Public Office of Health in Paris. (V) Those two organisations had focused on the control of epidemics, quarantine measures, and the standardisation of drugs.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]}]}]},{routeName:"2017-Fall",items:[{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the space.",questions:[{number:1,answer:2,question:"Some ethnic minority groups of students within the US, such as African Americans and Hispanic Americans, achieve below the national average of all students; however, one ---- is the high educational achievements demonstrated by Asian American students.",choices:["aspiration","defect","exception","influence","complaint"]},{number:2,answer:2,question:"Without artificial fertilisers and pesticides, there would not be enough food grown on Earth to satisfy our needs, even with equal ---- of agricultural output.",choices:["recognition","deterioration","distribution","fluctuation","reduction"]},{number:3,answer:0,question:"An important reason to re-evaluate how we are raising the next generation grows out of an incredibly exciting discovery about brain development: during adolescence, the brain\u2019s potential to change through experience is ----.",choices:["tremendous","frustrating","debatable","redundant","exhausted"]},{number:4,answer:4,question:"Children and adolescents with attention deficit or hyperactivity disorder frequently experience difficulties in school settings, most ---- in the areas of academic achievement and interpersonal relationships.",choices:["appropriately","urgently","subtly","compulsorily","notably"]},{number:5,answer:0,question:"Children who grow up in two-parent homes where the parents are non-traditional in their own gender roles ---- less gender-stereotypic behaviour than do children whose parents are traditional in their role enactment.",choices:["display","alter","achieve","reject","eradicate"]},{number:6,answer:1,question:"When Columbus sailed west from Spain in 1492 in pursuit of the riches of the Far East, he ---- recent advances in navigation and age-old geographical knowledge.",choices:["kept off","drew on","put forward","gave away","brought about"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word(s) or expression(s) to fill the space(s).",questions:[{number:7,answer:3,question:"In 1517, the Italian physician Girolamo Fracastoro was probably the first person ---- that fossils are animal remains; however, it was not until the 18th century that scientists ---- to realise that fossils can tell us a great deal about the history of living things.",choices:["suggesting / had begun","being suggested / were beginning","to have suggested / have begun","to suggest / began","having suggested / were going to begin"]},{number:8,answer:3,question:"The technological advancements that once made nations prosperous, such as the internal combustion engine, ---- to shatter empires during the First World War, on a scale few people ---- before the outbreak of the war.",choices:["had been used / should have imagined","should have been used / used to imagine","would have been used / might have imagined","were used / could have imagined","must have been used / can imagine"]},{number:9,answer:3,question:"Tomatoes are so widely consumed that they represent a vehicle ---- beneficial nutrients to those who ---- expensive seasonal berries.",choices:["having introduced / would not afford","introducing / could not afford","to have introduced / may not afford","to introduce / cannot afford","being introduced / might not afford"]},{number:10,answer:0,question:"Early mastery of fire offered many benefits to humankind, including protection ---- wild animals, heat that enabled them to spread ---- cooler regions, and the ability to cook food.",choices:["against / into","from / by","to / over","for / along","on / towards"]},{number:11,answer:1,question:"Anschluss, the political union of Germany and Austria, was specifically prohibited ---- the Versailles Treaty, but was carried out by Hitler in March 1938 ---- any resistance from the victors of the First World War.",choices:["across / through","under / without","for / on","from / behind","to / about"]},{number:12,answer:3,question:"Home-grown produce tastes better than grocery store produce ---- it is freshly picked and perfectly ripe, which shines through even when cooked or preserved.",choices:["although","whereas","whether","because","unless"]},{number:13,answer:4,question:"---- there have been dozens of proposals for gender-neutral third-person pronouns in English over the past two centuries, none has gained acceptance.",choices:["Now that","As long as","In case","Once","Even though"]},{number:14,answer:3,question:"The story of the cat\u2019s domestication is one of mutual appreciation: early farming communities benefited from cats\u2019 rodent-catching skills ---- cats won themselves protection and shelter without losing their independence.",choices:["even if","only when","as soon as","while","before"]},{number:15,answer:2,question:"In most cultures around the world, men and women typically differ in a number of ways ---- physical appearance, personality traits, and occupational preferences.",choices:["in case of","in spite of","such as","similar to","as well as"]},{number:16,answer:3,question:"19th-century scientists fell into a bitter debate as to ---- intelligence lay in anatomy ---- a vital force was responsible for thoughts.",choices:["as / as","neither / nor","so / that","whether / or","not only / but also"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:"In the 1960s, people had greater employment opportunities and a new buying power. ---- this growing affluence, music and fashion became mass-market industries and were quick to cater to the demands of the youth market. The growing popularity of television helped to spread popular culture throughout the world, ---- new trends could develop rapidly. Programmes such as Top of the Pops in the UK and The Ed Sullivan Show in the US could lead people ---- considerable attention to pop music. In 1962, the Beatles emerged from Liverpool`s Cavern Club. Their first album Please Please Me became very famous ---- the globe within a year. They grew ---- popular, sparking such intense devotion in their fans that it became known as `Beatlemania`.",questions:[{number:17,answer:2,question:"---- this growing affluence, music and fashion became mass-market industries and were quick to cater to the demands of the youth market.",choices:["Instead of","Rather than","As a result of","Contrary to","Regardless of"]},{number:18,answer:4,question:"The growing popularity of television helped to spread popular culture throughout the world, ---- new trends could develop rapidly.",choices:["though","otherwise","instead","just as","so"]},{number:19,answer:3,question:"Programmes such as Top of the Pops in the UK and The Ed Sullivan Show in the US could lead people ---- considerable attention to pop music.",choices:["to be paid","having paid","to have paid","to pay","being paid"]},{number:20,answer:1,question:"Their first album Please Please Me became very famous ---- the globe within a year.",choices:["from","around","toward","into","about"]},{number:21,answer:4,question:"They grew ---- popular, sparking such intense devotion in their fans that it became known as `Beatlemania`.",choices:["slightly","coincidentally","steadily","equally","immensely"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:"Since ancient times, architecture has been considered the \u2018mother\u2019 of the arts. (22)---- music, painting, and sculpture that exist in a way separate from life, architecture incorporates life. People and their activities are an (23)---- component of architecture, not merely as spectators to be entertained but as contributors and participants. Painters, sculptors, and composers of music (24)---- about how their viewers or audience never see or hear their art in quite the same way as it was conceived, or that is interpreted or displayed in ways that affect its innate character. However, they have control (25)---- the essence of their work and that essence is, in a way, tightly sealed within the object: the musical score, the covers of a book or the picture frame. (26)----, even the essence of architecture is realised by the people whose activities it influences.",questions:[{number:22,answer:2,question:"---- music, painting, and sculpture that exist in a way separate from life, architecture incorporates life.",choices:["As well as","By means of","As opposed to","In terms of","Because of"]},{number:23,answer:3,question:"People and their activities are an ---- component of architecture, not merely as spectators to be entertained but as contributors and participants.",choices:["impoverished","immeasurable","unreasonable","indispensable","unintentional"]},{number:24,answer:1,question:"Painters, sculptors, and composers of music ---- about how their viewers or audience never see or hear their art in quite the same way as it was conceived, or that is interpreted or displayed in ways that affect its innate character.",choices:["would have complained","may complain","should complain","must have complained","used to complain"]},{number:25,answer:1,question:"However, they have control ---- the essence of their work and that essence is, in a way, tightly sealed within the object: the musical score, the covers of a book or the picture frame.",choices:["about","over","against","from","with"]},{number:26,answer:4,question:"----, even the essence of architecture is realised by the people whose activities it influences.",choices:["Otherwise","Unfortunately","For instance","Therefore","On the contrary"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the given sentence.",questions:[{number:27,answer:2,question:"---- until they are considered ready to switch to English.",choices:["Around 2.6 million school-aged children throughout the US do not speak English at all","It is difficult for bilingual teachers to help their students improve their native language skills in some subjects","In transitional bilingual education, students are taught academic subjects in their native languages","The language rights of ethnic minorities in the US have been a source of public controversy for decades","Most people who are opposed to bilingualism are part of the English-only movement"]},{number:28,answer:4,question:"Though China began as a small empire centred on the Great Bend of the Yellow River, ----.",choices:["almost all of what we know about its culture comes from the wealthy classes","the emperor of China, believed to have descended from the gods, was at the top of society","it was with the Shang dynasty that people began to keep written records of Chinese history","kings of local areas gained more power and sometimes fought among themselves","it expanded considerably over time to become quite a vast kingdom"]},{number:29,answer:0,question:"While scientists are pretty certain that black holes exist, ----.",choices:["they have never observed one directly, let alone gotten in near proximity of one","they are defined as areas in space from which nothing can escape","it has been long known that the gravity there is intensely strong","they can be produced in supernova explosions, marking the death of a star","they use quantum rules to show that black holes must evaporate"]},{number:30,answer:3,question:"Even though parchment was more difficult to produce and more expensive than papyrus, ----.",choices:["the king of Egypt stopped exporting papyrus to Pergamum, fearing that Pergamum`s great library might overshadow that of Alexandria","the finest parchments, especially those made from the skins of very young animals, were called `vellum`","parchment was made from the skins of sheep and goats while papyrus was made from the stems of the papyrus plant","it was Europe`s favoured writing material until the 14th-century advances in paper making","among the most famous medieval manuscripts written on parchment is the stunning Tre\u0300s Riches Heures of the Duc de Berry"]},{number:31,answer:2,question:"Although the science of geology as we know it today is a relatively young field, ----.",choices:["it basically refers to the scientific study of rocks and soil","it is a vast field, stretching from palaeontology to mineralogy","insightful observations of the Earth`s processes dates back to the ancient Greeks","many geologists think there are some truths that work most of the time","many of the processes attached to geology cannot be used for measurement in all situations"]},{number:32,answer:4,question:"Preventing children`s academic failure means developing individuals who are able to contribute to the common good; ----.",choices:["yet, some types of academic failure prevention call for an increased emphasis on arithmetic skills","nevertheless, causes of academic failure include socioeconomic and cultural issues","accordingly, academic failure has recently come to mean a failure to acquire basic literacy skills","on the contrary, a positive family environment is very important in preventing academic failure","thus, the prevention of academic failure should be a primary concern for any society"]},{number:33,answer:3,question:"----, we regularly leave digital traces of our economic standing when expressing ourselves through posts on social media.",choices:["In order that people can stay away from the negative effects of the Internet","Unless we talk about business, politics and non-profit work with others","No matter we reveal our own personal information online","Although money is a topic that most of us avoid discussing publicly","Since more than half of the Internet users stay away from using social media actively"]},{number:34,answer:0,question:"Early humans had no explanation for the existence of a vast array of substances and their transformations, ----.",choices:["so they could only attribute chemical phenomena to the acts of the gods","but the first step to modern chemistry was the recognition of the fact that atoms existed","as they were able to observe various materials on Earth and predict their future forms","because chemical researchers identified the building blocks of matter in modern times","for they could interpret chemical changes between substances in a small amount of time"]},{number:35,answer:2,question:"----, the illness can present itself at any stage of life.",choices:["As cultural pressures foster both unhealthy dieting and anorexia","Even though anorexia is often claimed to overlap with clinical depression","While there is certainly a prevalence of anorexia in teenagers","If a lack of serotonin has a causal effect on the existence of anorexia","Despite the common belief that anorexia is the result of an abnormality in the brain"]},{number:36,answer:2,question:"World Space Week takes place every year in October, ----.",choices:["so World Space Week 2016 has been, by far, the largest space celebration in history","because you do not have to be an astronaut to be part of the global celebration of World Space Week","and it has grown into the largest public space event on Earth since its declaration by the United Nations","but it can be a great framework for countries and agencies to foster space exploration","while the Mexican Space Agency has been an important promoter of World Space Week"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the most accurate Turkish translation of the sentences in English, and the most accurate English translation of the sentences in Turkish.",questions:[{number:37,answer:3,question:"New Zealand, separated from other land masses, has unique plant and animal species, which are vulnerable to the impacts of non-native species.",choices:["Es\u0327siz bitki ve hayvan tu\u0308rlerinin bulundug\u0306u Yeni Zelanda dig\u0306er kara parc\u0327alar\u0131ndan ayr\u0131d\u0131r, dolay\u0131s\u0131yla bu tu\u0308rler yabanc\u0131 tu\u0308rlerin etkilerine kars\u0327\u0131 savunmas\u0131zd\u0131r.","Yeni Zelanda\u2019n\u0131n dig\u0306er kara parc\u0327alar\u0131ndan ayr\u0131 olmas\u0131, es\u0327siz bitki ve hayvan tu\u0308rlerini yabanc\u0131 tu\u0308rlerin etkilerine kars\u0327\u0131 savunmas\u0131z ha\u0302le getirmis\u0327tir.","Yeni Zelanda dig\u0306er kara parc\u0327alar\u0131ndan ayr\u0131lm\u0131s\u0327 olsa da yabanc\u0131 tu\u0308rlerin etkilerine kars\u0327\u0131 savunmas\u0131z ha\u0302lde bulunan es\u0327siz bitki ve hayvan tu\u0308rlerine sahiptir.","Dig\u0306er kara parc\u0327alar\u0131ndan ayr\u0131 olan Yeni Zelanda, yabanc\u0131 tu\u0308rlerin etkilerine kars\u0327\u0131 savunmas\u0131z ha\u0302lde bulunan es\u0327siz bitki ve hayvan tu\u0308rlerine sahiptir.","Yeni Zelanda dig\u0306er kara parc\u0327alar\u0131ndan ayr\u0131 oldug\u0306u ic\u0327in burada bulunan es\u0327siz bitki ve hayvan tu\u0308rleri, yabanc\u0131 tu\u0308rlerin etkilerine kars\u0327\u0131 savunmas\u0131zd\u0131r."]},{number:38,answer:0,question:"Believing that sports could be used to promote peace between countries, the French aristocrat Pierre de Coubertin organised the first modern Olympic Games in Athens, in 1896.",choices:["Frans\u0131z aristokrat Pierre de Coubertin, sporun u\u0308lkeler aras\u0131ndaki bar\u0131s\u0327a o\u0308nayak olmas\u0131 ic\u0327in kullan\u0131labileceg\u0306ine inanarak 1896`da Atina`da ilk modern Olimpiyat Oyunlar\u0131`n\u0131 du\u0308zenledi.","1896`da, sporun u\u0308lkeler aras\u0131ndaki bar\u0131s\u0327a o\u0308nayak olmas\u0131 ic\u0327in kullan\u0131labileceg\u0306i inanc\u0131yla ilk modern Olimpiyat Oyunlar\u0131`n\u0131 du\u0308zenleyen kis\u0327i Frans\u0131z aristokrat Pierre de Coubertin`dir.","Frans\u0131z aristokrat Pierre de Coubertin, spor arac\u0131l\u0131g\u0306\u0131yla u\u0308lkeler aras\u0131ndaki bar\u0131s\u0327a o\u0308nayak olunabileceg\u0306ine inanarak 1896`da Atina`da ilk modern Olimpiyat Oyunlar\u0131`n\u0131 du\u0308zenledi.","Frans\u0131z aristokrat Pierre de Coubertin, sporun u\u0308lkeler aras\u0131ndaki bar\u0131s\u0327a o\u0308nayak olabileceg\u0306ine inand\u0131g\u0306\u0131 ic\u0327in 1896`da Atina`da ilk modern Olimpiyat Oyunlar\u0131`n\u0131n du\u0308zenlenmesini sag\u0306lad\u0131.","I\u0307lk modern Olimpiyat Oyunlar\u0131`n\u0131n 1896`da du\u0308zenlenmesi, Frans\u0131z aristokrat Pierre de Coubertin`in sporun u\u0308lkeler aras\u0131ndaki bar\u0131s\u0327a o\u0308nayak olmas\u0131 ic\u0327in kullan\u0131labileceg\u0306i du\u0308s\u0327u\u0308ncesine dayan\u0131r."]},{number:39,answer:1,question:"Originally imported from China in the 12th century, tea has been a significant component of Japanese culture ever since.",choices:["12. yu\u0308zy\u0131ldan beri Japon ku\u0308ltu\u0308ru\u0308nu\u0308n o\u0308nemli bir parc\u0327as\u0131 olan c\u0327ay, asl\u0131nda C\u0327in\u2019den getirilmis\u0327tir.","12. yu\u0308zy\u0131lda asl\u0131nda C\u0327in`den getirilen c\u0327ay, o zamandan beri Japon ku\u0308ltu\u0308ru\u0308nu\u0308n o\u0308nemli bir parc\u0327as\u0131 olmus\u0327tur.","Japon ku\u0308ltu\u0308ru\u0308nu\u0308n o\u0308nemli bir parc\u0327as\u0131 olan c\u0327ay, asl\u0131nda 12. yu\u0308zy\u0131ldan beri C\u0327in`den getirilmektedir.","C\u0327ay asl\u0131nda 12. yu\u0308zy\u0131lda C\u0327in`den getirilse de o zamandan beri Japon ku\u0308ltu\u0308ru\u0308nu\u0308n o\u0308nemli bir parc\u0327as\u0131 olmus\u0327tur.","C\u0327ay asl\u0131nda 12. yu\u0308zy\u0131lda C\u0327in\u2019den getirildig\u0306inden beri Japon ku\u0308ltu\u0308ru\u0308nu\u0308n o\u0308nemli bir parc\u0327as\u0131 olmus\u0327tur."]},{number:40,answer:3,question:"Kutup ay\u0131lar\u0131 iklim deg\u0306is\u0327iklig\u0306inin sadece sembolu\u0308 deg\u0306il, ayn\u0131 zamanda her yaz biraz daha seyrekles\u0327en dog\u0306al yas\u0327am alanlar\u0131n\u0131 terk eden as\u0131l kurbanlar\u0131d\u0131r.",choices:["Polar bears are both the symbol of climate change and true victims of it, because they have to leave their habitat which has become sparser every summer.","Climate change is not only responsible for making polar bears a symbol but also a victim of it, as they have to leave their habitat becoming sparser every summer.","Polar bears are known as both the symbol and the victims of climate change since they have to leave their habitat every summer as it becomes sparser.","Polar bears are not just the symbol of climate change but they are also true victims, leaving their habitat which has become sparser each summer.","Polar bears have become the symbol of climate change; however, they are also the victims of it due to the necessity of leaving their habitat every summer."]},{number:41,answer:1,question:"Newton`\u0131n evrensel yer c\u0327ekimi kanunu, Gu\u0308nes\u0327 sistemindeki nesnelerin matematiksel olarak tahmin edilebilir bir dizi kurala go\u0308re hareket ettig\u0306ini go\u0308stermektedir.",choices:["It is shown by Newton`s law of universal gravitation that the objects in the solar system move according to a mathematically predictable set of rules.","Newton\u2019s law of universal gravitation shows that the objects in the solar system move according to a mathematically predictable set of rules.","Newton`s law of universal gravitation shows how the objects in the solar system move according to a mathematically predictable set of rules.","Thanks to Newton`s law of universal gravitation, it is shown that the objects in the solar system move according to a mathematically predictable set of rules.","Newton`s law of universal gravitation shows that the moves of the objects in the solar system are linked to a mathematically predictable set of rules."]},{number:42,answer:0,question:"Besin kaynaklar\u0131n\u0131n dag\u0306\u0131l\u0131m\u0131, bollug\u0306u ve mevsimsellig\u0306i, insanlar\u0131n go\u0308c\u0327ebe veya yerles\u0327ik bir yas\u0327am su\u0308rme tercihini etkilemis\u0327tir.",choices:["The distribution, abundance and seasonality of food resources affected people`s choice to live a nomadic or settled existence.","What affected people`s choice to live a nomadic or settled existence were the distribution, abundance and seasonality of food resources.","People`s choice to live a nomadic or settled existence was affected by the distribution, abundance and seasonality of food resources.","Food resources, with their distribution, abundance and seasonality, affected people`s choice to live a nomadic or settled existence.","People`s choice to live a nomadic or settled existence was affected by food resources, based on their distribution, abundance and seasonality."]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:'Sometimes it feels like the Internet has the answer to everything. At our fingertips, we have the ability to improve our knowledge or test someone`s doubtful "Did you know...?" statement. Our online searches have their limits, though. If we have questions about what is in front of us, the Internet cannot always help. Is this water safe to drink? How much fat is really in this steak? Search engines cannot access these objects, so their answers are limited to averages and tendencies. To get real answers, we must tap into the chemical make-up of our world. The technology to do this exists, but it is limited to immovable pieces of lab kit called near-infrared (NIR) spectrometers. NIR spectrometers work by shining a spectrum of near-infrared light onto objects and analysing the light that bounces back. Say you want to scan an apple. Each substance within the fruit, be it water, sugar, or fibre, will respond to the light in a unique way. The bonds within them will be energised, moving around at specific wavelengths. The spectrometer can detect these wavelengths and then identify what is inside your particular apple. NIR light is also perfectly safe to use, unlike more destructive X-rays or ultraviolet radiation.',questions:[{number:43,answer:2,question:'By asking questions such as "Is this water safe to drink?", what is the author actually trying to say?',choices:["We can expand our knowledge about almost everything by using the Internet.","A great number of questions can be answered thanks to the Internet.","What we can learn through online searches is not endless.","Doubtful statements made by others cannot be exactly clarified by doing online searches.","We can easily discover averages and tendencies via search engines."]},{number:44,answer:0,question:"What is the main function of NIR spectrometers?",choices:["They enable us to examine the chemical structure of objects.","They help scientists explore the chemistry of objects through search engines.","They reply to questions that cannot be answered through the Internet.","They reveal the amount of substances like water and sugar in foods.","They detect whether objects are destroyed by X-rays or ultraviolet radiation."]},{number:45,answer:3,question:"What is the drawback of NIR spectrometers?",choices:["The light they give out can be hazardous.","When the substances in an object respond in the same way, they cannot be distinguished.","Their functions are limited to foods.","They are restricted to laboratory use.","They cannot accurately analyse the light reflected from objects."]},{number:46,answer:4,question:"Which could be the best title for this passage?",choices:["Advantages and Limitations of Search Engines","Are NIR Spectrometers Safe to Use?","Can Wavelengths Be Used with Search Engines?","Choosing the Best Food to Eat through Scanning","Seeing Inside Things through NIR Spectrometers"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"2014 was a landmark year for drug development. The US Food and Drug Administration approved 41 new pharmaceuticals, the most since 1996. Each of these will hopefully make the world a better place, alleviating distress and preventing premature deaths. But developing drugs is incredibly expensive \u2013 and increasingly so. The cost of bringing a new compound to the market is now around $2.5 billion, twice as much in real terms as it was a decade ago. One of the costliest parts is recruiting and retaining volunteers to test the drug in a clinical trial. Around three quarters of trials are delayed by problems with this process. Most trials over-recruit by up to 50 percent to compensate, but the drop-out is still so high that only 1 in 20 volunteers end up generating useful data. The result: wasted time, effort and money. That is not for lack of patient willingness. In 2013, the UK`s House of Commons found that people want to volunteer but do not know how. Yet, volunteers can be brought on board and kept there by making more effort to inform and help them to choose which trial they would like to enter. The problems with volunteer recruitment were identified a decade ago but have not been eradicated. It is high time they were. It is in everyone`s interest to get rid of this unnecessary waste.",questions:[{number:47,answer:4,question:"It is understood from the passage that many participants in clinical trials ----.",choices:["think that their time and effort will be wasted","are recruited again when a clinical trial ultimately fails","have to comply with strict regulations in order to take part in these trials","are well informed about the processes and procedures in these trials","fail to contribute to the production of reliable data on drugs"]},{number:48,answer:3,question:"One can conclude from the passage that the problems of volunteer recruitment ----.",choices:["have been solved using a strategy called `over-recruitment`","show many differences in each clinical trial","are to be solved soon by making up for waste of time in clinical trials","can be reduced by providing people with more guidance on volunteering","have changed a lot in time with respect to their basic characteristics"]},{number:49,answer:3,question:"What is the primary purpose of the author?",choices:["To highlight the number of the drugs introduced to the market in 2014","To explain reasons why developing drugs has become too expensive in recent years","To elaborate on the role that the US Food and Drug Administration plays in developing drugs","To inform readers about some important problems confronted in clinical trials of drugs","To emphasise the health benefits that 41 new pharmaceuticals are expected to yield"]},{number:50,answer:2,question:"Which could be the best title for this passage?",choices:["The Activities of the US Food and Drug Administration","A Variety of Methods of Volunteer Recruitment in Drug Trials","Time to Take Voluntary Participation in Drug Trials Seriously","The Huge Expense of Drug Development","How to Participate in Clinical Trials of Drugs"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Socrates was a classical Greek philosopher whose thoughts had profound influence in his field. Little is known about his early and middle years, although according to ancient tradition, he worked as a stonecutter. The fact that he served as a heavily armed soldier in the Peloponnesian War indicates that during the early years of the war, he was roughly middle class, because men from this social class were required to provide their own armour. At some time during this period, Socrates began the mission of moral reform for which he became famous. He passed his time arguing about various moral subjects that interested him with his fellow Athenians and attempting to inspire them to be virtuous and honourable. Socrates` followers included not only Plato, but Alcibiades and Critias as well, both of whom later undermined the Athenian democracy. Possibly because of such notorious connections, Socrates was accused of impiety \u2013 showing a lack of respect for God \u2013 and corrupting youth. Different versions of the speech he made to defend himself against these accusations still exist today. In his speech, he described himself as a great benefactor to the city, and claimed that the Athenians would harm themselves in killing him. In spite of, or perhaps to some extent because of, his defence, Socrates was convicted, sentenced to death, and executed.",questions:[{number:51,answer:0,question:"Which of the following is certainly true about Socrates?",choices:["His initiation of moral reform earned him a reputation in Athenian society.","Socrates earned his living by selling his ideas to his fellow philosophers.","Socrates became a soldier because he wanted to gain a higher social status.","Socrates took up stonecutting in his early years and practised it until his execution.","One can learn minute details of his whole life because he is a famous philosopher."]},{number:52,answer:4,question:"What could be said about the philosophical tradition of Socrates?",choices:["His ideas fiercely competed with those of Alcibiades and Critias.","His philosophical arguments were heartily welcomed by authorities.","His main philosophical point of view was to debate the legitimacy of the Athenian democracy.","Authorities thought that his prevailing philosophy was in line with religious principles.","He discussed ethical issues with the Athenians to foster respectable behaviours."]},{number:53,answer:0,question:"Which of the following can be inferred based on the speech Socrates made to defend his actions?",choices:["His defence might have had an adverse effect on his chances of survival.","His defence failed just because he had some ill-famed supporters who were strongly condemned by the Athenians.","Although he completely refuted accusations in his defence, he was executed.","He made several spontaneous speeches to defend himself in the court.","He failed to take appropriate action to reject the accusations against him."]},{number:54,answer:3,question:"Which could be the best title for this passage?",choices:["Achievements of the Distinguished Ancient Philosopher Socrates","The Execution of the Leading Greek Philosopher Socrates","Unfounded Accusations Against Socrates","A Life Story of Socrates: From Ideas to Execution","A Soldier Serving as a Philosopher: Socrates"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Body image can be affected by outside influences. Media sources, such as television, the Internet, and magazines, often portray people closer to the commonly accepted ideal body type than the average body image in order to sell their products and services. Consequently, people, especially older children and young adults, are overly influenced by such depictions of body image. Family life can also affect children`s perception of their body image. Parents who criticise how their children look, talk, or act, may often have a negative effect on the development of self-esteem in their children. Young people may also be affected by the comments of classmates and peers when it comes to their body image. Teasing is often a method used by young people to convey negative comments and hurtful words. Common characteristics for being teased include being too small or too large; too smart or too dumb; too popular or not very popular; and any of a number of other personal characterisations. Additionally, young people often try to pressure their peers to conform to what is currently popular in clothing styles, language, and other characteristics \u2013 all that can potentially hurt one`s perception of their body image.",questions:[{number:55,answer:1,question:"What could be inferred about the relationship between the media and body image?",choices:["The body image promoted by the media encourages people to keep up with the latest trends, thus enriching their lives.","The way the media presents body image can badly influence how people see their bodies.","The media presents an ideal body type in order to improve people`s perceptions of their body image.","A great majority of people are aware of how the media affects their perception of body image.","The ideal body type described by the media is harshly criticised by families since it has a negative impact on their children`s self-esteem."]},{number:56,answer:0,question:"It is clearly understood from the passage that young people ----.",choices:["may encounter a lack of self-esteem if they face criticism from their parents","can disregard the influence of parental behaviour on their perception of body image","could get help from their families or peers to improve their perception of body image","tend to follow the latest trends to become much more popular among their peers","are often forced by their peers to follow popular trends, which either improves or harms their perception of body image"]},{number:57,answer:4,question:"According to the author, teasing ----.",choices:["might sometimes be performed by media sources to draw attention to the importance of body image","is generally used by people who are not satisfied with their own body image","is used as a way to communicate both positive and negative comments","is mostly characterised with criticism on wearing outmoded clothes","might concern a great variety of issues related with typical personal features"]},{number:58,answer:3,question:"What is the main idea of the passage?",choices:["Families can improve their children`s body image by criticising them and choosing what is good for them.","It is no use ignoring peer pressure if you want to build a positive perception of body image.","Popular ways of behaving and types of clothing may help young people build a stronger body image.","Various familial and societal factors can influence the perception of body image in young people.","Families and society should stop trying to shape young people`s body image through criticism and teasing."]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"Botany, the study of plants, is one of the major fields of biology, together with zoology and microbiology, and has been around for a very long time. Aristotle and Theophrastus, who lived in ancient Greece around the 4th century BC, were both involved in identifying and describing plants. Theophrastus has been called the `father of botany` due to his two well-known books on plants that are still influential. The early study of plants, however, was not limited to Western cultures. The Chinese developed the study of botany along lines similar to the ancient Greeks at about the same time. In 60 AD, another Greek, Dioscorides, wrote De Materia Medica, a work that described a thousand medicines, 60 percent of which came from plants. It remained the guidebook on medicines in the Western world for 1,500 years until the compound microscope was invented in the late 16th century. During the 17th century, progress was made in plant experimentation. In the 19th century, rapid advances were made in the study of plant diseases after the potato blight that killed potato crops in Ireland in the 1840s. The study of plants continues today as botanists try to understand the structure, behaviour, and cellular activities of plants in order to develop better crops and create new medicines.",questions:[{number:59,answer:3,question:"Why is Theophrastus called the \u2018father of botany\u2019?",choices:["He distinguished botany from zoology and microbiology as a distinct field.","He was more successful than Aristotle in identifying and describing plants.","He was the first person who studied plants.","He produced significant works whose effects last today.","He worked on plants for long periods of time."]},{number:60,answer:4,question:"Which of the following is true about De Materia Medica?",choices:["It contained information on which plants are more widely used to make medicines.","It continued to be highly influential even after the invention of the compound microscope.","It contributed much to the invention of the compound microscope.","It was written by Dioscorides as a reaction to the botanical developments that occurred in China.","It was a book for consultation in the Western world for a very long time."]},{number:61,answer:1,question:"What is the current objective of botany?",choices:["To study the works of Theophrastus and Dioscorides for better crops and new medicines","To improve products in the agricultural and pharmaceutical sectors","To make people have a better understanding of the long history of the discipline","To prevent certain plants like the potato plant from catching diseases","To analyse plants in greater detail by enhancing the experiments conducted in the 17th century"]},{number:62,answer:3,question:"What is the passage mainly about?",choices:["The comparison of the Western and Chinese studies of botany","The differences between botany and other fields of biology","The contribution of botany to the cultivation of crops","The history of the study of botany","The medical applications of botany"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the dialogue.",questions:[{number:63,answer:0,question:"Journalist:\n- Could you tell us about your research on heroic Egyptian kings?\nAnthropologist:\n- We found a skeleton that showed extensive battle trauma. After examining his injuries, we discovered that he had died due to the injuries he got while on a horse.\nJournalist: - ----\nAnthropologist:\n- Previously, the Egyptian kings riding into battle could only be seen in paintings and were thought to be just aggressive depictions of the ruling class. This is the first real evidence that points to the kings actually joining their armies in battle.",choices:["How does this discovery impact our traditional perceptions of the Egyptian kings?","How often did the Egyptian kings fight in battle and get injured?","Why is it significant that all the Egyptian kings were on horseback in battle?","Why did you focus on the injuries the Egyptian kings had?","Do you think that old paintings portray the Egyptian kings in detail?"]},{number:64,answer:0,question:"Patient:\n- I don\u2019t know if I\u2019ll ever overcome this fear. Can you tell me again about this new memory therapy you want to try?\nPsychologist:\n- Well, I\u2019m going to show you a series of pictures of the thing you\u2019re afraid of at 10-minute intervals.\nPatient: - ----\nPsychologist:\nTime is crucial to disrupting the brain\u2019s ability to remember your fear. If we increase the time intervals between the pictures, your brain has more time to remember, and that\u2019s exactly what we don\u2019t want.",choices:["Are the lengths of the intervals important?","Is there a particular order of pictures?","How many times will you show me these pictures?","What does memory have to do with my fear?","What happens if my fear doesn\u2019t go away?"]},{number:65,answer:2,question:"Ann:\n- There`s a very interesting article in this magazine about a scientist, Ella Al-Shamahi, who\u2019s a palaeontologist and also performs stand-up comedy about her field.\nJane:\n- Science and comedy, how does that work?\nAnn: - ----\nJane:\n- I get it now. She`s using comedy to increase interest in her scientific research. Well, she might be on the right path, maybe comedy is the next stage in the evolution of how we present science.",choices:["I guess she`s using palaeontology to add variety to the topics she`s talking about in her performance to be different from the other stand-up performers.","I`m not sure, but I can assume that she might have really good time management skills to be able to do research and fulfill other responsibilities as a palaeontologist.","Well, when you think about it, we seem to have a communication problem in science, so she might be using comedy to get to people with no enthusiasm about science.","The rest of the article says it`s an incredible therapy for her as some of the places she researches are quite dark and it`s nice to find the funny side in them.","If she`s really good at it, these shows might even make her famous meaning that she can also continue doing research in her field if she wants to."]},{number:66,answer:0,question:"Journalist:\n- You always highlight the importance of keeping a checklist during complex operations. You\u2019ve also written a book on how to create such checklists. Why do we need them?\nSurgeon:\n- Well, they`re memory aids. They can help you perform well when you`re working with many people on a complex procedure which eventually will save lives during surgery.\nJournalist: - ----\nSurgeon:\n- A checklist was used during surgical procedures for 8,000 patients in eight hospitals around the world. In every hospital, major complications were reduced by 36 percent and the death rate was lowered by half.",choices:["How did you come to the decision that checklists are really beneficial?","How did you manage to create a common checklist to be used in various complications?","How exactly can a checklist be used during a surgical procedure?","How could you spare enough time to write a book on checklists while working as a surgeon?","How did you convince your medical staff to start using a checklist?"]},{number:67,answer:4,question:"Robert:\n- Can perfectionism or stress be a reason for nail-biting?\nCarl:\n- This might be true, but I`m not sure one can find reliable research as to why nail-biting is so addictive.\nRobert: - ----\nCarl:\n- Anyway, I think it`d be better not to form an opinion on the causes of nail-biting without knowing all the details and scientific facts.",choices:["Some experts say childhood nail-biters are less prone to allergies, presumably because they`re exposed to more germs.","The most common treatment of this addiction, which is also cheap and widely available, is to apply a bitter-tasting nail polish to the nails.","I know some other body-focused repetitive behaviours like skin-picking and the urge to pull out hair, and they sometimes coexist with nail-biting.","Doctors state that nail-biting does not only lead to harmful effects in fingers, but also mouth and more generally the digestive system.","We can speculate that it`s to do with experiencing high levels of anxiety and fear, or being too passionate or impatient about things and events."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best rephrased form of the given sentence.",questions:[{number:68,answer:3,question:"The fierce debate among scientists over whether intelligence is inherited or acquired later is yet to be resolved.",choices:["Scientists have not still agreed upon how much of intelligence is inherited and how much of it is acquired after birth.","Whether people are innately endowed with intelligence or they acquire it at a later time has stimulated an intense debate among scientists.","A hot debate among scientists revolves around the inheritance of intelligence rather than its acquisition in the following years.","The heated debate among scientists over whether people are born with intelligence or they acquire it later has not still ended in agreement.","The fact that intelligence can be both inherited and acquired in later years has been vigorously debated by scientists."]},{number:69,answer:1,question:"According to a recent study, there are more overfed people in the world today than those who do not have enough food to eat.",choices:["A new study shows that there is a significant increase in the number of overfed people worldwide when compared to those who suffer from a lack of food.","A recent study reveals that, across the world, overfed people now outnumber those who are malnourished.","A current study suggests that, in today\u2019s world, the difference between the number of people who do not have enough food and that of those who overeat is slight.","The claim that there are as many overfed people as malnourished people in the world today has been proven by a recent study.","A new study has found that malnourished people are far greater in number than overfed people in the entire world today."]},{number:70,answer:3,question:"It is imperative that women start modifying their risk factors when they are younger in order to reduce the risk of developing heart disease once they are older.",choices:["If women immediately begin changing their risk factors when they are still young, they may decrease their risk of developing heart disease in their old ages.","Women are recommended to start changing their risk factors at young ages rather than old ages, because this will reduce the risk of developing heart disease.","It is extremely important for women to begin changing their risk factors when they are young because it might not be easy to decrease the risk of having heart disease in their old ages.","Women should immediately begin changing their risk factors at a young age so that they can decrease the risk of having heart disease in their old ages.","It is urgent that women begin changing their risk factors at a young age, otherwise the risk of developing heart disease among old women cannot be decreased."]},{number:71,answer:4,question:"It is already known that flowers display their bright colours and use their beautiful scents to lure bees; however, scientists have recently discovered that they use electric fields as well.",choices:["Scientists used to believe that flowers avoided using electric fields to attract bees despite utilising their vivid colours and scents, but now they suggest electric fields are also used.","It is common knowledge that bees are attracted by flowers` bright colours and beautiful scents, but what draws scientists` attention more these days is the electric fields that flowers also use.","It has long been known that flowers use several methods to attract bees, such as displaying striking colours and using their appealing scents, but scientists now think that flowers use electric fields for the same purpose.","In addition to the exploitation of their bright colours and beautiful scents, flowers make use of electric fields to attract bees, which has long been known by scientists.","The fact that flowers manifest their brilliant colours and benefit from their pleasant scents to attract bees has been known for a while, but what scientists have recently revealed is their use of electric fields."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the missing part of the passage.",questions:[{number:72,answer:2,question:"We are terrified of sharks, largely thanks to their reputation as vicious killers. Shark attacks are rare but appear to be rising: There were 98 unprovoked attacks worldwide in 2015, six fatal. There are three particularly notorious species: tiger sharks, great whites, and oceanic whitetips. ---- Recently, scientists have been shedding new light on these enigmatic creatures that are seemingly vital to the seas, and not as scary as you might think.",choices:["Tiger sharks are unlikely to attack divers who keep them in sight.","Novice divers may come face-to-face with the sharks and see their true nature.","On the other hand, a lesser known fact is the crucial role sharks play in ocean ecology.","Tiger sharks in the protected waters of the Bahamas are relatively harmless, but they rarely stay in one place for long.","Scientists in Australia say that sharks keep fish numbers down and stop them degrading sea grass ecosystems."]},{number:73,answer:1,question:"St. Valentine`s Day is set aside for lovers and for declarations of love, with these declarations traditionally sent anonymously. ---- Theories put forward generally refer the custom back to Roman times, telling the story of St. Valentine, a Roman priest who assisted the Christian martyrs during the persecutions in the time of Claudius II. St. Valentine was caught and ordered to give up the Christian faith. He refused to do so and was executed on the 14th February 270 AD. In another telling, St. Valentine was executed for the cause of love, after allowing Christian soldiers to marry in spite of a ban on them imposed by Emperor Claudius Gothicus.",choices:["St. Valentine`s Day flourishes in cultures where there is a free choice of spouse.","As with many traditions of this kind, it is difficult to determine the real origin of the practice.","In the past, there was a belief that the first member of the opposite sex you met on this day would be your valentine.","Nowadays, St. Valentine`s Day is promoted for commercial interests, by businesses from card manufacturers to flower merchants.","The Valentine`s card as we know it today did not begin to gain popularity until recent decades."]},{number:74,answer:0,question:"There is some indication that children whose access to television is restricted are less likely to be negatively affected by it, even when they do view it. A study has found that children whose parents restrict viewing are less likely to be unnecessarily fearful of the outside world. ---- In other words, children whose parents severely limit access to television may actually become more aggressive, perhaps due to the frustration that results from the deprivation of privileges.",choices:["It should be noted, however, that there is some evidence that very extreme levels of restriction will backfire.","Children with limited access to television are less likely to believe that what they see on television is real.","It is possible that the mere presence of parents while viewing makes children feel happy.","Children who receive parental restriction are better able to quickly understand the plots of television programmes.","Much of the research on the effects of television viewing has focused on children whose parents are more sophisticated consumers of television."]},{number:75,answer:3,question:"Beautifully coloured birds, acrobatic monkeys, and noisy insects are just a few of the sights and sounds in a tropical rainforest \u2013 the richest plant and animal habitat in the world. Rainforests are found near the Equator where it is wet and warm enough for plants to grow all year round. Most rainforest trees are evergreen, and they produce food and shelter for a vast number of animals. ---- Every year, huge areas are cut down for timber and to make way for pastures and crops.",choices:["Yet, the negative effect of global warming on this rich fauna can be seen.","Therefore, people should try hard to protect the variety of species living in rainforests.","In other words, the tropical rainforest is home to various plants and animals.","However, despite this richness, rainforests have recently been shrinking.","Some trees, on the other hand, are used to provide shelter for human beings."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the irrelevant sentence in the passage.",questions:[{number:76,answer:3,question:"(I) Images of distant and unknown places have inspired explorers and public for a very long time. (II) The photographs of Yellowstone were the reason why it was selected as America`s first national park in 1872. (III) Photographer William Henry Jackson captured the public`s imagination and support by confirming the existence of western landmarks in the park. (IV) Half a century later photographer Ansel Adams began his long career of delighting the public with his pictures of parks that many people would never visit. (V) These landmarks which were previously regarded as glorified myths made it easier to attract attention.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:77,answer:4,question:"(I) Groups perform many tasks, of which making decisions is one of the most important. (II) The course of our lives is largely determined by decisions made by groups: for example, selection committees, juries, parliaments and groups of friends. (III) In addition, many of us spend a significant portion of our working lives making decisions in groups. (IV) Therefore, social psychologists have long been interested in the social processes involved in group decision-making, and in whether groups make better or different decisions than individuals do. (V) Another important dimension of group decision-making is the ability to recall information.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:78,answer:2,question:"(I) In the North American autumn, Arctic air meets warmer air from the south, creating the perfect conditions for storms. (II) Wind rages around all of the Great Lakes at this time of year, but Lake Erie is the shallowest and contains the least water. (III) The water of Lake Erie is darkened by mud and sand mixed by the strong currents. (IV) This means its waves are typically the biggest as it is more easily influenced by the wind. (V) As the wind blows, the waves start to build a beat, rhythmically sloshing back and forth along the lake\u2019s roughly east-west axis, and growing in height as they do.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:79,answer:3,question:"(I) During impression formation, we tend to pay special attention to negative or potentially threatening information. (II) When we come to form an overall impression of the person, that negative information is weighed more heavily. (III) That is, a negative trait affects an impression more than a positive trait, everything else being equal. (IV) For example, in one study, students rated 97 percent of their professors in college favorably despite all the mixed experiences they have had in their college classes. (V) The main explanation for this fact is that negative traits are more unusual and therefore more distinctive.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:80,answer:2,question:"(I) The symptoms of senile dementia generally include a decline in memory, learning, attention, and judgement, as well as disorientation and increased difficulties in communication. (II) Alzheimer\u2019s disease is the most common cause of senile dementia, accounting for around 70 percent of all cases. (III) Alzheimer\u2019s disease often makes it more difficult to think of the right word, for example. (IV) Behavioural manifestations of Alzheimer\u2019s disease include a decline in personal hygiene, inappropriate social behaviour, and apparent changes in personality. (V) Wandering and forgetting what one is doing can also become a serious problem, as this can create a genuine danger.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]}]}]},{routeName:"2017-Spring",items:[{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the space.",questions:[{number:1,answer:2,question:"The ageing of population, also known as `demographic ageing`, is a term used to describe ---- in the age distribution of a population from the young towards people of older ages.",choices:["opportunities","regulations","shifts","assumptions","conflicts"]},{number:2,answer:3,question:"Large collections of books are often unusable without careful attention to classification, so providing easy access to library materials using such labels as author, title, and subject, is essential for proper ---- of any library.",choices:["violation","justification","abandonment","utilisation","elimination"]},{number:3,answer:3,question:"During the investigation of a lethal or an easily transmitted disease, the necessary precautions must be taken to protect health staff, because they are ---- to catching the disease in question.",choices:["committed","adaptable","entitled","vulnerable","accessible"]},{number:4,answer:1,question:"Parents who are responsive, non-authoritarian, and who manifest empathetic and caring behaviours can ---- the development of empathy in their children.",choices:["delay","acknowledge","relieve","enhance","surpass"]},{number:5,answer:3,question:"IQ tests are often faulted for ignoring cultural or social biases, particularly with regard to schoolchildren, and critics claim they cannot ---- predict a person\u2019s future performance.",choices:["initially","accurately","conventionally","narrowly","strictly"]},{number:6,answer:2,question:"World War II is an important turning point in that it ---- the beginning of the end of colonial empires.",choices:["made out","handed down","brought about","took over","put back"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word(s) or expression(s) to fill the space(s).",questions:[{number:7,answer:3,question:"New research ---- that mother monkeys ---- to other females to help share the burden of raising increasingly dependent offspring.",choices:["had suggested / were turning","suggests / had turned","suggested / have turned","has suggested / turn","will suggest / are turning"]},{number:8,answer:3,question:"Patients with implants or electronic devices put inside their bodies ---- using magnetic resonance imaging (MR`because the machine\u2019s magnet ---- these objects within the body, causing damage.",choices:["should not be examined / must move","could not be examined / had to move","may not be examined / used to move","cannot be examined / could move","must not be examined / ought to move"]},{number:9,answer:2,question:"In the age of steam, with new railroads ---- across Europe and the US, engineers began ---- even more applications for the steam engine.",choices:["to spread / finding","having spread / to have found","spreading / to find","to have spread / find","spread / having found"]},{number:10,answer:1,question:"More than 80 percent of the dry land will be affected if temperatures continue to increase ---- the present rate, but ---- very different extents.",choices:["on / for","at / to","in / about","by / with","from / over"]},{number:11,answer:4,question:"Starting ---- 800 AD, many agricultural communities emerged ---- the Mississippi and in other fertile river valleys in North America.",choices:["for / by","over / about","on / with","at / in","around / along"]},{number:12,answer:1,question:"70 percent of the Earth`s surface is liquid, ---- water scarcity affects more than a billion people each year.",choices:["as if","yet","given that","instead","thus"]},{number:13,answer:2,question:"Alphabetic writing systems are easy to learn and maximally efficient for transcribing any human language, ---- they are considered one of the major achievements of civilisation.",choices:["otherwise","but","so","whether","as"]},{number:14,answer:2,question:"---- historians cannot agree on when gold was first discovered, there is some evidence to suggest that the Egyptians were the first to mine it.",choices:["Now that","Just as","Even though","As long as","In case"]},{number:15,answer:4,question:"Wheat, which has been a staple food for centuries, can turn out to be bad for some people ---- because they are allergic to it ---- because they have an autoimmune disorder.",choices:["so / that","neither / nor","as / as","the more / the more","either / or"]},{number:16,answer:4,question:"---- its similarities with other Italian cities, it is important to emphasise that Venice`s aquatic environment and associations with foreign lands via the sea endowed it with a uniqueness.",choices:["Due to","By means of","In terms of","In case of","Despite"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:"The Atacama Desert in South America is peppered with odd, cushion-like plants known as the llareta, a spongy cousin of parsley. Despite the harsh weather conditions that they have to ----, some of these plants are up to 3,000 years old. Though looking like a rock covered by small green plants without flowers, the plant has a tightly packed structure of branches, each adorned ---- clusters of tiny leaves. The resulting plant is so strong that you ---- on top of it very comfortably. ----, this hardiness comes at a price: the plants are thought to grow just 1.5 cm a year. According to Catherine Kleier, a researcher from Regis University, Colorado, the llareta became very strong ---- a combination of environmental factors (cold at night and hot in the day) and it is compact to trap heat. The more compact the plant, the more successfully it protects itself.",questions:[{number:17,answer:0,question:"Despite the harsh weather conditions that they have to ----, some of these plants are up to 3,000 years old",choices:["endure","influence","avoid","trigger","improve"]},{number:18,answer:2,question:"Though looking like a rock covered by small green plants without flowers, the plant has a tightly packed structure of branches, each adorned ---- clusters of tiny leaves.",choices:["on","at","with","for","over"]},{number:19,answer:2,question:"The resulting plant is so strong that you ---- on top of it very comfortably.",choices:["had better stand","may have stood","can stand","used to stand","must stand"]},{number:20,answer:1,question:"----, this hardiness comes at a price: the plants are thought to grow just 1.5 cm a year.",choices:["For instance","However","Therefore","Similarly","Otherwise"]},{number:21,answer:4,question:"Colorado, the llareta became very strong ---- a combination of environmental factors (cold at night and hot in the day) and it is compact to trap heat.",choices:["rather than","in addition to","contrary to","except for","because of"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best word or expression to fill the spaces in the passage.",text:"Both Mars and Venus have been objects of scientific and popular speculation since at least the beginning of the 20th century, and since the 1960s spacefaring nations have been sending robotic probes to explore these two planets. ----, Mars has drawn far more attention. Since 2002 no fewer than two Mars probes have been actively gathering data during any given year. There were actually seven used in 2015 alone. This is ---- because Mars is far more hospitable than Venus, where surface temperatures can reach 480 \xb0C, surface pressure is 92 times that of the Earth and the planet is permanently surrounded by thick clouds of sulfuric acid. We have direct evidence that water once flowed and pooled ---- Mars. So, it can be assumed that life once existed there and ---- at present. Venus is far more Earth-like than Mars in its size, composition and surface gravity, but ---- its harsh environment, it could never host life.",questions:[{number:22,answer:1,question:"----, Mars has drawn far more attention.",choices:["Accordingly","Nevertheless ","Furthermore","That is","At first"]},{number:23,answer:4,question:"This is ---- because Mars is far more hospitable than Venus, where surface temperatures can reach 480 \xb0C, surface pressure is 92 times that of the Earth and the planet is permanently surrounded by thick clouds of sulfuric acid.",choices:["coincidental","irreversible","unintentional","preventable","plausible"]},{number:24,answer:3,question:"We have direct evidence that water once flowed and pooled ---- Mars.",choices:["from","by","toward","on","into"]},{number:25,answer:0,question:"So, it can be assumed that life once existed there and ---- at present.",choices:["may exist","must have existed","could have existed","would have existed","used to exist"]},{number:26,answer:0,question:"Venus is far more Earth-like than Mars in its size, composition and surface gravity, but ---- its harsh environment, it could never host life.",choices:["due to","instead of","in comparison to","unlike","such as"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the given sentence.",questions:[{number:27,answer:0,question:"Although buying energy-saving light bulbs and riding your bike to work are the correct choices to save the planet, ----.",choices:["we cannot imagine these are going to eradicate the problem","we could save the world by relying on renewable energy sources","that is what we should already be doing to take action","small acts of consumption can be politically activating","it seems that people are in search for a complete solution"]},{number:28,answer:2,question:"Since we now generate more data every year than the entire planet did up until 2003, ----.",choices:["libraries continue to keep records of knowledge in the form of books","it is inconceivable to have effective database management systems","the way we store and preserve that data has to change","it is not possible for data stored on digital platforms to vanish","humanity`s cumulative knowledge will not disappear if stored digitally"]},{number:29,answer:2,question:"Even though William Hamilton was not the first person to come up with the idea for a jet boat, ----.",choices:["Greek scholar Archimedes had the concept of a jet boat when he devised his water screw","the maneuverability of the jet boat has long made its design highly marketable","he has been credited with revolutionising the conventional world of boating","Italian inventor Secondo Campani had devised a remarkably similar jet-powered boat","he lived in New Zealand, where his boat was able to power quickly through shallow waters"]},{number:30,answer:1,question:"Although our bones stop growing in length in our late teens, ----.",choices:["there is some evidence that too little or too much protein can reduce bone strength","it is crucial that we get necessary nutrients to keep them strong and healthy right through adulthood","from the first few weeks after pregnancy, our bones grow and develop healthy and strong bone tissues","sources of dairy and non-dairy calcium can help fight even hereditary bone conditions","low bone density disease is largely preventable at any age with the right diet and lifestyle"]},{number:31,answer:1,question:"Just as an accomplished writer must help us visualise events rather than plainly tell them, ----.",choices:["storytellers are a significant voice of culture, and their storytelling takes many forms","a good storyteller is expected to provide not just a description but an experience","some people make a living as professional storytellers","the intellectual and emotional impacts of effective storytellers are undeniable","the words of storytellers may capture the minds and feelings of listeners"]},{number:32,answer:3,question:"The huge improvement in levels of readership in the 1960s largely coincided with the arrival of television, ----.",choices:["but there was a dramatic increase in the number of people who spent their time watching TV","thus people began to pay more attention to the best-selling books, especially detective novels","because the production of cheaper pocket editions within reach of a wider range of the population fostered reading","so the habit of book reading came to occupy proportionately less of people`s leisure time","while the readership of humour, biography, and history was decreasing among the younger generation"]},{number:33,answer:2,question:"In 19th-century Europe, women and children were used extensively in factories ----.",choices:["although only about 20 percent of workers were employed in factories in 1850","when they became aware of the effects of factory work on their health","since they worked for lower wages and compensated for reluctant male labour","as the factory worker was not characteristic of European labour in the 19th century","while domestic industry and agriculture engaged most of the population"]},{number:34,answer:0,question:"A recent study shows that workers tend to be more committed to their institution ----.",choices:["when the managers express their gratitude and make them feel appreciated","even though payments are increased to resolve hot conflicts","until they are provided with little practical direction by their bosses","even if they engage in new, interesting activities together with their colleagues","while supporting each other`s attempts to improve relationships is crucial"]},{number:35,answer:4,question:"It is more energy efficient for small birds to move by hopping ----.",choices:["but they cover much more distance in a single hop than with a step with their short legs","since birds spending most of their time in trees jump from branch to branch","so there is an extra load on the joints of heavier birds leaving one leg on the ground all the time","as almost all birds are capable of both hopping and walking at the same time","because of the fact that their light bodies easily bounce into the air"]},{number:36,answer:1,question:"Many of us tend to overlook our mental well-being ----.",choices:["so that mental health disorders can be correctly diagnosed through specialised tests","until a serious problem arises and we lose balance in our lives","because we should try to maintain good mental and physical health","now that we may have mental health problems when we experience too much stress","although there are many complex reasons why we develop mental health problems"]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the most accurate Turkish translation of the sentences in English, and the most accurate English translation of the sentences in Turkish.",questions:[{number:37,answer:2,question:"The arrival of the domestic horse in West Africa transformed warfare there and turned the area into a set of kingdoms dependent on the force of cavalry.",choices:["Bat\u0131 Afrika\u2019n\u0131n atl\u0131 asker gu\u0308cu\u0308ne bag\u0306l\u0131 bir dizi krall\u0131g\u0306a do\u0308nu\u0308s\u0327mesinin nedeni, evcil atlar\u0131n bo\u0308lgeye gelis\u0327i ve oradaki savas\u0327 anlay\u0131s\u0327\u0131n\u0131 deg\u0306is\u0327tirmesidir.","Bat\u0131 Afrika\u2019daki savas\u0327 anlay\u0131s\u0327\u0131 evcil atlar\u0131n gelis\u0327iyle deg\u0306is\u0327ti ve bo\u0308lge atl\u0131 asker gu\u0308cu\u0308ne dayal\u0131 bir dizi krall\u0131g\u0306a do\u0308nu\u0308s\u0327tu\u0308.","Evcil atlar\u0131n Bat\u0131 Afrika\u2019ya ulas\u0327mas\u0131 oradaki savas\u0327 anlay\u0131s\u0327\u0131n\u0131 deg\u0306is\u0327tirdi ve bo\u0308lgeyi atl\u0131 asker gu\u0308cu\u0308ne dayal\u0131 bir dizi krall\u0131g\u0306a do\u0308nu\u0308s\u0327tu\u0308rdu\u0308.","Evcil atlar\u0131n bo\u0308lgeye ulas\u0327mas\u0131yla savas\u0327 anlay\u0131s\u0327\u0131nda deg\u0306is\u0327iklikler yas\u0327ayan Bat\u0131 Afrika, atl\u0131 asker gu\u0308cu\u0308ne dayal\u0131 bir dizi krall\u0131k ha\u0302line geldi.","Evcil atlar\u0131n Bat\u0131 Afrika`ya ulas\u0327mas\u0131 oradaki savas\u0327 anlay\u0131s\u0327\u0131n\u0131 deg\u0306is\u0327tirerek bo\u0308lgenin atl\u0131 asker gu\u0308cu\u0308ne dayal\u0131 bir dizi krall\u0131g\u0306a do\u0308nu\u0308s\u0327mesine neden oldu."]},{number:38,answer:4,question:"A study carried out at Weill Cornell Medical College has found out how the brain switches between waking and the unconscious, which is promising for rousing people from an unconscious state.",choices:["Weill Cornell T\u0131p Faku\u0308ltesi`nde yap\u0131lan ve beynin uyanma ve bilinc\u0327alt\u0131 aras\u0131nda nas\u0131l gec\u0327is\u0327 yapt\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131 ortaya c\u0327\u0131karan c\u0327al\u0131s\u0327ma, insanlar\u0131 bilinc\u0327siz bir durumdan uyand\u0131rma konusunda u\u0308mit vericidir.","Weill Cornell T\u0131p Faku\u0308ltesi`nde yap\u0131lan bir c\u0327al\u0131s\u0327ma, beynin uyanma ve bilinc\u0327alt\u0131 aras\u0131nda nas\u0131l gec\u0327is\u0327 yapt\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131 ortaya c\u0327\u0131kard\u0131g\u0306\u0131 ic\u0327in insanlar\u0131 bilinc\u0327siz bir durumdan uyand\u0131rma konusunda u\u0308mit vadediyor.","Weill Cornell T\u0131p Faku\u0308ltesi`nde, beynin uyanma ve bilinc\u0327alt\u0131 aras\u0131nda nas\u0131l gec\u0327is\u0327 yapt\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131 ortaya c\u0327\u0131karma ve insanlar\u0131 bilinc\u0327siz bir durumdan uyand\u0131rma konusunda u\u0308mit vadeden bir c\u0327al\u0131s\u0327ma yap\u0131lm\u0131s\u0327t\u0131r.","Beynin uyanma ve bilinc\u0327alt\u0131 aras\u0131nda nas\u0131l gec\u0327is\u0327 yapt\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131 ortaya c\u0327\u0131karan ve insanlar\u0131 bilinc\u0327siz bir durumdan uyand\u0131rma konusunda u\u0308mit vadeden bir c\u0327al\u0131s\u0327ma, Weill Cornell T\u0131p Faku\u0308ltesi`nde yap\u0131lm\u0131s\u0327t\u0131r.","Weill Cornell T\u0131p Faku\u0308ltesi`nde yap\u0131lan bir c\u0327al\u0131s\u0327ma, beynin uyanma ve bilinc\u0327alt\u0131 aras\u0131nda nas\u0131l gec\u0327is\u0327 yapt\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131 ortaya c\u0327\u0131karm\u0131s\u0327t\u0131r, ki bu insanlar\u0131 bilinc\u0327siz bir durumdan uyand\u0131rma konusunda u\u0308mit vericidir."]},{number:39,answer:0,question:"Widely regarded as Australia\u2019s capital of culture, Melbourne is a vibrant city with various surprises around every corner.",choices:["C\u0327og\u0306unlukla Avustralya\u2019n\u0131n ku\u0308ltu\u0308r bas\u0327kenti olarak kabul edilen Melbourne, her ko\u0308s\u0327esinde c\u0327es\u0327itli su\u0308rprizler bar\u0131nd\u0131ran canl\u0131 bir kenttir.","Melbourne\u2019u\u0308n c\u0327og\u0306unlukla Avustralya\u2019n\u0131n ku\u0308ltu\u0308r bas\u0327kenti olarak kabul edilmesinin sebebi, bu canl\u0131 s\u0327ehrin her ko\u0308s\u0327esinde c\u0327es\u0327itli su\u0308rprizler bar\u0131nd\u0131r\u0131yor olmas\u0131d\u0131r.","C\u0327og\u0306unlukla Avustralya`n\u0131n ku\u0308ltu\u0308r bas\u0327kenti olarak kabul edilen Melbourne, canl\u0131 oldug\u0306u kadar her ko\u0308s\u0327esinde c\u0327es\u0327itli su\u0308rprizler de bar\u0131nd\u0131ran bir kenttir.","Her ko\u0308s\u0327esinde farkl\u0131 su\u0308rprizler bar\u0131nd\u0131ran ve canl\u0131 bir kent olan Melbourne, c\u0327og\u0306unlukla Avustralya`n\u0131n ku\u0308ltu\u0308r bas\u0327kenti olarak kabul edilir.","Melbourne c\u0327og\u0306unlukla Avustralya\u2019n\u0131n ku\u0308ltu\u0308r bas\u0327kenti olarak kabul edilir, c\u0327u\u0308nku\u0308 bu canl\u0131 s\u0327ehir her ko\u0308s\u0327esinde c\u0327es\u0327itli su\u0308rprizler bar\u0131nd\u0131r\u0131r."]},{number:40,answer:2,question:"O\u0308g\u0306retmenler, o\u0308g\u0306retim yo\u0308ntemi sec\u0327erken, o\u0308g\u0306rencilerinin o\u0308zellikleri ve ha\u0302lihaz\u0131rdaki kaynaklar\u0131n yan\u0131 s\u0131ra kendi yeterliliklerini ve bilgilerini de go\u0308z o\u0308nu\u0308nde bulundurmal\u0131d\u0131rlar.",choices:["What teachers need to do when choosing a teaching method is to take their own capabilities and knowledge into account as well as their students` characteristics and the resources available.","When they follow a teaching method, teachers are expected to consider their own capabilities and knowledge together with their students` characteristics and the resources available.","When choosing a teaching method, teachers should take their own capabilities and knowledge into account along with their students` characteristics and the resources available.","When implementing a teaching method, teachers should consider not only their students` characteristics and the resources available but also their own capabilities and knowledge.","Their own capabilities and knowledge besides their students` characteristics and the resources available should be taken into account by teachers when choosing a teaching method."]},{number:41,answer:2,question:"Ko\u0308pek bal\u0131klar\u0131n\u0131n say\u0131s\u0131 o\u0308nemli o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308de azal\u0131yor ve bu y\u0131rt\u0131c\u0131 bal\u0131klar yavas\u0327 gelis\u0327tikleri ve nadiren u\u0308redikleri ic\u0327in nu\u0308fuslar\u0131n\u0131n h\u0131zl\u0131 bir s\u0327ekilde artmas\u0131 olas\u0131 go\u0308ru\u0308nmu\u0308yor.",choices:["Given that the number of sharks is falling drastically as these predatory fish slowly mature and seldom reproduce, there is no likelihood that their population will increase quickly.","Because sharks slowly mature and rarely breed, their number is falling greatly, and therefore the population of these predatory fish seems unlikely to increase rapidly.","The number of sharks is falling dramatically, and since these predatory fish slowly mature and rarely reproduce, it seems unlikely that their population`, will increase quickly.","It seems unlikely that shark population will increase quickly since these predatory fish, whose number is falling considerably, slowly mature and seldom breed.","The number of sharks is falling substantially, and because these predatory fish slowly mature and rarely reproduce, it is not probable that there will be a significant increase in their population."]},{number:42,answer:2,question:"Du\u0308nya u\u0308zerinde yas\u0327am bas\u0327lad\u0131g\u0306\u0131ndan bu yana yu\u0308z milyonlarca bitki ve hayvan tu\u0308ru\u0308nu\u0308n nesli tu\u0308kendi ve insanlar son 300 y\u0131ld\u0131r dog\u0306al yas\u0327am alanlar\u0131n\u0131 tahrip ederek yok olma su\u0308recini bu\u0308yu\u0308k o\u0308lc\u0327u\u0308de h\u0131zland\u0131rd\u0131.",choices:["Since life began on Earth, hundreds of millions of species of plants and animals have been threatened with extinction, and over the past 300 years the extinction process has substantially accelerated due to habitat destruction caused by people.","Hundreds of millions of species of plants and animals have become extinct since life began on Earth, and over the past 300 years people have been damaging habitats, thus significantly speeding up the extinction process.","Hundreds of millions of species of plants and animals have become extinct since life began on Earth, and over the past 300 years people have dramatically speeded up the extinction process by destroying habitats.","Since life began on Earth, hundreds of millions of species of plants and animals have become extinct, and habitats have been damaged by people, which has substantially accelerated the extinction process for the past 300 years.","There are hundreds of millions of species of plants and animals that have faced extinction since life began on Earth, and people who are destroying habitats have dramatically speeded up the extinction process for the past 300 years."]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"One day in 1952, John W. Hetrick was driving with his wife and daughter in the front seat when he had to change his direction suddenly and brake quickly to avoid an obstacle. Instinctively, he and his wife put their arms out to protect their daughter in case of a crash. This event inspired him to provide automobiles with airbags to protect people during accidents. Hetrick had been an engineer in the US Navy during World War II. He recalled a compressed-air torpedo accidentally turning itself on, causing its canvas cover to shoot up into the air, `quicker than a blink of an eye`. In 1952, Hetrick proposed using compressed air to inflate airbags rapidly during car crashes. He received a patent for this invention in 1953, but car manufacturers in the 1950s were more interested in style than safety. Later, consumers became more safety conscious and airbag technology improved. The first airbags were optional, but by the 1990s, they had become standard. Although airbags have saved thousands of lives, they are not always sufficient to prevent death and injury during crashes. Travellers must also wear seat belts, and automobiles must have dashboards made of soft materials and steering columns that can absorb energy during impact from car crashes.",questions:[{number:43,answer:4,question:"It can be understood from the passage that the airbags were ----.",choices:["widely accepted when they were first introduced in 1952","invented with the fundamental aim of making cars look more attractive","manufactured largely in order to improve automobile marketing and increase the sales","invented by a US engineer while he was launching the canvas cover into the air","designed to work very fast to provide immediate protection for people"]},{number:44,answer:2,question:"It is pointed out in the passage that in the 1950s, car manufacturers ----.",choices:["developed a compressed mechanism which inflated airbags swiftly","benefitted from optional airbags to raise the safety awareness among the customers","paid more attention to the physical appearance of cars rather than their safety","started to produce standard airbags in line with the innovations in airbag technology","were highly concerned with safety requirements imposed on automobile industry"]},{number:45,answer:4,question:"Which of the following can be inferred from the passage?",choices:["The injuries and deaths in car accidents can be completely prevented with airbags.","As soon as Hetrick patented the airbag, it became obligatory for manufacturers to equip cars with airbags.","The dashboards and steering columns of automobiles should be designed elaborately to increase the efficiency of airbags.","Travellers are expected to fasten their seat belts which enable the airbags to inflate more quickly.","Automobile designs are required to manipulate the energy in a crash in order to save people\u2019s lives."]},{number:46,answer:4,question:"Which could be the best title for the passage?",choices:["Advances in the Automobile Industry","An Alternative Way to Save Life","Airbags as a Safety Regulation","How to Prevent Car Accidents with Airbags","The Advance of Airbag Technology"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:'An application to translate chimp language may be available in the near future! Chimpanzees can learn to pronounce `apple` in two chimp languages \u2013 a finding that calls into question how unique our own language ability is. Katie Slocombe of the University of York, UK, and her team recorded vocalisations by a group of adult chimps from the Netherlands before and after their relocation to Edinburgh Zoo. Three years after the move, the Dutch chimps has picked up the pronunciation of their Scottish hosts. The peak frequencies of the Dutch chimps` loud calls fell from 932 to 708 hertz to match closely with the low-toned pronunciations of the Scottish apes. The change was gradual and coincided with the growing friendship of the two groups. This means that, like us, chimps can learn foreign language to fit in with new neighbours. The finding also challenges the prevailing theory that chimp words for objects are fixed because they result from excited, involuntary outbursts. The general assumption was that animals do not have control over the sounds they make, whereas we learn the labels for things socially, which is what separates us from animals, states Slocombe. But this may be wrong, it seems. "It is the first time call structure has been dissociated from emotional outbursts," she says.',questions:[{number:47,answer:3,question:"It is pointed out in the passage that after being relocated, the Dutch chimps ----.",choices:["changed the pronunciation patterns of their Scottish hosts","had increasing frequencies of loud calls","had a low-toned pronunciation as they did in the Netherlands","began to make sounds in a way similar to that of the Scottish apes","experienced a sudden change in how they pronounced words"]},{number:48,answer:0,question:"Which of the following makes chimpanzees resemble us?",choices:["Their language learning ability to get involved in a foreign environment","The fixed words that they use to refer to objects","The association between their words and emotional outbursts","Their capability to decrease the peak frequencies of their loud calls","The three-year period in which they can learn a foreign language"]},{number:49,answer:3,question:"What does the passage mainly focus on?",choices:["The differences between the Dutch and Scottish apes in Edinburgh Zoo","Why it took three years for the Dutch chimps to establish friendship with the Scottish apes","How chimps differ from humans in their language ability","How chimps can learn to pronounce words through socialising","The importance of emotional outbursts for chimps"]},{number:50,answer:1,question:"One can understand from the passage that unlike what is commonly accepted, ----.",choices:["chimp words for objects do not vary","chimps can consciously change the sounds they produce","chimp call structure includes involuntary outbursts","chimps are not able to produce sounds that have meanings","chimp words for objects are linked to emotional outbursts"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"George Manby is most famous for his invention of the Manby Mortar \u2013 a device once used to rescue a lot of people from shipwrecks. He is also known as the father of the modern fire extinguisher, which in itself has also saved thousands of lives. Fire extinguishers actually predate Manby`s invention. One of the earliest ones was designed in 1723 by Ambrose Godfrey. Godfrey`s device consisted of a fire-extinguishing liquid and a chamber of gunpowder. When the attached fuses were lit, the gunpowder exploded and scattered the liquid. They were not widely used, although there is an account of them being used in a fire in London in 1729. Manby`s 1818 invention was more efficient. He was inspired to invent a portable fire extinguisher after witnessing firemen`s inability to fight fires on the top floors of buildings because they were difficult to get to. He designed a device containing potassium carbonate with the remaining space taken up by compressed air. When the device was activated, it allowed the air to rush out and spread the potassium carbonate over quite a range. The system could also be used with water, and was portable, allowing firemen to reach otherwise inaccessible areas. Manby`s invention was soon replaced by a newer model. However, the use of compressed air formed the premise for new prototypes, with modern extinguishers using carbon dioxide as the pressurising agent in a similar way.",questions:[{number:51,answer:2,question:"It is clear from the passage that Manby ----.",choices:["was inspired by different types of fire extinguishers while producing his own type","became famous when he himself rescued a lot of people from a shipwreck","is regarded as the creator of the fire extinguisher although similar types existed before","was the first person to use a fire extinguisher in a fire in London in 1729","collaborated with Godfrey to invent the fire extinguisher"]},{number:52,answer:1,question:"What is the main reason why Manby`s invention in 1818 was more efficient?",choices:["It could use various pressurising agents to scatter the extinguishing liquid.","It enabled firemen to deal with fires in places that they had previously been unable to reach.","It proved its convenience when it helped to extinguish a fire in London in 1729.","It contained potassium carbonate which could spread over a large area.","It could save more lives than Godfrey`s invention could do."]},{number:53,answer:3,question:"One can understand from the passage that Manby`s fire extinguisher ----.",choices:["was designed with the help of the firemen who wanted to reach inaccessible areas","was not used as widely as Godfrey`s device when it was first introduced","was very similar to his another invention called the Manby Mortar","was appropriate for the use of several pressurising agents to spread the potassium carbonate","took more time to activate when compared to Godfrey`s device"]},{number:54,answer:2,question:"What is the primary purpose of the author?",choices:["To give examples of the pressurising agents used in fire extinguishers","To make a comparison between Manby`s fire extinguisher and Godfrey`s device","To inform the reader about the development of the fire extinguisher","To put emphasis on portable fire extinguishers that help firemen to reach inaccessible areas","To describe the benefits and limitations of Manby`s fire extinguisher"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"It might sound like something from a modern-day vampire movie, but transfer of youthful blood can have a reviving effect on the mind, researchers have found. Or at least, it can in mice: a study by Stanford University School of Medicine has discovered that something in the blood of young mice has the ability to restore mental capabilities in older mice. Over the course of three weeks, the scientists gave 18-month-old mice eight infusions of plasma taken from animals that were just three months old, and then put them through a set of experiments to test their spatial memory \u2013 memory relating to the position of things and how large or small they are. The mice were seen to perform consistently better in the tests after receiving the young blood. Old mice injected with the blood of other old mice, on the other hand, showed no improvement in the tests. The team found that new connections were also formed in the old mice`s hippocampi, which again were not seen in the control group. The hippocampus is a brain region that plays a huge role in memory, particularly in recognising and recalling spatial patterns. It is very sensitive to ageing, showing a natural decline in function as people grow older. In conditions such as Alzheimer`s disease, this deterioration is accelerated, leading to an inability to form new memories. It is as yet unclear whether transferring young blood into older individuals would have the same effect in humans.",questions:[{number:55,answer:0,question:"It is clearly stated in the passage that transfer of blood from young mice into old mice ----.",choices:["has helped old mice boost their performance in spatial-memory tests","was performed with the blood especially obtained from 18-month-old mice","has hardly made a difference in old mice in making connections in their hippocampi","improves their memories and it is evidently going to have the same effect on humans","is one of many similar studies carried out by the Stanford University School of Medicine"]},{number:56,answer:1,question:"A control group is a group in an experiment where the factor being tested is not applied so that it can be compared against another group  where the factor is applied. \n\nAccording to this definition, which of the following is referred to with the expression `the control group` that is underlined in the passage?",choices:["The old mice injected with the blood of young mice","The old mice injected with the blood of other old mice","The old mice with more sophisticated hippocampi","The young mice with less sophisticated hippocampi","The young mice injected with the blood of old mice"]},{number:57,answer:2,question:"It is understood from the passage that the hippocampus ----.",choices:["weakens more quickly in mice than in humans","will perform much better in old people if they receive blood from young ones","provides help in remembering the place and size of things","gets better at remembering as one gets older and his or her spatial awareness develops","stops functioning when someone develops such conditions as Alzheimer`s disease"]},{number:58,answer:3,question:"Which could be the best title for this passage?",choices:["How to Take Care of Your Hippocampus","The Important Role of the Hippocampus","How Mice`s Spatial Memory Functions","Looking to Mice for Better Memories","Saying Goodbye to Mental Disorders"]}]},{directions:"Answer these questions according to the passage below.",text:"For many years praise was awarded to the US explorer Robert Peary, who claimed to have reached the North Pole on 6 April 1909. Yet even at the time his claim was disputed. Dr Frederick Cook, a rival American explorer, insisted he had reached the pole almost a year earlier. But neither of them could provide definitive proof of their supposed triumph. Cook`s own evidence was rejected by an independent commission, while Peary refused to hand over any details at all. In 1989, the US National Geographic Society announced that an analysis of photographs taken by Peary, together with his records of ocean depths and other data, were consistent with his expedition getting within eight kilometres of the true pole. Cook`s claim, meanwhile, has always been followed by suspicions of fraud. In the years that followed, the North Pole was reached many times by airborne and submarine expeditions. Surprisingly, the first undisputed expedition to reach the North Pole over the surface did not achieve its goal until 1968, when the American Ralph Plaisted and three companions arrived on snowmobiles. On 6 April the following year, the British explorer Wally Herbert became the first to reach the North Pole the traditional way, on foot.",questions:[{number:59,answer:1,question:"It is stated in the passage that Robert Peary ----.",choices:["was worried that people would learn he was not the the first explorer to reach the North Pole","had been accepted for years as the first person to reach the North Pole although he did not offer conclusive evidence about his expedition","did not want to present the details of his expedition to the independent commission after he learned that Dr Cook was rejected","requested the US National Geographic Society to analyse the photographs and data he gathered during his expedition to prove his claim","was not viewed as the first person to reach the North Pole since Dr Cook was thought to have arrived there earlier"]},{number:60,answer:4,question:"Which of the following was declared by the US National Geographic Society in 1989?",choices:["Dr Cook`s expedition was proven to have taken place a year before Peary`s journey.","Peary`s photographs and records were as controversial and unconvincing as those of Dr Cook.","Dr Cook`s claim was suspicious since he did not reveal clear evidence relating to his travel to the North Pole.","The North Pole was discovered several times by airborne and submarine expeditions before Peary\u2019s and Dr Cook`s expeditions.","The information collected by Peary could describe the real characteristics of the North Pole."]},{number:61,answer:2,question:"Why did the arrival of Ralph Plaisted and his companions at the North Pole in 1968 cause surprise?",choices:["They succeeded in arriving at the North Pole using snowmobiles.","No one was expecting that a group of people could walk as far as the North Pole.","At that time, their expedition was the only one that was recognised to be true.","Herbert was claimed to have arrived at the North Pole before them on foot.","They provided more accurate data than earlier airborne and submarine expeditions did."]},{number:62,answer:3,question:"Which of the following can be concluded from the passage?",choices:["All of the expeditions to the North Pole were questioned until Herbert reached the pole on foot.","Even though Peary has been accepted as the first explorer to reach the North Pole, it was actually Dr Cook who attained the goal.","The adventurers were strongly supported by the US National Geographic Society during their trip to the North Pole.","Reaching the North Pole has been an objective to be achieved for adventurers, which brings reputation to them.","April is the best time for embarking on an expedition to the North Pole, as both Peary and Herbert did."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the dialogue.",questions:[{number:63,answer:0,question:"Christopher:\n- I like the idea of Formula E, which is a new racing championship for single-seater cars powered only by electricity.\nAlbert: - ----\nChristopher:\n- Well, it is a platform for research to improve electric powerstations and charging systems to make electric cars more feasible and hopefully more popular.\nAlbert:\n- I see, this seems to be a good way to encourage the use of energy-efficient and sustainable transportation.",choices:["Why do we need this when there are other races such as Formula 1?","What kind of power do Formula E race cars use?","How do they plan to attract sponsors for such an event?","Where do they plan to have these races?","How frequently will the Formula E races be held?"]},{number:64,answer:3,question:"Reporter:\n- Antibiotic resistance is on the rise, and we are potentially facing a time when standard antibiotics simply won`t work anymore. Why is antibiotic resistance becoming more widespread?\nChemist:\n- One reason could be that a type of bacteria has\ndeveloped molecular mechanisms that actually make an antibiotic drug ineffective.\nReporter:\n- Why is the increase in bacterial resistance considered a threatening issue?\nChemist: - ----\nReporter:\n- This sounds horrible!",choices:["The misuse of antibiotics has certainly contributed to the resistance phenomena. A lot of antibiotics are used in farming, which is practised without complete control.","We should prevent them from producing toxins that lead to illness rather than kill them. That kind of intervention can reduce the chances that the bacteria will develop resistance.","Whenever any pressure is put on bacteria, it will resist. If such pressure is not created, there will be no evolutionary pressure for the bacteria to develop resistance.","If new drugs are not developed against these resistant bacteria, by the year 2050, death from antimicrobial resistant bacteria could actually even surpass death from cancer.","I`m encouraged by the fact that there are more than 200 different bacteria species that live in our guts, and the majority of them are actually beneficial to us."]},{number:65,answer:2,question:"Daisy:\n- I want to take up gardening as a hobby and grow vegetables, but I don`t have a garden to plant them in.\nCaroline: - ----\nDaisy:\n- But they may not grow successfully if they don`t get a sufficient amount of sunlight.\nCaroline:\n- You can grow some vegetables without any sun at all. For example, lettuce and parsley will grow beautifully under artificial light.",choices:["It`s not only the space you should take into account, but sunlight is also important when growing vegetables.","Vegetables need to be watered very frequently, and they tend to grow more nicely in sunny areas.","Have you ever heard about indoor gardening? You can use your attic, basement, or balcony to grow vegetables.","Near a bright window that takes sunlight at high intensity, you can grow cherry tomatoes and cucumbers.","I suggest you install a greenhouse. Greenhouses are the most convenient places to grow vegetables, and they vary vastly in size and price."]},{number:66,answer:2,question:"Defne:\n- I read that remembering the past in a positive way could make us happy in times of crisis.\nBeren: - ----\nDefne:\n- Can you give me an example?\nBeren:\n- During a divorce, I`m not sure that it`s helpful for a person to focus on all the good times in the marriage. They`re likely to experience an even greater sense of loss.",choices:["Actually, when I`m in a bad mood, I find it more beneficial to think about a prosperous future rather than the better past.","Most people believe that looking at old photos showing the good times in the past has a positive influence on mood.","I don`t agree. Recalling better times when a person is depressed will worsen their problems rather than solve them.","I don`t think so. Instead of being nostalgic to feel happy, I generally try to find possible ways to overcome my crisis.","In such situations, seeking professional help or receiving support from close friends may bring a deep relief."]},{number:67,answer:4,question:"Edward:\n- What do you think the difference between the words `inequality` and `disparity` is?\nWilliam:\n- Well, both have negative connotations. And they\nboth imply a lack of something. I guess they are basically synonyms.\nEdward: - ----\nWilliam:\n- Oh, I see. So, if I say that there is a disparity between you and me, it might not be a bad thing, but inequality would be negative.",choices:["That`s sort of correct, but we use `disparity` when we talk about scientific topics and `inequality` for social issues.","That`s basically correct, though `disparity` tells us that something is unfair, while `inequality` means some groups have more advantages than others.","They`re more or less the same, but in academic circles, the term `disparity` is an out-of-date expression; the current term is `inequality`.","They`re essentially synonymous, but we can use `inequality` to express minor differences and `disparity` for significant levels of difference.","You`re right, they`re very similar, but `disparity` can be used to talk about differences neutrally, while `inequality` suggests a value judgement."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best rephrased form of the given sentence.",questions:[{number:68,answer:0,question:"Exercise both strengthens our muscles and encourages the production of special chemicals called endorphins, which make us feel good and act to reduce pain.",choices:["In addition to having stronger muscles through exercising, we are in a better mood and feel less pain thanks to special chemicals, endorphins, that it activates.","In order for our body to generate more endorphins \u2013 the special chemicals that make us happier and reduce pain \u2013 and to strengthen our muscles, we should exercise.","Making our muscles stronger with exercise produces special chemicals, such as endorphins, in the body and makes us feel good by relieving pain.","The production of important chemicals like endorphins not only strengthens our muscles but also encourages us to do exercise to feel better and feel less pain.","Endorphins, special chemicals which are produced while exercising, strengthen our muscles as well as making us happier by reducing pain."]},{number:69,answer:3,question:"Chameleons cannot generate their own body heat so when they want to warm themselves, their colour will darken to absorb more heat from the sun.",choices:["Once their colours darken, chameleons can get more heat from the sun, but to warm themselves much better, they have to produce their own body heat.","When chameleons transform themselves into a dark colour, they take in more heat from the sun and warm themselves easily, which helps them control their own body heat.","Chameleons can warm themselves with the heat from the sun thanks to the dark colours they change into, and that is why they do not need to generate their own body heat.","Because chameleons are not capable of providing their own body heat, their colour gets darker so that more heat is received from the sun, and they can warm themselves.","Chameleons\u2019 body heat is linked to dark colours because when they are darker, more heat from the sun can be absorbed, otherwise they cannot warm themselves."]},{number:70,answer:0,question:"Rome expanded from a small Italian city-state to a world power not just by conquering other societies but also by assimilating them.",choices:["Rome, which was initially a small Italian city-state, evolved into a world power by both assimilating and conquering other societies.","Rome could not have developed into a world power from a small Italian city-state if it had not been able to conquer other societies and assimilate them.","What led Rome to emerge as a world power was the assimilation of various societies it conquered, otherwise it would have remained as a small Italian city-state.","The reason why Rome turned into a world power from a small Italian city-state is that it placed a higher priority on the assimilation of other societies than on their conquest.","Rome, which was a small Italian city-state at the very beginning, conquered and assimilated other societies that had been struggling to become a world power."]},{number:71,answer:2,question:"English is a mother tongue for many people in the world, who are increasingly outnumbered by those who learn English as a foreign language.",choices:["English, either the mother tongue or foreign language of many people, is being spoken in almost every part of the world.","Although English is being learnt as a foreign language more widely than ever, there are also a large amount of people whose first language is English.","Lots of people around the world are native speakers of English; however, the number of learners of English as a foreign language has far surpassed the number of its native speakers.","Throughout the world, there is a significant gap between people who speak English as their first language and those who learn it as a foreign language.","In the past, the number of English native speakers was greater than those who had been learning English as a foreign language, but now it is not the case."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the best option to complete the missing part of the passage.",questions:[{number:72,ansser:3,question:"Almost all of us experience prejudice in one form or another. People make assumptions about us on the basis of our age, ethnicity, race or sex, and we often find ourselves automatically making the same sorts of assumptions about others. Herein lies a paradox: prejudice is socially undesirable; however, it is widespread in society. ---- For example, the system of apartheid in South Africa, where black people were forced to live away from white people, was a classic case of such prejudice, as it was defended publicly as being recognition of and respect for cultural differences.",choices:["No matter what the majority thinks, the government has to make sure that all citizens are safe regardless of their background.","If public awareness is raised, prejudice may not trigger serious problems in multicultural societies.","Once the influence of certain ideologies becomes commonplace throughout the world, it is not easy to eradicate the core beliefs.","Even in societies where prejudice is institutionalised, sophisticated justifications are often used to excuse or deny its presence.","Only when the necessary precautions are taken, can people feel secure, respected and equal in society."]},{number:73,ansser:0,question:'When someone we regard as a cherished friend suddenly is not there for us, it can feel like a hurtful betrayal. But before accusing or condemning them, you might want to ask yourself such questions as "Have they disappointed me before?", "Are my expectations too high?", "Have I always behaved perfectly towards them?". ---- Since we are all fallible and could potentially disappoint our friends, it is good to remember that there are two sides to every story.',choices:["Exploring these issues honestly will allow you to accept your share of responsibility.","It is common in these situations to start wondering if the person was ever a `real` friend.","Particularly with social media, many bestow the status of friend on others with surprising speed and ease.","An enduring friendship is based on a similar life experience, and a shared value system.","One reason for ending the friendship or distancing yourself from it is growing apart in terms of interests."]},{number:74,ansser:3,question:"The origins of the 35 mm camera lie in the increasing availability of motion picture film stock during the early years of the 20th century. The 35 mm format was first used in Edison\u2019s Kinetoscope, a moving picture viewing device patented in 1891, and was later adopted as the standard film gauge by cinema-makers after 1896. ---- However, as the quality of the film improved, the potential virtues of small size and convenience of handling began to appeal to still camera designers.",choices:["Three Spanish inventors took out a British patent for a still camera using 35 mm format as early as 1908.","Unsurprisingly perhaps, the 35 mm camera gained enormous popularity across the world.","Sales of the cameras were limited by the outbreak of World War I in 1914.","The earliest 35 mm film was very slow and not ideal for still camera work.","The first 35 mm camera sold to the public was probably an American model developed in 1913."]},{number:75,ansser:2,question:"Children who do not master basic reading skills at an early age, specifically the ability to automatically decode new words and build vocabulary that leads to fluency, experience academic failure. ---- In other words, the curriculum focuses much less on teaching students to acquire the basic tools of literacy, and much more on using those tools to learn content, express ideas, and solve problems. At this point, students are likely to be given content textbooks in science and social studies and to read non-fiction for the purpose of gaining new information.",choices:["The readiness of children to read, in particular, has recently gained greater attention from educators.","Family environment is as important as the school environment in children\u2019s development.","By the third grade, learning to read has become reading to learn.","Children with good phonological awareness skills usually learn to read quickly.","They also need to learn book-handling skills such as orienting a book correctly."]}]},{directions:"For these questions, choose the irrelevant sentence in the passage.",questions:[{number:76,answer:1,question:"(I) As evidence has mounted about the threats that the Earth is facing, from rising temperatures and ocean acidification to deforestation and extreme weather, NASA has given priority to missions aimed at coping with the impacts. (II) NASA will be devising new technology to monitor earthquake-prone regions on the Earth via the satellites. (III) One of its newest satellites, a $916 million observatory called SMAP (for Soil Moisture Active Passive) was launched in January 2015. (IV) It was designed to measure soil moisture both by bouncing a radar beam off the surface and by recording radiation emitted by the soil itself. (V) In July 2015, the active radar stopped transmitting, but the passive radiometer is still doing its job, and its maps will help scientists forecast droughts, floods, and famines.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:77,answer:3,question:"(I) During the Renaissance, Italy was not a single, unified country. (II) It consisted of a patchwork of small states, each with its own history, government, and traditions. (III) Artistic styles varied significantly from region to region. (IV) The writings of Vasari, a painter and architect from Florence, helped establish the idea that Renaissance art originated in Italy. (V) Although Florence, Rome, and Venice were the main centres of artistic activity, skilled artists produced significant works in other areas as well.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:78,answer:3,question:"(I) When we listen to music, electrical waves in our brains synchronise to the tempo, but some people`s brains are better at synchronising to the beat. (II) Keith Doelling at New York University and his team recorded brainwaves of musicians and non-musicians as they listened to music. (III) While both groups could synchronise their brain waves to the rhythms, non-musicians struggled to synchronise to particularly slow music. (IV) Musical training might also help people with dyslexia \u2013 a difficulty with reading and writing caused by the brain`s inability to see the difference between some letter shapes. (V) Musicians can do this, not because of their natural talent, but because they have been trained to mentally subdivide music into shorter sections.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:79,answer:2,question:"(I) While urbanisation has been a notable characteristic of European society for centuries, the trend toward industralisation and urbanisation has accelerated phenomenally since World War II. (II) London and Paris, for example, have been major urban centres for centuries, but many other European cities have experienced rapid expansion of their populations only since the late 1940s. (III) The clustering of substantial populations into metropolitan regions is a distinctive demographic feature of Europe. (IV) In countries such as Italy and Spain, which were largely agricultural and rural before World War II, we find that many of their cities have now become home to large numbers of people. (V) For example, Madrid and Rome experienced remarkable increases between 1960 and 1990, in comparison with more moderate increases for most cities in the former West Germany, France, and the United Kingdom.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:80,answer:0,question:"(I) Although iron is the most common metal, it was the last to be used by people. (II) Humanity made a huge advance when people learned how to use metals. (III) Metal tools were easier to shape than stone ones, and could be mass-produced using molds. (IV) Unlike a stone axe, which was useless when broken, a copper or bronze one could be melted down and recycled. (V) Shiny metals, such as gold and silver, were also perfect materials for jewellery and coins.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]}]}]},{routeName:"2016-Spring",items:[{directions:"sorularda, cu\u0308mlede bos\u0327 b\u0131rak\u0131lan yerlere uygun du\u0308s\u0327en so\u0308zcu\u0308k veya ifadeyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:1,answer:3,question:"As we learn more about the neural mechanisms of intelligence, ---- for enhancing intelligence become more likely.",choices:["precautions","substitutions","necessities","prospects","permissions"]},{number:2,answer:0,question:"From the early 1800s scientists began to gather ---- amounts of data about marine life, paving the way for future knowledge about the importance of the planet`s oceans.",choices:["immense","predictable","equivalent","relevant","sustainable"]},{number:3,answer:4,question:"Reduction in cholesterol, body fat and oxidation is believed to help slow the ageing process ----.",choices:["doubtfully","reflectively","externally","obscurely","considerably"]},{number:4,answer:2,question:"Trade between people depends on a uniform set of weights and measures that can be used by both sides of the transaction to ---- that the amount obtained or handed over is correct.",choices:["disapprove","pretend","ensure","realise","estimate"]},{number:5,answer:1,question:"Despite its problems, the Space Shuttle has been a major step forward in spaceflight, ---- more than one hundred successful missions and pointing the way for future reusable spacecraft.",choices:["standing for","carrying out","running into","calling for","putting aside"]},{number:6,answer:0,question:"From the beginning of human history, innovators have experimented with all kinds of elements, from the ordinary to the invisible, trying to ---- new, improved materials.",choices:["come up with","do away with","cut down on","get along with","make up for"]}]},{directions:"sorularda, cu\u0308mlede bos\u0327 b\u0131rak\u0131lan yerlere uygun du\u0308s\u0327en so\u0308zcu\u0308k veya ifadeyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:7,answer:2,question:"With the development of agriculture, humans ---- to transform more and more extensively the environments in which they ----.",choices:["had begun / had been living","are beginning / were living","began / lived","have begun / were going to live","would begin / have been living"]},{number:8,answer:3,question:"Any student who ---- four years in high school or college attempting to learn a second language ---- the struggle of trying to memorize vocabulary, verb conjugation or tenses.",choices:["was spending / had to appreciate","spends / has to appreciate","had spent / should have appreciated","has spent / can appreciate","is spending / used to appreciate"]},{number:9,answer:0,question:"For many consumers from all over the world, the Internet is the first place ---- for useful information that ---- them about what they buy.",choices:["to look / will inform","looking / has informed","to have looked / informs","to be looking / is informing","having looked / will have informed"]},{number:10,answer:4,question:"In 1971, construction began on a vast hydroelectric project to dam the rivers that flow ---- James Bay and Hudson Bay, generating electricity ---- use in Canada and the US.",choices:["through / in","by / with","along / about","at / on","into / for"]},{number:11,answer:0,question:"By the middle of the 19th century, the growing acceptance that microbes can kill us had once more focused people\u2019s attention ---- a world only visible ---- a microscope.",choices:["on / through","to / upon","by / over","against / in","of / for"]},{number:12,answer:0,question:"Astronomers discover thousands of new members of the solar system every month, most of which, ----, are insignificant bodies like small asteroids or comets.",choices:["however","therefore","otherwise","accordingly","in other words"]},{number:13,answer:0,question:"---- sustainable technologies usually cost a lot of money to set up, they save money in the long run.",choices:["Even if","After ","Just as","Unless","Once"]},{number:14,answer:1,question:"With normal ocean waves, only the surface of the water body is in motion; a tsunami, ----, brings not only the surface into motion but lifts and then drops an entire water column in the ocean.",choices:["namely","though","for example","similarly","hence"]},{number:15,answer:4,question:"The basic principles of good diets are ---- simple ---- one can summarize them in just ten words: eat less, move more, eat lots of fruits and vegetables.",choices:["neither / nor","the more / the less","whether / or","such / as","so / that"]},{number:16,answer:3,question:"The henna, which may have spiritual significance in various cultures, is applied ---- different graphic rules, with different symbolic relations.",choices:["due to","except for","unlike","according to","prior to"]}]},{directions:"sorularda, as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327ada numaralanm\u0131s\u0327 yerlere uygun du\u0308s\u0327en so\u0308zcu\u0308k veya ifadeyi bulunuz.",text:"A genetically modified plant may produce specific proteins or other substances that have never before been a part of the human food supply. These substances have potentially negative side effects; for instance, they ---- as toxins or allergens. Accordingly, an extensive testing and approval process is mandated for foods of this kind, including individual ingredients and additives ---- whole foods. Approval is granted ---- the food is shown to be safe in accordance with scientific standards. This is accomplished by comparing the genetically modified product with its traditional ----. The long-term effects of the use of genetically modified plants ---- people and the environment have not yet been adequately determined.",questions:[{number:17,answer:0,question:"These substances have potentially negative side effects; for instance, they ---- as toxins or allergens.",choices:["may act","could have acted","were to act","will have acted","must act"]},{number:18,answer:4,question:"Accordingly, an extensive testing and approval process is mandated for foods of this kind, including individual ingredients and additives ---- whole foods.",choices:["in terms of","regarding","thanks to","despite","as well as"]},{number:19,answer:1,question:"Approval is granted ---- the food is shown to be safe in accordance with scientific standards.",choices:["though","only if","unless","as if","in case"]},{number:20,answer:4,question:"This is accomplished by comparing the genetically modified product with its traditional ----.",choices:["provision","consumption","management","distribution","counterpart"]},{number:21,answer:2,question:"The long-term effects of the use of genetically modified plants ---- people and the environment have not yet been adequately determined.",choices:["beyond","against","on","with","for"]}]},{direction:"sorularda, as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327ada numaralanm\u0131s\u0327 yerlere uygun du\u0308s\u0327en so\u0308zcu\u0308k veya ifadeyi bulunuz.",text:"Thousands of years ago, agriculture began as a highly site-specific activity. The first farmers were gardeners who grew individual plants, and they ---- the microclimates and patches of soil that favoured those plants. But as farmers acquired scientific knowledge and mechanical expertise, they enlarged their plots using standardized approaches ---- ploughing the soil and spreading animal manure as fertilizer to increase crop production. ---- the years, they developed better 26. methods of preparing the soil and protecting plants from insects, and eventually, machines to reduce the labor required. ---- in the 19th century, scientists invented chemical pesticides and used newly discovered genetic principles to select for more productive plants. ---- these methods maximized overall productivity, they caused some areas within fields to underperform.",questions:[{number:22,answer:2,question:"The first farmers were gardeners who grew individual plants, and they ---- the microclimates and patches of soil that favoured those plants.",choices:["brought in","paid for","looked for","kept on","took away"]},{number:23,answer:4,question:"But as farmers acquired scientific knowledge and mechanical expertise, they enlarged their plots using standardized approaches ---- ploughing the soil and spreading animal manure as fertilizer to increase crop production.",choices:["on behalf of","in the light of","on account of","in contrast with","such as"]},{number:24,answer:0,question:"---- the years, they developed better methods of preparing the soil and protecting plants from insects, and eventually, machines to reduce the labor required.",choices:["Over","For","In","From","Off"]},{number:25,answer:3,question:"---- in the 19th century, scientists invented chemical pesticides and used newly discovered genetic principles to select for more productive plants.",choices:["Being started","To start","Having been started","Starting","To have started"]},{number:26,answer:1,question:"---- these methods maximized overall productivity, they caused some areas within fields to underperform.",choices:["Given that","Even though","Just as","In case","Because"]}]},{directions:"sorularda, verilen cu\u0308mleyi uygun s\u0327ekilde tamamlayan ifadeyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:27,answer:2,question:"We will soon have to find new ways of living that do not harm the environment ----.",choices:["because researchers aim to make waste products less damaging to the environment","when humans waste an enormous amount of the Earth`s resources","if we continue using the Earth`s resources at current rate","while the habitats of some species have been largely destroyed by humans","although environmental organizations are trying to conserve the wildlife"]},{number:28,answer:0,question:"Many vitamins and minerals are necessary components of our diet ----.",choices:["unless they are consumed excessively","although they are basic fuels of life","but lack of vitamin E can cause skin diseases","while moderate levels will be beneficial","even if they help us stay healthy"]},{number:29,answer:0,question:"Cosmetics companies have started to remove parabens and other harmful chemicals from their products ----.",choices:["even though there is not much pressure from regulatory bodies to do so","when they experience no adverse effects on humans","even if a link between parabens and breast cancer exists","because most underarm deodorants do not contain parabens","although there is a long-running debate about the safety of parabens"]},{number:30,answer:2,question:"---- he is well known to future generations mostly because of his treasure-filled tomb, which was discovered intact in 1922.",choices:["After King Tutankhamun`s body was mummified and placed in a series of coffins","Although the grave goods accompanying King Tutankhamun to the afterlife tell much about daily life then","While King Tutankhamun had little opportunity to achieve greatness in his short life of 18 years","Because King Tutankhamun died from a fracture in his left leg that became infected with gangrene","When King Tutankhamun was still a child and under the influence of advisers"]},{number:31,answer:3,question:"NASA`s Kepler space telescope was launched in 2009 and stopped gathering data in 2013 after a mechanical failure ----.",choices:["whereas no input has been detected from it since it broke down","because during its construction the engineers worked meticulously to maximize its lifespan","so it searched for planets by measuring the levels in a star`s brightness","yet in its relatively short lifetime it has provided a wealth of discovery","since it has discovered a group of stars where each star has planets of its own"]},{number:32,answer:0,question:"Whereas the aeroplanes of the future were expected to cross oceans and continents as fast as possible in the 1980s ----.",choices:["we now focus on noise reduction, lighter and stronger materials, and lower fuel consumption","the race to develop new aircraft technologies is at least as intense now as it was 30 years ago","the first heavier-than-air machines to fly were kites, invented by the Chinese in about 1000 BC","the needs of aircraft travellers are very well-matched with the technological development of airlines","designers have improved the conditions of both the terminals and the neighbourhoods of airports all over the world"]},{number:33,answer:2,question:"To cope with the increasing number of tourists visiting Saudi Arabia ----.",choices:["investment in the tourism sector is not among the top priorities of the government","hotel managers say that the average stay for a tourist is between two and seven days","the government has outlined a plan to invest more money in its airports and transportation","officials have been concerned about the potential oversupply of hotels in the country","the country`s four main international airports handle most of the domestic air travel"]},{number:34,answer:4,question:"---- since scholars and researchers have an unrivalled understanding of potential drug targets in the development procedures of new medicines.",choices:["There is an increasing recognition from scientists that they need to work closely with companies that provide complementary expertise","The reason for the failure of alternative drugs in the market is their limited efficacy for their targets rather than purely safety","It is sometimes ignored by authorities that brilliant experts need to be chosen earlier in the development process by the companies","Academic institutions are falling short of engaging with leading drug companies at an earlier stage of a pharmaceutical development","Pharmaceutical companies are increasingly turning to collaboration with the academicians at the top ranking universities"]},{number:35,answer:1,question:"---- so as to maximise the amount of accurate information in hand.",choices:["The police often have the option of closing an investigation file","It is highly crucial for the police to interview eyewitnesses","It would be easy to identify someone with the help of closed-circuit television","One must realise how important it is to avoid identifying an innocent person as the criminal","The cognitive interview has proved itself to be more effective than other interview techniques"]},{number:36,answer:1,question:"Although the story of humankind and the peopling of the planet still holds many mysteries ----.",choices:["receding oceans are likely to expose ancient land bridges between continents","the most widely accepted theory states that modern humans came out of Africa","efforts to trace the diversification of animal forms by analyzing the change in DNA are premature","one of the earliest pieces of art found in Europe can be dated to 24,000 BC","no one knows where exactly the first agricultural villages appeared"]}]},{directions:"sorularda, verilen I\u0307ngillizce cu\u0308mleye anlamca en yak\u0131n Tu\u0308rkc\u0327e cu\u0308mleyi, Tu\u0308rkc\u0327e cu\u0308mleye anlamca en yak\u0131n I\u0307ngilizce cu\u0308mleyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:37,answer:0,question:"The notion of an algorithm, a procedure for arriving at a solution by a sequence of elementary steps, was also familiar to the ancient Greeks, as can be seen in Euclid`s algorithm used even today.",choices:["Bir dizi temel ad\u0131mla bir c\u0327o\u0308zu\u0308me ulas\u0327ma prosedu\u0308ru\u0308 olan algoritma kavram\u0131, O\u0308klid`in bugu\u0308n bile kullan\u0131lan algoritmas\u0131nda da go\u0308ru\u0308lebileceg\u0306i u\u0308zere antik Yunanl\u0131lar taraf\u0131ndan da bilinmekteydi.","Algoritma kavram\u0131, yani bir dizi temel ad\u0131mla bir c\u0327o\u0308zu\u0308me ulas\u0327ma prosedu\u0308ru\u0308, O\u0308klid`in bugu\u0308n bile kullan\u0131lan algoritmas\u0131nda da go\u0308ru\u0308lebileceg\u0306i gibi antik Yunanl\u0131lar do\u0308neminde de bilinmekteydi.","Bir temel ad\u0131mlar zinciri ile bir c\u0327o\u0308zu\u0308me ulas\u0327ma prosedu\u0308ru\u0308 olan algoritma kavram\u0131, O\u0308klid`in algoritmas\u0131nda da go\u0308ru\u0308lebileceg\u0306i u\u0308zere bugu\u0308n oldug\u0306u gibi antik Yunanl\u0131lar zaman\u0131nda da biliniyordu.","Bir temel ad\u0131mlar dizisiyle bir c\u0327o\u0308zu\u0308me ulas\u0327ma prosedu\u0308ru\u0308 olan ve antik Yunanl\u0131lar taraf\u0131ndan da bilinen algoritma kavram\u0131, O\u0308klid`in bugu\u0308n bile kullan\u0131lan algoritmas\u0131nda go\u0308ru\u0308lebilir.","O\u0308klid`in bugu\u0308n bile kullan\u0131lan algoritmas\u0131nda da go\u0308ru\u0308lebileceg\u0306i u\u0308zere antik Yunanl\u0131lar taraf\u0131ndan da bilinen algoritma kavram\u0131, bir dizi temel ad\u0131mla bir c\u0327o\u0308zu\u0308me ulas\u0327ma prosedu\u0308ru\u0308du\u0308r."]},{number:38,answer:1,question:"Reptiles and insects have no need to sweat because, unlike mammals, they do not need to maintain a constant body temperature.",choices:["Memelilerin sabit bir vu\u0308cut \u0131s\u0131s\u0131n\u0131 korumak ic\u0327in terlemeye ihtiyac\u0327lar\u0131 vard\u0131r fakat su\u0308ru\u0308ngenler ve bo\u0308cekler ic\u0327in ayn\u0131 durum so\u0308z konusu deg\u0306ildir.","Su\u0308ru\u0308ngenler ve bo\u0308cekler terlemeye ihtiyac\u0327 duymaz c\u0327u\u0308nku\u0308 memelilerin aksine sabit bir vu\u0308cut \u0131s\u0131s\u0131n\u0131 korumalar\u0131 gerekmez.","Memelilerin sabit bir vu\u0308cut \u0131s\u0131s\u0131n\u0131 korumak ic\u0327in terlemeleri gerekmektedir ancak su\u0308ru\u0308ngenlerin ve bo\u0308ceklerin buna ihtiyac\u0131 yoktur.","Su\u0308ru\u0308ngenler ve bo\u0308cekler, sabit bir vu\u0308cut \u0131s\u0131s\u0131n\u0131 korumalar\u0131 gerekmedig\u0306i ic\u0327in, memeliler gibi terlemeye ihtiyac\u0327 duymazlar.","Su\u0308ru\u0308ngenlerin ve bo\u0308ceklerin terlemeye ihtiyac\u0327lar\u0131 yoktur c\u0327u\u0308nku\u0308 memelilerde oldug\u0306u gibi sabit bir vu\u0308cut \u0131s\u0131s\u0131n\u0131 korumalar\u0131 gerekmez."]},{number:39,answer:4,question:"It is true that power nourishes all relationships, but only equally shared power can create happy individuals and satisfying marriages.",choices:["Bu\u0308tu\u0308n ilis\u0327kileri besleyen s\u0327eyin gu\u0308c\u0327 oldug\u0306u dog\u0306rudur, ancak mutlu bireyler ve tatminka\u0302r evlilikler, gu\u0308c\u0327 sadece es\u0327it olarak paylas\u0327\u0131l\u0131rsa yarat\u0131labilir.","Bu\u0308tu\u0308n ilis\u0327kilerin gu\u0308c\u0327le beslendig\u0306i dog\u0306rudur, ancak gu\u0308c\u0327 sadece es\u0327it olarak paylas\u0327\u0131ld\u0131g\u0306\u0131nda mutlu bireyler ve tatminka\u0302r evlilikler yaratabilir.","Gu\u0308cu\u0308n bu\u0308tu\u0308n ilis\u0327kileri besledig\u0306i dog\u0306rudur, ancak gu\u0308c\u0327 sadece es\u0327it olarak paylas\u0327\u0131ld\u0131g\u0306\u0131 takdirde mutlu bireyler ve tatminka\u0302r evlilikler yaratabilir.","Gu\u0308cu\u0308n bu\u0308tu\u0308n ilis\u0327kileri besledig\u0306i dog\u0306rudur, ancak mutlu bireyler ve tatminka\u0302r evlilikler sadece es\u0327it olarak paylas\u0327\u0131lan gu\u0308c\u0327le yarat\u0131labilir.","Gu\u0308cu\u0308n bu\u0308tu\u0308n ilis\u0327kileri besledig\u0306i dog\u0306rudur, ancak sadece es\u0327it olarak paylas\u0327\u0131lan gu\u0308c\u0327 mutlu bireyler ve tatminka\u0302r evlilikler yaratabilir."]},{number:40,answer:1,question:"C\u0327ok az insan renklerin, nesnelerin o\u0308zellikleri olmad\u0131g\u0306\u0131n\u0131 ancak go\u0308zlerimiz ve beynimizle etkiles\u0327en \u0131s\u0327\u0131g\u0306\u0131n farkl\u0131 dalga boylar\u0131n\u0131n bir sonucu oldug\u0306unu bilir.",choices:["Despite the fact that colours are not the property of objects, few people know that they are a result of different wavelengths of light that interact with our eyes and brain.","Few people know that colours are not the property of objects but a result of different wavelengths of light interacting with our eyes and brain.","Realizing that they are not the property of objects, few people know that colours are a result of different wavelengths of light that interact with our eyes and brain.","Colours are not the property of objects; however, few people know that they are a result of different wavelengths of light interacting with our eyes and brain.","Colours, which are not the property of objects, are known by few people to be a result of different wavelengths of light that interact with our eyes and brain."]},{number:41,answer:3,question:"I\u0307ngiliz posta sisteminin 1510 y\u0131l\u0131ndaki kurulus\u0327undan beri en bu\u0308yu\u0308k ve yegane yenilig\u0306i olan du\u0308nyan\u0131n ilk yap\u0131s\u0327kanl\u0131 posta pulu Penny Black, 1840 y\u0131l\u0131nda bas\u0131ld\u0131.",choices:["In 1840, the world`s first adhesive postage stamp, the Penny Black, was issued, and it is the greatest single reform of the English postal system since its establishment in 1510.","In 1840, the English postal system issued the world`s first adhesive postage stamp, the Penny Black, which is the greatest single reform since its establishment in 1510.","The Penny Black, which was issued in 1840 and became the world`s first adhesive postage stamp, is the greatest single reform of the English postal system since it was established in 1510.","The world`s first adhesive postage stamp, the Penny Black, which is the greatest single reform of the English postal system since its establishment in 1510, was issued in 1840.","The Penny Black, the world`s first adhesive postage stamp by the English postal system, was issued in 1840 as its greatest single reform since its establishment in 1510."]},{number:42,answer:2,question:"Sesinizi yu\u0308kselttirecek kadar c\u0327ok gu\u0308ru\u0308ltu\u0308ye uzun su\u0308re maruz kalma, kalp krizi oranlar\u0131n\u0131 yu\u0308zde 50 artt\u0131rabilmektedir, o\u0308zellikle bu hem is\u0327te hem de evde gec\u0327erliyse.",choices:["Being chronically exposed to loud noise and raising your voice can increase heart attack rates by 50 percent, especially if this is true at both work and home.","Chronic exposure to noise loud enough to make you raise your voice by 50 percent can increase heart attack rates, especially if this happens at both work and home.","Chronic exposure to noise loud enough to make you raise your voice can increase heart attack rates by 50 percent, especially if this is true at both work and home.","Being chronically exposed to noise loud enough to make you raise your voice, especially at both work and home, can increase heart attack rates by 50 percent.","Chronic exposure to loud noise can make you raise your voice and increase heart attack rates by 50 percent, especially if this happens at both work and home."]}]},{directions:"sorular\u0131 as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327aya go\u0308re cevaplay\u0131n\u0131z.",text:"Beneath a temple thought to mark the location of the Buddha`s birth, archaeologists may have discovered the physical roots of the religion: an ancient tree shrine that predates all known Buddhist sites. The archaeological record of Buddhism stretches back to the time of Ashoka, an Indian emperor who enthusiastically embraced the religion in the 3rd century BC and built many temples. The sage known as the Buddha though, probably lived about three centuries earlier. The remains of one of Ashoka`s temples lie at Lumbinini in Nepal, which many recognise as the Buddha`s birthplace. As part of his conservation work, Robert Coningham at Durham University, excavated below the temple foundations. He found evidence of pre-Ashokan stonework and, below that, signs of a timber structure that was radiocarbon dated to between 800 and 550 BC. When the surrounding soil was examined it was found to contain the remains of ancient tree roots, but was strangely free of the debris usually left by human occupation. This suggests that a tree grew at the centre of the wooden structure, and that the area around it was regularly cleaned, just as Buddhist tree shrines are cleaned today.",questions:[{number:43,answer:3,question:"It can be understood from the passage that the excavation below the temple at Lumbinini has ----.",choices:["located the remains of an ancient shrine where nothing was thought to exist","provided little evidence that the Buddha was actually born there","shown that Ashoka was the first emperor to follow the teachings of Buddhism","possibly revealed the very first tree shrine in the Buddhist religion","enabled archaeologists to make a previously unknown link between Ashoka a]nd the Buddha"]},{number:44,answer:2,question:"It is clearly stated in the passage that Ashoka ----.",choices:["lived during the same period as the Buddha","knew exactly where the Buddha was buried and built a shrine there","was a firm believer in the religon that the Buddha founded centuries earlier","dedicated his time to finding the actual birthplace of the Buddha","welcomed the Buddha to his empire to spread his religon"]},{number:45,answer:4,question:"The unusual thing about the soil around the timber structure was that it was ----.",choices:["full of dead organic matter","examined by previous excavators","contaminated by radiation","surrounded by ancient trees","without any human waste"]},{number:46,answer:3,question:"One can understand from the passage that over the centuries, Buddhist tree shrines have been ----.",choices:["built away from royal residences","protected by the warriors of the emperor","kept hidden under temple foundations","taken care of in a very similar manner","constructed of both timber and stone"]}]},{directions:"sorular\u0131 as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327aya go\u0308re cevaplay\u0131n\u0131z.",text:'The floods causing damage across much of central Europe are a sign of catastrophes to strike as the continent`s climate gets harsher. In the German town of Passau on 3 June 2013, waters rose to their highest level since 1501. At that time, the floods in Czech capital Prague were beginning to recede but Dresden, Germany, was preparing itself for the river Elbe to rise 5 metres higher than normal. "Several factors are responsible", says Ste\u0301phane Isoard of the European Environment Agency in Copenhagen, Denmark. "It was spring, so snow was melting from the mountains," she says. When two months of rain fell in two days, the water had nowhere to go because the ground was soaked. Climate change also causes heavier rainfall, and might be partly to blame. However, Isoard points out that bad land management is just as important. "In urban areas, there is less opportunity for water to infiltrate the soil. With more floods inevitable, Europe needs to adapt," Isoard says. Some work is already under way. Wetlands are being restored around stretches of the Danube. Green spaces like this can absorb extra water, making floods less severe. "Over the last 20 years, events like this have become more common," says Iain White of the University of Manchester in the UK. "Central Europe has improved its flood responses since 2002, but there comes a point where you can`t defend," he maintains.',questions:[{number:47,answer:4,question:"It is clearly stated in the passage that ----.",choices:["bad land management is especially responsible for devastating floods as in Passau","the rise in water levels in central Europe in 1501 was more alarming than that of 2013","waters from melting snow caused the river Elbe to rise 5 meters, resulting in great harm in Prague and Dresden","Prague was more vulnerable to harmful consequences of the flood than Dresden","central Europe should be ready for more severe floods as they seem unavoidable"]},{number:48,answer:1,question:"One of the strategies to cope with floods is to ----.",choices:["build on areas that are water-resistant","reconstruct wetlands that can take in more surface water","decrease the number of urban areas near rivers","redirect the water that results from melting snow","establish a system by which neighbouring countries inform each other"]},{number:49,answer:3,question:"One can infer from the passage that in central Europe ----.",choices:["extreme weather conditions have brought floods, yet there have not been any attempts to cope with them","the severity of the floods has dramatically decreased since 2002 thanks to the long-term solutions to prevent them","heavy rainfall will no longer pose a big threat because urban areas have become more prepared for a possible flood","there have been some precautions taken against the floods, but they are still not totally effective","climate change has had a more damaging effect than in any other parts of the world"]},{number:50,answer:2,question:"The primary aim of the author is to ----.",choices:["draw attention to how central Europe has recently been contributing to climate change","warn governments in central Europe to take immediate action to protect themselves against floods","give detailed information about the reasons for flooding in central Europe and how to deal with it","prove the claims made by researchers like Isoard and White about the floods in central Europe","exemplify the methods to make the soil absorb more water in central Europe"]}]},{directions:"sorular\u0131 as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327aya go\u0308re cevaplay\u0131n\u0131z.",text:"The influence of technology on diplomacy can be illustrated by leaked and misunderstood telegrams, which shaped the history in unexpected ways. For example, the 1917 Zimmermann telegram (sent by German foreign minister Arthur Zimmermann to the German Mission in Mexico and intercepted by the British) instructed the German representative to start negotiating Mexico`s entrance into World War I as a German ally by offering Mexico control of the US states of New Mexico, Utah and California after the war. The Zimmermann telegram was leaked at a time when the American public were still neutral and not ready to join World War I. It prompted the United States to join the Allied forces. The most illustrative case study of the influence of the telegraph on diplomacy was the 1914 July crisis that led to the beginning of the World War I. Telegraph messages were being sent between St. Petersburg, Berlin, Belgrade, Vienna, Paris and other countries involved in the conflict. However, there was little awareness of how to use the telegraph properly. The Russian czar sent a conciliatory note to Germany, but the German kaiser had already sent a note that was not conciliatory at all, thus creating communication confusion and mistrust that contributed toward escalation and ultimately war. A new technology coupled with human failure led to an unfortunate outcome.",questions:[{number:51,answer:4,question:"The Zimmermann telegram ----.",choices:["redefined the relationship between Germany and Russia","tried to convince the Mexicans that the British were to invade their country","caused the Mexicans to become suspicious of the United States","showed Germany`s intention to take control of the United States","provoked the US government into joining the war against Germany"]},{number:52,answer:1,question:"As it is stated in the passage, the 1914 July crisis ----.",choices:["was due to the conflict between Russia and Germany although both were capable of using the telegraph effectively","resulted from a confusion in understanding telegraph messages between the Russian and German heads of state","caused a breakdown in communication systems due to technical problems with the telegraph system","led to a general distrust of the telegraph system in the major countries involved in the conflict","arose because the telegraph messages could not be sent to other capitals such as Paris and Vienna"]},{number:53,answer:2,question:"One can understand from the passage that the Germans ----.",choices:["could not use diplomacy effectively in the past","were not skillful in using the telegraph compared with other nations","resorted to sending telegraph messages to form alliances and other diplomatic relations","relied on the British to intercept their messages","were against the development of technology in diplomatic relationships"]},{number:54,answer:4,question:"What could be the best title for the passage?",choices:["The Development of the Telegraph","The Use of Telegraph in World War I","The Telegraph and Its Various Uses","The Early Days of the Telegraph","The Impact of Telegraph on German Diplomacy"]}]},{directions:"sorular\u0131 as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327aya go\u0308re cevaplay\u0131n\u0131z.",text:"The Paleo diet is very popular these days. The Red Lady of El Miro\u0301n cave in northern Spain also ate the Paleo diet almost 19,000 years ago. But it was not a trend for her. A close look at the Red Lady`s teeth shows that the meat of the hoofed animals, such as red deer and mountain goat, made up about 80 percent of her diet. Fish seems to have made up most of the rest of her diet. If that sounds a little dull, fear not. Meticulous dental analysis reveals she also ate some starchy plant material, most likely to have been seeds, plus mushrooms, although probably in small amounts. Whether mushrooms were eaten for nutrition or for some other purpose is unknown. Could the diet revealed by this unique fossil from northern Spain make you live a longer, healthier life? Although the surviving bones of the Red Lady suggest she was healthy, her age at death was between 35 and 40. That may have counted as middle-aged for people who lived in Paleolithic times. Perhaps you had better stick to a balanced diet with five portions of fruit and vegetables a day.",questions:[{number:55,answer:1,question:"As it is stated in the passage, thanks to dental examinations, ----.",choices:["why the Red Lady was not able to live longer than 40 years was known","what the Red Lady`s diet included was revealed","when the Red Lady lived was brought to light","why the Red Lady`s diet depended heavily on meat was found","where the Red Lady lived in Spain was disclosed"]},{number:56,answer:1,question:"According to the passage, the diet of the Red Lady ----.",choices:["was made up of large portions","was mainly composed of meat","was followed by a great number of women in Paleolithic times","involved foods eaten especially for nutrition","shows that eating meat is important between the ages of 35 and 40"]},{number:57,answer:3,question:"It is implied in the passage that the Paleo diet ----.",choices:["puts emphasis on strachy plant materials","leads people to have a diet consisting only of meat","requires eating all types of food in small portions","does not have direct effects on living a longer life","allows people to live as long as the Red Lady"]},{number:58,answer:1,question:"The primary purpose of the author is to ----.",choices:["persuade the reader to start the Paleo diet to lead a long life","give information about the Paleo diet by providing the reader with an example","criticize the reader for not following the healthy Paleo diet","warn the reader against the consequences of following the Paleo diet","explain the reasons why the Red Lady died at such a young age"]}]},{directions:"sorular\u0131 as\u0327ag\u0306\u0131daki parc\u0327aya go\u0308re cevaplay\u0131n\u0131z.",text:"Hunger is known to increase food purchases, but Alison Jing Xu at the University of Minnesota and her team wanted to know if it also increased desire to buy non-food items. They asked 63 people to come to the lab with an empty stomach. Half were given a piece of cake to eat before all the volunteers were asked to examine a binder clip and decide how many they would like. Hungry participants asked for 70 percent more free clips than those who had just eaten. To find out if the same association held true for real purchases, the team had a look at the receipts of 81 customers leaving a department store that sold mostly non-food goods. Customers who were hungrier spent 64 percent more than the others. So, what is going on? When we are hungry, our stomach releases a hormone called ghrelin which acts on an area of the brain that makes people not only want to consume calories but also to seek out reward and motivation in buying other things. Jing Xu and her team suggest that consumers better feed themselves before they go shopping.",questions:[{number:59,answer:2,question:"It is stated in the passage that ----.",choices:["63 people who joined the lab experiment were given information about ghrelin beforehand","researchers intentionally increased the level of ghrelin of the participants with a slice of cake","participants who had eaten a piece of cake did not want as many binder clips as those who had not","the aim was to find out the effect of hunger on purchasing food items","some of the participants wanted to have more binder clips rather than a piece of cake because they were not feeling hungry"]},{number:60,answer:1,question:"For the real-life part of the experiment, ----.",choices:["81 hungry people were asked to shop at a department store","the receipts of the customers were checked to see the effect of hunger on purchasing","the research team reached contrasting findings for the lab participants and the department store customers","all customers who shopped at the department store were equally hungry","64 percent of the department store customers purchased non-food items"]},{number:61,answer:4,question:"It can be concluded from both experiments that ----.",choices:["shopping leads the stomach to release ghrelin more","food alone is not enough to motivate hungry people","spending money is not associated with extreme hunger","purchasing is rewarding for people who are not hungry","the effect of ghrelin is not restricted to food"]},{number:62,answer:3,question:"The study may make people aware that ----.",choices:["it is usually the needs that play a key role in how much money people spend when shopping","non-food goods do not attract people when they are hungry","taking part in lab experiments may change their previous shopping tendencies","shopping on an empty stomach might result in spending more money than intended","consumption of unnecessary calories may be demotivating to do shopping"]}]},{directions:"sorularda, kars\u0327\u0131l\u0131kl\u0131 konus\u0327man\u0131n bos\u0327 b\u0131rak\u0131lan k\u0131sm\u0131n\u0131 tamamlayabilecek ifadeyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:63,answer:1,question:"Defne:\n- Why have you been stirring your tea for so long? You`ve cooled it off faster.\nBeren:\n- ----\nDefne:\n- When you stir it, the molecules move faster. So, you quicken the heat loss.\nBeren:\n- Okay, next time I won`t stir my tea a lot.",choices:["What do you think can be done to reduce the heat loss?","What are you trying to say? I can`t see any relation between them.","As far as I know, the purpose of stirring drinks is to help the sugar dissolve in it.","I agree that it`s much more related to evaporation than to stirring.","Do you say the spoon takes away some of the heat during the stirring?"]},{number:64,answer:1,question:"Cahit:\n- It says here in the newspaper that although a woman`s core body temperature is generally higher than a man`s, her hands are usually a few degrees colder.\nAys\u0327e:\n- ----\nCahit:\n- It must be about women`s hormone levels and relatively smaller muscle mass.\nAys\u0327e:\n- That`s interesting! I`d never have thought of it that way.",choices:["Does this happen even in mildly cold situations?","What`s the explanation for this?","Are there any situations where a man`s hands get colder?","Don`t the blood vessels constrict when temperatures drop?","Have you also read anything about the contribution of blood circulation?"]},{number:65,answer:0,question:"Okan:\n- Recently, I`ve been sleeping far less than I normally do. Do you think this could be related to stress?\nSinan:\n- Well, we all have stress but how it affects us differs from one person to another.\nOkan: \n- ----\nSinan:\n- Probably. But I also know people who suffer from eating disorders due to their stress levels.",choices:["I think I`m one of those whose sleeping patterns are dramatically disturbed.","However, my body needs more sleep than many people because I work at night.","These days, I also have poor appetite since I can`t get sufficient sleep.","Do you mean lack of sleep has both biological and psychological reasons?","I agree. People who are self-employed tend to have less stress-related problems."]},{number:66,answer:3,question:"P\u0131nar:\n- I`m just back from the hospital. The doctor changed my medication and suggested more rest.\nHazal:\n- OK. But why do you look so depressed? It`s probably a good thing, right?\nP\u0131nar: - ----\nHazal:\n- So, you`re worried that your manager won`t be very happy with the news.",choices:["I guess so, but every type of medication has its side effects along with benefits.","No, it`s bad news because the new medication is not covered by my health insurance.","I don`t think so because I`m supposed to exercise more after work in the evenings.","I`m not sure. That means I`ll have to take more days off, so I`ll fall behind with my work.","It might work better, but I`m afraid it`s going to provide temporary relief."]},{number:67,answer:4,question:"Student:\n- ----\nProfessor:\n- They`re fixed three months before you`re born.\nYou can leave a mark on them with a cut, abrasion or acid, but they`ll grow back within a month.\nStudent:\n- What about aging?\nProfessor:\n- It doesn`t have such an effect, but it gets harder to scan your fingers or take a print from them.",choices:["Do all people throughout the world have different fingerprints?","How do they treat finger injuries without damaging one`s fingerprints?","Are fingerprints utilized in any fields other than forensics?","What`s the role of fingerprints in upcoming technological advances?","Do fingerprints change during our lifetime?"]}]},{directions:"sorularda, verilen cu\u0308mleye anlamca en yak\u0131n cu\u0308mleyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:68,answer:4,question:"The latest report from the UN\u2019s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change is more confident than ever that most of the warming of the past 60 years is humanity\u2019s fault.",choices:["The latest report by the UN\u2019s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change underestimated the role of humankind over the warming that occurred during the last 60 years.","A recent report by the UN\u2019s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change is the most convincing one up to now, proving man\u2019s responsibility for the warming that has taken place over the past 60 years.","The latest report from the UN\u2019s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change confidently proclaimed that humankind is partially to blame for the warming of the planet over the past 60 years.","A recent report by the UN\u2019s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change has confidently demonstrated that humanity must take responsibility for the warming of the planet in the last 60 years.","The latest report by the UN`s Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change is the most confident one so far to assert that mankind has been responsible for most of the warming over the last 60 years."]},{number:69,answer:3,question:"One should visit the theater not merely for the purpose of entertainment, but rather draw lessons from the play performed on stage.",choices:["The purpose of visiting the theatre is to be entertained rather than draw lessons from the play performed on stage.","Instead of entertainment, which is not the only intention of a play, one must acquire knowledge with the help of the play acted on stage.","Paying a visit to the theater must not be for entertaining ourselves; instead, we should understand the messages passed on by the actors.","Theaters should not be visited with the aim of entertainment alone; instead, one should learn lessons from the play acted on stage.","Drawing lessons from the play acted on stage rather than being entertained must be the sole reason for visiting the theater."]},{number:70,answer:2,question:"Scientists are struggling to understand the strange biology of Rafflesia, one of the world`s largest flowers, in case it disappears from the jungle.",choices:["It is a well-known fact that Rafflesia, one of the world`s largest flowers, will vanish from the jungle soon, which makes scientists interested in understanding its biology.","One of the world`s largest flowers, Rafflesia has started to disappear from the jungle; therefore, scientists are rushing to study the biology of this large flower.","There is a possibility that one of the world`s largest flowers, Rafflesia, may become extinct from the jungle, so scientists are working hard to comprehend its unusual biology.","Scientists have difficulty in understanding the complex biology of Rafflesia, which is one of the world`s largest flowers, as it is about to disappear.","It is strange that although Rafflesia, one of the world`s largest flowers, is vanishing from the jungle, scientists are still trying to understand its biology."]},{number:71,answer:3,question:"The notion that we might one day be able to communicate by thought alone has preoccupied scientists and science-fiction writers for decades.",choices:["Scientists and science-fiction writers have long been trying to demonstrate that people can actually interact by thought alone.","Scientists and science-fiction writers have long been thinking that one day people will be able to transmit their ideas not only by words, but also by thought.","Not only scientists but also science-fiction writers have long been endeavouring to find an answer to the problem regarding thought communication.","Scientists and science-fiction writers have long been considering the idea that one day it will be possible for people to transmit messages via thought only.","Scientists have already proven that people can communicate by thought alone, which has also been a popular theme for science-fiction writers for a long time."]}]},{directions:"sorularda, bos\u0327 b\u0131rak\u0131lan yere, parc\u0327ada anlam bu\u0308tu\u0308nlu\u0308g\u0306u\u0308nu\u0308 sag\u0306lamak ic\u0327in getirilebilecek cu\u0308mleyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:72,answer:2,question:"There are a lot of doubts and questions about how effective antidepressants are. Many professionals in the field of psychology claim that for drugs to work, we need `precision medication`. The aim of precision medication is to develop strategies that are best suited to each patient`s biological, psychological, and social profile. ---- For example, if you have a job, you may be more likely to respond to a specific type of antidepressants.",choices:["Studies of antidepressant response prediction continue with millions of dollars and generate data derived from neurophysiology and genetics.","Doctors can now use new technologies in neuroimaging to improve treatment that can produce better results.","Certain characteristics, such as socioeconomic factors, can predict how someone will respond to a drug.","We can understand from large clinical trials that antidepressants do not work as much as we expect them to on average.","We do not need big data studies on antidepressant response, as even finding out the complaints of a patient can provide doctors with sufficient information."]},{number:73,answer:2,question:"Ethnic groups can differ greatly in appearance, dress codes, cultural practices, and religious beliefs. ---- For instance, the Welsh and the English in the UK are most distinctive in terms of their accent and language. Speech style, then, is an important and often central stereotypical or normative property of group membership.",choices:["Therefore, communities that live in well-defined boundaries exhibit uniformity in the way they use language orally.","Yet, communication involves spoken and written languages and a rich mix of expressions which are contextualized by ethnicity and nationality.","Nevertheless, language or speech style is often regarded as one of the most distinct and clear markers of ethnic identity.","Besides, the nature of the power and status relations between ethnic groups in society is influenced by self-respect and pride.","In addition, ethnic groups that are high on status and have respectful jobs have high ethno-linguistic value."]},{number:74,answer:3,question:"Sons look to their fathers for support and example. They need to be instructed and inspired, but sometimes fathers cannot meet these needs of their sons. For example, Abraham Lincoln had little to learn from his father, Thomas. Abraham Lincoln and his father differed in almost every way. While Thomas could not understand reading as a passion, Abraham read every book he could get hold of. ---- Unlike his son Abraham, Thomas was unambitious and stubborn. Thus, when Abraham was a young adult, he turned to the heroes of the past generation for inspiration.",choices:["When fathers cannot inspire their children, they often search for father figures among their favourite teachers.","Abraham was not content with his life; therefore, at the age of 21, he left his parents` home and rarely saw his father again.","Thomas was a good father, as he always supported Abraham to read different kinds of books to gain different perspectives.","In addition to their intellectual differences, Thomas and Abraham were emotionally incompatible, too.","Besides, it was hard for Abraham to hide his reactions to the political and social events that occured when he was young."]},{number:75,answer:3,question:"There are some 100 billion galaxies in the observable universe, with about 100 billion stars in each of these galaxies. ---- In fact, there are more planets in the universe than there are sand grains on all the beaches of all the coastlines of all the continents. Yet, in all this immensity, there is only one place where we know there is life \u2013 the tiny, fragile blue dot we call Earth.",choices:["The reality is that finding life in remote planets will be very difficult and it will take quite a lot of time.","Many scientists are trying to explain the origin of the disparate bodies in the solar system.","Since one of Saturn`s moons has been found to have ice fountains, we should be looking more widely for alive bodies.","In recent years, we have discovered that there are probably more planets than there are stars.","It is possible to find some kind of life in space, but whether we can talk to it is a matter of debate."]}]},{directions:"sorularda, cu\u0308mleler s\u0131ras\u0131yla okundug\u0306unda parc\u0327an\u0131n anlam bu\u0308tu\u0308nlu\u0308g\u0306u\u0308nu\u0308 bozan cu\u0308mleyi bulunuz.",questions:[{number:76,answer:1,question:"(I) Decision-making theories assume that individuals evaluate the costs and benefits of various actions and pick the best alternatives in a fairly logical, reasonable way. (II) Judgements and decisions do not always follow strict rationality. (III) They choose the alternative that gives them the greatest rewards at the least cost. (IV) Decision-making involves weighing the advantages and disadvantages of possible alternatives and then adopting the best one. (V) In other words, the relative strengths of the advantages and disadvantages determine the final decision.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:77,answer:0,question:"(I) Some people choose not to consume meat as they think it comes from animals having consciousness just as we do. (II) Quite a few people wonder whether plants have a form of consciousness. (III) It is not really possible as plants do not have nerve cells, let alone a brain. (IV) Some plants can signal to each other, and to insects, using chemical messenger compounds, but that is quite different. (V) Human concepts such as emotion and self-awareness simply do not apply to plants.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:78,answer:4,question:"(I) By the 12th century an aristocratic class of warriors had begun to exercise great power throughout Japan. (II) Their original center, the military government of Minamoto, was located at the coastal town of Kamakura, near modern Tokyo. (III) Known as the Samurai, they dominated Japanese society for nearly 700 years. (IV) However, as power shifted from civil aristocracy to a new bureaucratic regime based on these provincial warriors, the Samurai became famous for offering security through military talent. (V) The ritual where the defeated warrior committed suicide with his own sword was also portrayed in the film The Last Samurai.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:79,answer:3,question:"(I) Bats live in caves to avoid danger and save energy. (II) Some species spend their daytime in caves while others hibernate there for the winter because caves provide optimal humidity, a stable low temperature, and few disturbances from light or noise. (III) Temperature is important because bats are warm-blooded but very small. (IV) Hibernation is a deep state of inactivity in which the animals` body temperature decreases. (V) Unlike many other mammals, bats let their internal temperature drop when they are resting, going into a state of decreased activity to conserve energy.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]},{number:80,answer:0,question:"(I) Although it was only in recent years that the 3D printing technology became good enough to produce more than prototypes, the very idea of printing in 3D is not new. (II) The 3D printing technology development has been so rapid and quick. (III) Nevertheless, 3D printers will hardly out-compete existing technologies, when it comes to the production of large quantities of consumer goods and machine parts. (IV) For a long time to come, the technology will probably be more suitable for customized goods, spare parts, minor quantity production, and products difficult to make in a conventional way. (V) But experts have no doubt that 3D printers will be increasingly used in many industries.",choices:["I","II","III","IV","V"]}]}]}]);var y=function(){h.a.initialize("UA-158180736-1"),h.a.pageview("/homepage");var e=b.map((function(e){return e.routeName}));return o.a.createElement("div",null,o.a.createElement(l.c,null,b.map((function(e,t){return o.a.createElement(l.a,{key:t,path:"/".concat(e.routeName)},o.a.createElement(g,{questions:e.items}))})),o.a.createElement(l.a,{path:"/"},o.a.createElement(c,{exams:e}))))};Boolean("localhost"===window.location.hostname||"[::1]"===window.location.hostname||window.location.hostname.match(/^127(?:\.(?:25[0-5]|2[0-4][0-9]|[01]?[0-9][0-9]?)){3}$/));s.a.render(o.a.createElement(r.a,null,o.a.createElement(y,null)),document.getElementById("root")),"serviceWorker"in navigator&&navigator.serviceWorker.ready.then((function(e){e.unregister()}))}},[[23,1,2]]]);
//# sourceMappingURL=main.787ca0bb.chunk.js.map